<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="64"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q2 2016Selection of industry features for the professional adviserSynaptic Risk Rating• Risk and suitability? It’s time to access the real thing • The Synaptic Risk Rating TableThe Synaptic guide to SIPPs• How to research and recommend SIPPs – Synaptic • Survival of the fittest, Abraham Okusanya• Contributions from AJ Bell, Ascentric, Standard Life,Suffolk Life, Zurich, TransactDue diligence and SuitabilityMake or break time for advisers?Inside...›› An investment proposition for advisers, built with advisers’ perspective -James Priday, P1 Investment›› Research results from FE - The changing world of financial advice, Mika-John Southworth›› The power of asset allocation - Justin Onuekwusi, Legal & General Investment Management›› Diversification - Currency is key - Ben Kumar, 7IM›› Scottish Widows Protect - Johnny Timpson›› Critical Illness - The life lottery the UK loves to play - Andrew Wibberley, Alea Risk›› Synaptic Webline new user interface unveiled - Stuart Carmichael, Synaptic Software›› Brit-in, Brit-out or Brit-ish? - Lee Oliver, TCF Investment]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Enjoy an easy life with WeblineBuying financial products online has never been easier with the help of the Synaptic Webline portal, which can be accessed forNot only can you compare hundreds of online products against each other, you can also apply online directly into the chosen providers extranet, reducing time and effort usually spent re-keying data.By applying directly from Synaptic Webline firms may be entitled to an extra 10% of additional commission –For more information call us on0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.ukApplying Online - The Myths and Facts• The cost for applying via Webline is exactly the same astrading with the Provider on their site.• Webline portal will take a cut of the plan commission due to the adviser.• Applying via Webline means the data from the quote is populated, avoiding double data entry.• Application process cannot be re-started from within Webline service.• The Providers treat the application in exactly the same way as an application coming in via their extranet.• Advisers are often entitled up to an additional 10%commission when applying from Webline into provider extranet.• The client data is not kept by Webline, the application is input directly onto the provider’s system.• There is no cost to you or the client for sending the application in via Webline.Free to existing customersthis could result in huge gainsyou could even earn more commissionFact MythFactFact MythFact FactFact]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[CONTENTSDon’t be a proposition in search of a market, 04 Mark Polson, Founder, The Lang CatThe power of asset allocation, Justin Onuekwusi CFA, L&G Investment Management08 Market Outlook, M&G Multi-Asset team, M&G Investments. 10The changing world of financial advice: key findings, Mika-John 12 Southworth, Director, FEDiversification – Currency is key, Ben Kumar, Investment 14 Manager, Seven Investment ManagerConnecting with your clients, Neil Cowell, Head of Retail Sales, 16 Vanguard Asset ManagementBrit-in, Brit-out or Brit-ish? Lee Oliver, Investment Researcher, 18 TCF InvestmentStart with the Why? Gareth Johnson, Head of Managed 20 Investment Services, Brewin DolphinThe Synaptic Guide to SIPPsWhy everyone loves a SIPP, Eric Armstrong, Product Marketing, 22Synaptic Software LimitedSurvival of the fittest bespoke SIPP Providers, 26 Abraham Okusanya, Principal, FinalytiQRetirement income: why the scale of your platform’s universe 28 matters, Jon Taylor, Managing Director, AscentricPensions Freedoms: using SIPP drawdown to support full 29 flexibility, Alastair Black, Head of Financial Planning Proposition,Standard LifeThe SIPP, Brian Radbone, Head of Technical, Transact 30 AJ Bell – from SIPP to full platform, Billy Mackay, Marketing 31Director, A J BellPension technical update - the extended definition of a 32dependant, Jessica List, Pensions Analyst, Suffolk LifeIs decumulation where the money is? 33Alistair Wilson, Head of Retail Platform, ZurichAn investment proposition for advisers, built with advisers’ 34 perspective, James Priday, Managing Director, P1 Investment Management LimitedWhy that fund for that client? Dan Russell, Managing Director, 36 Verbatim Asset ManagementWhere for defensive returns or sustainable income? John 38 Stopford, Head of Multi-Asset Income, Investec Asset ManagementRathbones Multi-Asset Portfolios, David Coombs, Head of Multi- 40 Asset Investments, Rathbone Multi Asset PortfoliosRisk and suitability? It’s time to access the real thing. 42 Eric Armstrong, Product Marketing, Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Risk Ratings TableSynaptic – finger on the pulse, Tiina Stephens, Operations 52Manager, Synaptic Software LimitedHow trends in healthcare will start a protection revolution, 54 Gwilym Morrison, Senior Analytics Manager, Royal LondonCritical Illness – the life lottery the UK loves to play, 56 Andrew Wibberley, Director, Alea RiskIncome protection - it’s time to think differently, 58 Justin Harper, Head of Intermediary Marketing, LV=Scottish Widows Protect, Johnny Timpson, Financial Protection 60 Market & Industry Affairs Manager, Scottish WidowsWe’ve improved: Synaptic Webline, Stuart Carmichael, Head of 62 Proposition, Synaptic Software Limited443Suitability - is it make or break time for advisers?Contact DetailsSynaptic Software Limited Fusion 1, Parkway,Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO157AASales: 0800 783 4477 www.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Hardmannaomi.hardman@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969What started as a trickle is now fomenting into something fiercer. The regulator has announcedits review of Suitability following the February publication of its recent TR16/1 report, after a few years of tinkering around the edges. A second golden age of due diligence?What makes this initiative different is the announcement that the regulator will be scrutinising firms on a large scale, so we will all be affected at some level; the 2015 file check exercisewill involve 700 firms, including 500 smaller firms. Some have made the cynical observation that the current initiative is a re3a0ction to political pressure from the NAO and Europe – but the implications are the same either way. It is time for everyone to get their compliance in order.The recent report TR16/1 quotes:“the poor quality of an advisory firm’s research and due diligence is one of the three root causes for poor consumer outcomes. The other two root causes are incorrect risk profiling and costs.”Research. Due Diligence. Risk Profiling. Costs. Welcome to the world of Synaptic! We have built a suite that delivers on these requirements. No other firm collects and verifies the data that you need to the extent that we do – and provides access to the leading risk engine (Moody’s).Our message is clear - there is no need to fear the reaper if you are protected by Synaptic, which in many cases will prove to be an investment very well made.Eric ArmstrongEditorThe Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all nights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4Don’t be a proposition in search of a marketMark Polson | Founder, the lang catMy thoughts recently have been turning to distinctiveness. Maybe it’s the changing of the seasons, maybe it’s getting older or something, but I’ve been feeling a certain ennui, a certain je ne sais quoi, about lots of what’s going on. I’ll put away the French dictionary now.Take the new breed of digital advice or digital investing services, for example. Like many of you, I enjoy hearing about new propositions which may or may not disrupt the market.I heard a good phrase from someone recently: ‘same dog, different kennel’. That’s aboutright for all the robo-advice services vyingfor attention (if not very much cash) at the moment. Most if not all of these services depend on their front end user experience to differentiate themselves. Sitting underneath is, and I am quoting here from Lord knows how many sites, ‘a basket of ETFs’.Now, ETFs are all jolly good, and if you livein America they’re available with minimal dealing fees for just a few basis points. Over here, though, the use case for them over passive mutual multi-asset funds like Vanguard LifeStrategy, BlackRock Consensus, Architas, AAP or even the passive MyFolio set is pretty unclear. We haven’t seen any investment evidence that any of the robos are performingbetter than these propositions. So what’s going on?My suspicion is that these propositionsare falling foul of the ‘single line of stock’ problem that plagues multi-asset providers on platforms. When you’re struggling to differentiate yourself anyway, giving yourself some kind of potential for out- (or under-) performing is probably irresistible. Niggling issues like fractional dealing, higher trading costs and so on are just part of the price you (or more properly the client) pays.But there’s safety in numbers, and you want to keep the costs down, hence a basket of ETFs, a dog and a kennel.To put it another way, who cares what restaurant you eat at when the menu is the same in each one?It all comes down to distinctiveness. Nutmeg is distinctive in a world of lookey-likey directplatforms. But the new wave all look pretty much like Nutmeg, to be honest. So what are we all doing here?I can’t help feeling that the explosion of robos (a robosplosion? Sorry) is a proposition in search of a market. We haven’t seen any sign yet that investors are flocking, and those who do invest (outside of staff, connections and friends) aren’t going all-in. It’s still early, but if the combined AUA of all the robo sector is over £250m, then I’ll be a monkey’s chunkies.The big problem here isn’t a funky logo,or a Shoreditch office address, or a nice website. It’s distribution. The robos haven’t got it – which is what is holding them back from accumulating major assets. The only way to get that is to get name awareness up there through a mix of PR, social media and advertising, relentlessly over weeks, months and years. That’s why you see Nutmeg at Victoria train station. It’s expensive, soul- destroying, thankless work. And it’s far from]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[5These propositions are falling foul of the ‘single lineof stock’ problem that plagues multi-asset providers on platforms.When you’re struggling to differentiate yourself anyway, giving yourself some kind of potential for out- (or under-) performing is probably irresistible.certain that name awareness will translate into trust, which will lead into investment.The truth is, in a heavily regulated environment, there’s only so much disrupting you can do. You have to behave in prescribed ways. You have to tell people what’s going on and what you’re doing with their money. You have to be ready to give it back to them when you want to. And all the rest of it.Step forward the big banks. RBS, Lloyds, Barclays and Santander all have their own fintech incubators, or lines into those incubators they think are worthwhile. The prize for these guys is plain to see. For example, Santander’s wildly successful 123 account now has 12m account holders, hundreds of thousands of whom are ‘premier’ customers with income or investments of over £100,000. It knows who they are, where they live, what they spend their money on and how much cash they’ve got in their accounts. Half the time it knows a lot more than that if you also have credit cards, mortgages or additional products with it.Whereas the robos, and indeed D2C platforms, have to go out and find clients, Santander and its ilk have them right there. The cost of distribution is a fraction of what others need to spend. They should be cleaning up. But will they?The strike against the banks is that no-one trusts them, and they’ve never got it right before.Taking the second point first, it’s undeniable that UK banks have had significant challenges finding their rear ends with both hands anda map. Despite having the world on a platter, they’ve always managed to snatch defeat from the jaws of victory. But all runs come to an end, and one of these guys is going to get it rightat some point. (In terms of who’s first, we’d be offering very short odds on Santander’s new self-directed service, which may be live as you read this).The first point is fascinating. A YouGov / Cambridge University study in 2013 found that only 7% of the UK adult population finds banks trustworthy. However, 24% would recommend their bank to a friend. I can imagine that conversation:‘Hi Mark! Can you recommend a bank? My one sucks.’‘Sure! Why not try The Bank Of Sorrow And Despair?’‘Great! You trust them? Do they suck less?’‘God no, I wouldn’t trust them as far as I can throw them and they’re awful.’ And so on.This disconnect is why the challengers findit hard to disrupt. It’s not inertia per se, it’sthe sense that the devil you know beats the one you don’t. People with money are quite attached to hanging onto it, and so gravitate to something they ‘trust’, where ‘trust’ means ‘have a base level of confidence in’ for our purposes. Sometimes a really attractive proposition can bust through that. The last one that managed was called Icesave and it didn’t turn out too well.So where does it leave us? In the absence of personal recommendation and experience,big wins. Scale wins. That’s why Standard Life has snaffled up AXA Portfolio Services and its Elevate and AXA Self Investor platforms. That’s why Hargreaves writes so much business. Distribution is everything. After a while it starts to have its own gravitational pull, and it gets harder and harder to disrupt.If you’re thinking of creating something new yourselves, that’s fantastic. But don’t bea proposition in search of a market. Don’t depend on reflexive reasoning. It’s almost impossible for you to mark yourself out from the crowd in terms of product offering, and price is also a poor determinant, as HL customers know.It has to be about distribution. Get that cracked, and the rest will follow.]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[8The power of asset allocationJustin Onuekwusi | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementLegal & General Investment Management’s (LGIM’s) Multi-Index Fund range is built on four key pillars. Last quarter we discussed the importance of maintaining client suitability. This quarter we explore the crucial role of active asset allocation.Active asset allocation is the keyAsset allocation, rather than stock selection, ultimately drives the risk, and therefore the returns, of a multi-asset portfolio. Academic studies have confirmed that more than 90% of an overall portfolio return is driven by asset allocation.The ‘active versus passive’ debate is now old hat. What matters most is meeting the client’soverall investment objective. A multi-asset solution that is active in its asset allocation carries a number of key benefits over other options such as model portfolios or static allocation multi-asset funds. This article outlines these benefits.Active vs. static allocationManaging the allocation of multi-asset funds dynamically means a portfolio can be adjustedin light of unfolding market conditions to help protect them from deteriorating prospects in one asset class or take advantage of improving conditions in another. LGIM’s Asset Allocation team uses a highly diversified ‘top-down’ approach, building portfolios from a rangeof positions across multiple asset classes. By exploiting such diversification across assets and time horizons, we aim to generate a smoother client outcome.The last decade has witnessed wars, geopolitical risks, market bubbles, an emerging Chinese superpower, a massive financial crisis and central bankers engaging in unprecedented monetary experimentation. This has resulted in a rise in correlations between and within asset classes. All this and more has brought top-down views to the top of the investing agenda.The figure shows how individual asset class performance has frequently moved fromtop to bottom and vice versa. The figure also shows that markets can follow trends. For instance, in a period with reasonable economic growth, such as 2004-2007, growth-sensitive]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[9assets like emerging markets do well. In a market downturn, such as 2008, these assets fall to the bottom. Static asset allocation, no matter how sophisticated, can never take account of these types of market movements.A manager that dynamically allocates across different asset classes can take advantage ofcould take on much more or less risk than those characteristics might imply, with the possibility of an unexpected outcome. For example, many strategic bond funds can take on significant high yield bond risk and yet within many risk tools these funds are modelled as being UK investment grade corporate bonds.managers then decide how to integrate these ideas into portfolios that meet the desired client outcome.A team of specialists collaborating to drive investor outcomesIndeed, we are humble enough to accept Yogi Berra’s undeniable truth – ‘It’s tough to make predictions, especially about the future’. For advisers, however, being dynamic in asset allocation is key to avoiding portfolio drift and managing risk, therefore ensuring long-term suitability with your clients’ attitude to risk.these opportunities, which can be crucial to enhancing investor returns and managing risk.In addition, a multi-asset solution which is static in its asset allocation can drift acrossrisk profiles over time, as the volatility of asset classes will change over time. For example, a multi-asset fund holding 60% in gilts today is a very different proposition than it would have been ten years ago given the current low yield environment. Investing in funds such as the Multi-Index Fund range, which is active in its asset allocation, should give you peace of mind that the chosen fund will consistently stay within a desired risk target and will not drift away over time.The risks of model portfoliosModel portfolio approaches can obscure the amount of risk within each component. For example, a model portfolio may stipulate an allocation in UK small-cap equities, perhaps based on the historical risk/return characteristics. However, the individual fundA unified active asset-allocation-focused, multi-asset solution, however, provides full line of sight to portfolio risk. It allows for portfolio adjustments, in light of market conditions,to maximise returns within the fund’s risk parameters. At the same time it avoids the type of portfolio drift that can occur with model portfolios, giving you assurance that the solution you have selected remains suitable.Collaborating to drive investor outcomesWithin LGIM, we place emphasis on in-house fundamental macroeconomic research. Our five dedicated economists initiate allocation decisions by concentrating and researching where they can add value with an economic view, where our views and models deviate from consensus and market pricing.Strategists take these fundamental economic views and consider them in light of factors such as valuations and positioning, in order to translate them into trade ideas. PortfolioThe value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise and investors may get back less than they invest. *Call charges will vary.Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Q0054188. 04/16. H0159220.1 Does Asset Allocation Policy Explain 40, 90 or 100% of performance? Roger G. Ibbotson and Paul D. Kaplan, Financial Analyst Journal, January/ February 2000.This is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons.Contact usFor further information about our Multi Asset FundsT / 0345 070 8684*E / fundsales@lgim.comW: lgim.com/multi-index]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[101M&G Multi Asset Team: Market Outlook 2016Our broad macroeconomic outlook has not changed in recent months. Although there has been a slowdown in global trade and manufacturing, especially in Asian and other emerging markets, data from most developed economies continues to improve, albeit slowly, and central banks remain supportive. Concerns over China, global economic growth and weak oil and commodity prices continue to feature in headlines, although less prominently than atthe start of this year. However, the low interest rate/low return environment persists and this magnifies the importance of generating returns from diverse sources across the global investment landscape.Volatility set to continueThe new year started much as 2015 finished – a continuation of the investor uncertainty and market volatility that had persisted since around the middle of the previous year. Headlines about impending recessions, plunging commodity prices and slowing economic growth sent investors fleeing for perceived ‘safe havens’, such as government bonds and cash.However, interest rates and mainstream government bond yields are very low – even negative in some cases (see figure 1). In our view, this means these assets are not as ‘safe’, or risk-free, as investors would like to believe. We believe that it is important to think carefully about where the real risks are, and not to confuse volatility with risk. Investors should be aware that a degree of risk can be useful, even essential, in generating attractive returns, so long as sufficient compensation is paid for taking that risk.Over the first quarter of 2016, the actionsof central bankers, once again, captivated investors. The European Central Bankwent beyond market expectations in its announcement of further economic stimulus. Federal Reserve Chair Janet Yellen was also dovish in her plans and committed to further raise US interest rates only cautiously. These developments seemed to boost investor sentiment and since mid-February, there was something of a rebound in equity markets and risk assets in general. Nonetheless, we expect turbulence across asset classes to persist for some time yet.These are certainly interesting times to be an investor. So rather than indiscriminately avoid all ‘risk assets’, it might be easier to accept that volatility remains and consider looking at ways of managing risk in pursuit of better returns.Fundamentals are mixed, but still encouragingNaturally, the recent rising and falling of stockmarkets has provoked questions about how best to navigate today’s uncertain global economic environment. As always, we are looking at all this volatility in the context of fundamentals.We maintain a broadly positive aggregate global outlook, but acknowledge that the fundamental economic picture is mixed. There are some genuine risks to be mindful of, especially in Asian and other emerging markets. However, thus far, we have not seen this affecting other parts of the global economy.The fact is that there has been a slowdown in global trade and manufacturing, especially in Asia and several other emerging countries.Figure 1: Are ‘safe havens’ really safe? Figure 1: Are ‘safe havens’ really safe?14% 12% 10% 8% 6% 4% 2% 0% -2% -4%Source: Datastream, Bloomberg, 31 March 2016. World equity proxy is MSCI World; cash proxy is EURIBOR 3 months; world government bond proxy is The BofA Merrill Lynch Global Government Index. All data is inflation-adjusted.World equityWorld government bondsEuro cashReal yieldsSource: Datastream, Bloomberg, 31 March 2016. World equity proxy is MSCI World; cash proxy is EURIBOR 3 months; world government bond proxy is The BofA Merrill Lynch Global Government Index. All data is inflation-adjusted.]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11Figure 3: Rapid changes in asset priceThis has dragged down corporate profits and that is something we are watching closely. Other issues are the dependency on the oil price across emerging markets and the lack of areas with good earnings growth.It is, however, worth noting that it is only certain segments that are experiencing slowing growth. For example, as shown in figure 2, in the US, most industrial sectors are growing steadily, while the collapse in the oil price is weighing on the oil & gas industry.Source: M&G, Datastream, 18 April 2016across global equity markets in the early part of 2016 – not just those directly related to problems with China and the oil price – suggested investors had a knee-jerk, rather than a considered, response to volatility.In sum, we think it is important not to be overly distracted by short-term market movements, despite anxieties about volatile asset and commodity prices, as well as low interest rates and uncertainty surrounding Brexit.Within emerging markets, many investors are debating whether now is the time to take advantage of the current economic weaknesses and invest. Valuations are indeed looking rather cheap, so we are currently monitoring the situation carefully for any investment opportunities.However, our preference remains for selected developed market equities.We still believe the equity risk premium remains one of the mainvaluationanomiesobservable.Taking advantage of these risk premiums is justone of the ways we are generating potential returns – a particular effort of ours within the current low interest rate environment.Another way we are trying to combat lowinterest rates is by investing in ‘unloved’ areas of credit, for example, BBB rated corporates and the mining sector. Although we still believe that mainstream government bonds are unattractive, we are holding someperipheral European and emerging market bonds. It cannot be denied that uncertainty is ongoing and sentiment therefore remains fragile. This means, even while maintaininga positive economic outlook, we expect a considerable degree of turmoil to persist across financial markets over the period ahead.However, in our view, this should not be confused with genuine risk, and may actually present some compelling investment opportunities.That is why genuinely and carefully diversified multi-asset funds that have the flexibility to respond to rapidly changing environments might be best positioned to navigate the turbulence ahead.M&G April 2016For Investment Professionals and Professional Investors only. Not for onward distribution. No other persons should rely on any information contained within. This information is not an offer or solicitation of an offer for the purchase of shares in any of M&G’s funds. For Switzerland: Distribution of this document in or from Switzerland is not permissible with the exception of the distribution to Qualified Investors according to the Swiss Collective Investment Schemes Act, the Swiss Collective Investment Schemes Ordinance and the respective Circular issued by the Swiss supervisory authority (“Qualified Investors”). Supplied for the use by the initial recipient (provided it is a Qualified Investor) only. This financial promotionis issued by M&G Securities Limited (registered in England 90776) and M&G International Investments Ltd. Both are authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority in the UK and have their registered offices at Laurence Pountney Hill, London EC4R 0HH. M&G International Investments Ltd is registered in England, No. 4134655. It has a branch located in France, 6 rue Lamennais, Paris 75008, registered on the Trade Register of Paris, No. 499 832 400 and a branch in Spain, with corporate domicile at Plaza de Colón 2, Torre II Planta14,28046,Madrid,Spain,registeredwiththeCommercial Registry of Madrid under Volume 32.573, sheet 30, page M-586297, inscription1,CIFW8264591B andregisteredwiththeCNMVunder the number 79.This financial promotion is further issuedby M&G Investments (Hong Kong) Limited. Office: Suite 08, 20/F One International Finance Centre, 1 Harbour View Street, Central, Hong Kong. For Hong Kong only: If you have any questions about this financial promotion please contact M&G Investments (Hong Kong) Limited. For Switzerland, the financial promotion is published by M&G International Investments Switzerland AG, Talstrasse 66, 8001 Zurich, authorised and regulated by the Swiss Federal Financial Market Supervisory Authority. The Portuguese Securities Market Commission (Comissão do Mercado de Valores Mobiliários, the “CMVM”) has received a passporting notification under Directive 2009/65/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council andthe Commission Regulation (EU) 584/2010 enabling the fund to be distributed to the public in Portugal. M&G International Limited is duly passported into Portugal to provide certain investment services in such jurisdiction on a cross-border basis and is registered for such purposes with the CMVM and is therefore authorised to conduct the marketing (comercialização) of funds in Portugal. 122802_133404Figure 2: Growth across all but one sector...Source: Datastream, Federal Reserve, 15 February 2016Nonetheless, there is good news to befound, especially in developed markets and particularly the labour market. There hasbeen a pick-up in wages in many areas, which suggests improving prospects in personal consumption and retail spending. This, combined with lower energy costs, could provide an economic boost as consumers might be more likely to spend than save. So, while market fundamentals have been moving aroundabit,westillbelievethatthecurrent data is encouraging and we have used this to shape our portfolios.Navigating uncertaintyGiven how fragile sentiment seems to beat the moment, navigating this uncertain environment will undoubtedly present challenges that will require rational analysis, emotional fortitude and patience. As we can see from figure 3, asset prices have been volatile. The sudden and dramatic sell-off]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12The changing world of financial advice: key findingsMika-John Southworth | Director | FEFE has built an influential position in the UK adviser market, with 82 per cent of the UK’s top advisers using our products and services to inform their research and fund selection. For the first time, we have decided to use this unparalleled reach to conduct a survey to better understand the state of the adviser industry.We set out to get a better understandingof how advisers have been impacted by regulation, what their investment approaches look like, which funds are catching their attention, how they are managing risk and what are they most worried about. Our hope is that by better understanding the advisers, the market will be in a stronger position to develop products and services, communicate with them effectively and ultimately help them to make better investment decisions. The report comprises data and surveys from nearly 190 UK advisers.The financial advice sector is a broad and diverse community, with no set model for making fund selections that could be described as typical. Years of regulatory pressure onfirms to improve their investment selection processes is taking effect, but advisory businesses are responding to this challenge in different ways. Intermediaries are still in the process of evolving their value propositions,working out the parts of the value chain in which they can deliver, the parts of the advice process for which they feel comfortable taking responsibility, and the ways they can both manage and harness the threat and opportunity of new technology.What seems clear from this report is thatthe industry’s drive towards increased professionalism will continue. Whether a decade from now the various of approaches highlighted in this report still exists remainsto be seen, but it is likely that a diversity of approaches will still operate. The trend towards advisers increasingly outsourcing investment decision making to external providers looks set to continue. This will leave many advisers focusing on the increasingly valued and respected area of pure financial planning.Adviser business modelsAdviser business models are many and varied – a mixture of in-house or external modelportfolios, recommended fund ranges they have created themselves, discretionary fund managers, and multi-asset and multi-manager funds. While the delineation between financial planning and investment advice is becoming clearer, a number of advisers are doing both, while some are outsourcing. Approaches to client segmentation differ wildly from firm to firm, as do approaches to income drawdown minimum.Understanding and managing riskAdvisers are confident in their ability to manage risks, although they are less confident their clients can understand risk, a state of affairs that we believe highlights a potential lack of suitability of product recommendation and also a regulatory risk to advisers.Another area of potential regulatory risk highlighted in this report is the finding that some firms are maybe shoehorning all their clients into a single proposition, blending]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[13Our hope is that by better understanding advisers, the market will be in a stronger position to develop products and services, communicate with them effectively and ultimately help them to make better investment decisions.together multiple solutions that are meantto be standalone investment strategies, and displaying a lack of awareness of the extentto which selected investments are performing against their risk parameters. Advisers may be adopting this approach because they believe doing so is the best solution given the products available to them. Alternatively they may be doing so because they think it demonstrates that they are adding value. However, this area will require us to further investigate - to get the full picture of how suitability is assessed in these situations.TechnologyInterest in new technology, in particular digital advice and so-called ‘robo-advice’ solutions,is still limited to a minority of innovators and early adopters, but most advisers do appreciate they will have to introduce new technology to remain competitive. However, there appearsto be a growing recognition amongst advisers that technology can and should form a core part of the adviser’s business proposition. Many advisers recognise that adoptingnew technology gives them a competitive advantage.Investment TrendsTrends in fund selection are not limited to the same old big names, and we have found that advisers engaging with a truly diverse array of investment management companies to meet their clients’ portfolio needs. A full list of trends is below.Key trends- There is no typical way for firms to select investments for clients. Firms are using a mixture of in-house or external model portfolios, self-select fund ranges, discretionary fund managers, and multi- asset and multi-manager funds.- Advisers are overwhelmingly positive about the prospects for their own business.- Macroeconomic factors are advisers’ biggest fear, with nearly half citing the next financial crisis as a moderate or significant risk to their business. Clients eroding their drawdown pot is their second biggest fear.- Only a small number of advisers see regulatory action against unsuitable product recommendations as a risk to their firm, despite FCA concerns of widespread suitability issues.- Advisers are confident in articulating risk and volatility, but there is a mismatch when it comes to confidence in their clients’ ability to understand what they have said.- Many advisers do not know the proportion of risk-targeted funds in their portfolios that are meeting their targets.- Advisers see provider multi-asset drawdown vehicles as high risk.- Drawdown minimums have fallen, with more advisers accepting pots representing the entirety of an individual’s retirement funding of £30,000 to £50,000- A number of advisers are putting all their clients’ assets into a single investment proposition.- A large proportion of advisers use a single model portfolio service provider.- A majority of advisers combine model portfolios with other investment approaches for the same client, and a large number blend multi-asset or multi- manager funds.- A small percentage of advisers plan a digital advice launch within 12 months.- 24/7 client web access to portfolio data is seen as essential to remaining competitive- Advisers are shifting portfolios towards UK and European equities, and away from Gilts, corporate bonds and emerging markets.- Advisers are selecting funds from a phenomenally diverse range of investment houses.Contact detailsT / 020 7534 7661E / mika-john.southworth@financialexpress.netFE, 2nd Floor, Golden House,30 Great Pulteney Street, London, W1F 9NN United Kingdomwww.financialexpress.net]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[14Diversification – currency is keyBen Kumar | Investment Manager | Seven Investment ManagementThe idea behind diversification is quite simple. It is the fundamental principle behind multi-asset investing (which 7IM is a firm believer in). Most investors have embraced it in one form or another – spreading your investments across companies, sectors and geographies reduces the likelihood of a one chance event affecting all of your holdings. An earthquake in California might hurt Silicon Valley-based tech stocks, but have no impact at all on German bonds or the price of industrial copper.The above appeals intuitively to almost everyone, and there are very few investors now, whether advised or independent, who own a concentrated portfolio of stocks. The famous exception is Warren Buffet, who calls the process “di-worse-ification” as it gets in the way of really getting to know a company’s merits. Having said that, even the Sage of Omaha admits that for 99.9% of people (i.e. unless you are Warren Buffet), broad and cheap tracker funds are the best investment.So far so good. Yet many investors overlook a major factor in their return – the impact of foreign currency exposure. It seems screamingly obvious, but in order to investabroad, you have to convert your Sterling; before buying a share in a US company, you first need the Dollars to do so!Suddenly, along with exposure to the share price, there are changes in exchange rates to consider – something which hugely increases the complexity of a portfolio. Imagine owning a single UK company – let’s say Tesco. Adding a holding in something like BP means there are two sources of return, depending on the performance of the two shares. If we then add a position in Apple, we now have to consider the share price movements of the three stocks plus the movement in the Dollar/Sterling exchange rate. Buying another internationalequity such as Volkswagen (VW) adds another two moving parts to the equation – VW’s price plus the Euro movement.Some academics argue that over time, currency fluctuations tend to even out, which may well be true over decades (although there is some doubt about even that broad a statement). In the real world though, failing to take currencies into account can change the whole perspective on whether an investment was successful or not.Looking at Japan over recent years provides an excellent demonstration of the above. In December 2012, Shinzo Abe became Prime]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[15Many investors overlook a major factor in their return – the impact of foreign currency exposure.Minister, winning a landslide election on a platform of structural reform and economic growth. This was great for the equity market, with the Tokyo Price Index of Japanese companies rising 70% over the following two years.yet after adjusting for currency they would have been better off just buying their own local market!Obviously, foreign currency can rise rather than fall too – over the course of the 2008 crisis, theThe main takeaway should be that when diversifying your investment portfolio, it is important to understand ALL of the additional risk that comes with such a move. Havingan additional, ignored variable can turn good decisions into bad ones in a very short space of time.When diversifying your investment portfolio, it is important to understand ALL of the additional risk that comes with such a move.However, one of the stimulus measuresthat Mr Abe introduced was a loosening of monetary policy, which drastically weakened the Yen. For a Sterling investor, this meant that the 70% return was reduced to 27%. Over the same period, the FTSE 250 index of mid cap UK companies returned 37%. So a UK investor may have correctly identified the growth in the Japanese economy and invested accordingly,Dollar rose by more than 30% against Sterling, so any US equities massively outperformed their UK equivalents.The point of the above discussion is not to argue for or against foreign currency exposure - there is no consensus in the financial world as to the correct approach (arguably having the ability to do either is the ideal option).NotesSeven Investment Management LLP is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Member of the London Stock Exchange.Registered office: 55 Bishopsgate, London EC2N 3AS. Registered in England and Wales No. OC378740.The value of investments may fluctuate in price or value and you may get back less than the amount originally invested. Past performance is not a guide to the future.The investment service may not be suitable for all recipients and if you have any doubts you should contact your investment adviser.Ben KumarInvestment ManagerFor more information call 0207 760 8777or visit www.7im.co.uk]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[16Connecting with your clientsNeil Cowell | Head of Retail Sales | Vanguard Asset ManagementWhy it’s more important than ever to build long-term relationshipsThe financial advice landscape has been transformed in recent years.We’ve seen major changes in regulation, technology and access to information. One effect of these developments is that an adviser’s ability to create a successful and lasting practice more than ever depends on the quality of client relationships.the coming year, client touch points have a simple objective: to ensure a client never asks themselves “Has my adviser forgotten about me?” If a client has no reason to ask that question, they are far more likely to feel looked after and understood.What if you have nothing new to say?It doesn’t matter if you have nothing new to discuss relative to the specific account. Ask about the client. The purpose of reaching out to clients isn’t to reinforce the value of your investment strategy, but, to build a relationship.It also doesn’t have to be lengthy. Consider the difference between a 30-minute conversation every six months and a 10-minute chat every two months. Frequency is more important than duration.Listen to the clientTalking less and listening more to what your clients say can have a positive effect on your relationship with them, leaving them feeling understood. Information gathering doesn’t have to stop after the first meeting.Industry-wide research confirms this shift. For example, in 2014 Vanguard worked with a US- based independent research firm Sprectrem which found that affluent and high-net-worth investors gave more weight to communication, trustworthiness and transparency than to fees and performance when deciding whether to hire or fire an adviser.So how do you deepen client relationships?Reach out to clients more oftenOne of the simplest changes you can maketo improve relationships with your clients isto reach out to them more often, increasing the number of client touch points. Research reveals a direct, positive correlation between the frequency of adviser contact and the level of client satisfaction. In the Vanguard-Spectrem study, the most striking difference in reported satisfaction appeared between clients who were contacted at least quarterly and those who were contacted semiannually or less.1While annual client meetings are likely to focus on investment activity and expectations for]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[17Whether you simply reach out more often, cultivate deeper discussions or initiate relationships with clients’ families, the key to more meaningful relationships is honest conversation.Maintaining curiosity and interest in your clients’ lives means you’re more likely to have conversations that reveal additional client needs, leading to greater opportunities.For example, Spectrem found that affluent clients want to have deeper discussions,even if they are difficult. Yet both clients and advisers are generally reluctant to initiate these important, yet potentially sensitive, topics:1Are clients prepared for potential long-term medical care needs for themselves or family members? Is the client or a loved one showing signs of dementia? Will clients’ heirs be prepared for a sudden inheritance?Connect with clients’ familiesConnecting with clients’ families is another simple, yet critical, way to strengthen relationships and expand your practice. Some advisers resist pursuing younger clients because most millennials have yet to accumulate significant assets, and they tend to have different expectations and styles of communicating.However, taking time to develop connections with the children and grandchildren of clients – without being intrusive or overly familiar, of course – offers multiple benefits. In the nearterm, you may gain stronger relationships with current clients. Helping the child or grandchild of a client with something simple can create a foundation for a substantial client relationship in the future once he or she has accumulated assets.Cultivating family relationships doesn’t have to be time-intensive. Maintain periodic touch points with family members by offering appropriate education as they move through the stages of life. Potential topics include getting the most out of retirement, combining finances in marriage, funding school or university, housing and understanding the financial aspects of caring for elderly relatives.Use technology to get the most out of client relationshipsWhile personal contact with clients is the best way to enrich your relationships with them, technology can also help you reach out to clients little and often, as well as build new contacts. Your presence online is known as your digital footprint – all the information that can be found about you online. It’s important to shape this as much as possible – after all, it’s likely to be the first thing that will be found if anyone searches for you online. Make sure your website is up to date and complete and thenpick one or two social media platforms to help amplify your web presence (while of course being aware of any regulatory constraints).The power of conversationWhether you simply reach out more often, cultivate deeper discussions or initiate relationships with clients’ families, the keyto more meaningful relationships is honest conversation. By giving clients the opportunity to talk openly about their goals, concerns and families, you can create a deeper connection, which is more likely to lead to loyalty over the long term.1 Spectrem Group, in partnership with Vanguard, 2014. The affluent investor: Insights and opportunities for advisers. Valley Forge, Pennsylvania: The Vanguard Group, Inc.This information is directed at professional investors and should not be distributed to, or relied upon by, retail investors. It is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments.This information is designed for use by, and is directed only at, persons resident in the UK.The opinions expressed in this article are those of individual author and may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Limited.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.© 2016 Vanguard Asset Management, Limited. All rights reserved.]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[18Brit-in, Brit-out or Brit-ish?Lee Oliver | Investment Researcher | TCF InvestmentKnown knownsWe know that in the event of a leave voteon the 23rd June David Cameron, along with high-level EU representatives such as Donald Tusk, president of the European Commission, have attempted to dismiss a second roundof negotiations following the referendum. The Prime Minister will instead invoke Article 50 of The Treaty of Lisbon, kick-starting the UK’s minimum two year divorce process from the EU where, at the end of it all, the EU will offer the UK a “take it or leave it package” upon which the UK parliament will have little influence. This will have the effect of injecting more uncertainty into the marketplace.During this period of uncertainty, it would be reasonable to say that the UK and European equity / bond markets are likely to experience greater levels of volatility and lower valuations in the short term. While sterling is also likely to exhibit further volatility and lower valuations, having hit a 7-year low during February 2016.Less well knownsThe long-term effects being simply unknown and near impossible to quantify. The argument often feels like more of a political argument than an economic one as campaignerscontinue to battle over issues such as immigration, national identity and regaining total control of policy-making.When focusing on these issues, leave campaigners needto be conscious they don’t underestimatethe effects of what we don’t know i.e. the short-term effects of uncertainty, the easeasset manager DoubleLine Capital, believesa Brexit is simply not going to happen. The cost of hedging against a fall in the pound has risen sharply and Mr Gundlach believes that “investors are being foolish pushing up the cost of such insurance.” Conversely, echoing Mr Carney’s comments, David Coombs, Head ofDuring this period of uncertainty, it would be reasonable to say that the UK and European equity / bond markets are likely to experience greater levels of volatility and lower valuations in the short term.of re-negotiating existing deals with Europe, the extent of de-regulation that the UK might pursue and the ease of negotiating free trade agreements with the rest of the world, amongst other things.The repercussions from a Brexit are just so difficult to predict, so should investors be focusing on the more perceptible issues? For example, Jeffrey Gundlach, founder of theMulti-Asset Investment at Rathbones believes a Brexit is “The biggest macro-risk affecting their strategy.” Of course the significance of the risk that a Brexit might pose will, to some extent, depend on the portfolio in question. But one thing is clear - the risk is substantial because it is a step into the unknown. As the saying goes “The Devil you know is better than the Devil you don’t.”]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[19The most concerning issue for those in the financial services industry is likely to be the loss of the single market and the ability for EU member states to “passport” their services to other parts of the EU without the need for further authorisation.The most concerning issue for those in the financial services industry is likely to be the loss of the single market and the ability for EU member states to “passport” their services to other parts of the EU without the need for further authorisation. A significant proportion of UK exports are derived from financial services, some of which may be lost in the event of a Brexit. There is a risk of some of the large financials choosing to relocate portions of their business due to the inability to access the single market, using Britain as a base to sell into Europe, but this will ultimately be determined by post-Brexit arrangements.Known unknownsIt is likely there will be a negative effecton GDP post-Brexit although the extentand shape of the decline will once again be dependent upon the short and medium-term effects of uncertainty and the longer term trade negotiations.We also know that the fundamentals stay the same regardless. There are too many unknowns in question to produce credible economic models for a Brexit. It’s a nil-sum game, whether we stay or leave. So for advisers and investors alike much can remain unchanged in terms of their long-term strategies.The effect on the UK stock market may be relatively small - at least the FTSE 100 is dominated by diverse international companies offering a degree of protection. Investors however should also be aware of the sectors that are significantly exposed to the weakness in sterling, such as the London property market. Mark Martin, Neptune’s Head of UK equities and manager of the UK mid-cap fund has been reducing the portfolio’s exposureto the London housing market recently in response to this. While Blackrock, in a recent report compiled by a team of economists and portfolio managers, have warned of the effect a Brexit may have on London property prices, which already stand at high levels.There is also little reason to believe that a Brexit would enhance EU trade relative to the stay-in position. Although, in the longer-term the UK may begin to internalise more, “Buying British” and replacing EU goods with home produced goods, consequently improving the trade balance and boosting the UK economy.The biggest unknown is of course the outcome of the vote on June 23rd. A leave vote is very possible; according to recent polling by NatCen Social Research, the pro-EU camp is currently leading the race, with 52% of respondents opting to remain. On the other hand asurvey of international pension funds and asset managers, produced by NN Investment partners, show that 27% believe the June referendum would result in a leave vote. This is up from fewer than 20% in March last year.Risk managementFor advisers and long-term investors there’s no reason to believe anything will change in terms of their asset allocation models. Normal planning rules will continue to apply although for particularly nervous investors, who believe a UK exit is imminent, reducing the risk profile of the portfolio may be appropriate.]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[20Start with the WhyGareth Johnson | Head of Managed Investment Services | Brewin DolphinSimon Sinek, bestselling author of corporate America staple, ‘Start with the Why’ argues that by focussing on why you do something, rather than what you do or how you do it, you are more likely to succeed in business. Sinek says people buy people they believe in, so if you start by telling them why you do something - using the ‘how’ and the ‘what’ as proof - then you can create something really desirable and ultimately more successful.Brewin Dolphin’s business is built on selling our investment management expertise as part of a service to others. So what I’d call the ‘Why conversation’ is one we naturally and frequently end up having with potential adviser partners.“We’re not good at everything, we’re not good by ourselves. Our ability to build trust and relationships is the key to our survival as a race and to thriving as idea makers”Simon SinekFor some advisers, investment management is a core part of their personal service offering to clients - they have the expertise, regulatory permissions and business set up to do it. For advisers whose skills lie elsewhere – such as building relationships, guiding and coaching clients to their goals, being contactable when markets become volatile - getting help from experts in investment management can add real value to their client offering.In the 2013 The Trusted Adviser survey – ’honouring the client at every turn’ – 82% of respondent’s stated interpersonal skills and empathy were the key traits they valued in their adviser. Just 4% said technical skills were the most valued trait and 11% valued knowledge above all else.Getting help from experts in investment management can add real value to their client offering]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[21By being clear on why you are doing what you do and then bringing in outside experts with different but complementary skills, the combined result can mean a more powerful business and one that is more likely to grow.Everyone has their own thing they are great at. By being clear on why you are doing what you do and then bringing in outside experts with different but complementary skills, the combined result can meana more powerful business and one that is more likely to grow.Identify your assets...... analyse your business and the things you’re great atInspire your team...... to focus on the things you and they are great atInteract...... with companies that can offer expertise in the areas that are not valued as much by your clientsIgnite...... your business by working together with your chosen experts and creating real alpha in your businessOutsourcing is typically defined as ‘obtaining goods or a service from an outside supplier’. However, a successful DFM/adviser partnership should be seen as a collaborative partnership as advisers implement centralised investment propositions. By working in partnershipwith a DFM, advisers can draw on theDFMsThe value of investments can fall and your clients may get back less than they invested.All information within this article is for illustrative purposes only and is not intended as investment advice; no investment is suitable in all cases and if you have any doubts as to an investment’s suitability then you should contact us.The information contained in this document is believed to be reliable and accurate, but without further investigation cannot be warranted as to accuracy or completeness.By working in partnership with a DFM, adviserscan draw on the DFMs complementary skills for the long term benefitof their clients and their businesscomplementary skills for the long term benefit of their clients and their business. Working as a team to deliver the best investment solution allows both parties to play to their strengths.Brewin Dolphin’s Managed Portfolio Service is used by more than 900 adviser firms across the UK and is risk rated by Synaptic. The service is available via Aegon, Aviva, AXA Elevate, Ascentric, Fusion, James Hay, Novia, Nucleus, Standard Life and Zurich.For more information on the service and how using the service can help, please contact your local Business Development Manager.www.brewin.co.uk/financial-advisers/ meet-the-team]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[22The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsThe Synaptic guide to SIPPsEric Armstrong looks at Synaptic Software’s due diligence capabilities, and why everyone loves a SIPP in the evolving Financial Planning landscapeThe worst things you can say regarding SIPPs is that they can be accessed irresponsibly and stuffed full of rubbish. Conmen cold calling pensioners to ‘unlock’ their pensions favour SIPPs, in order to channel funds into ‘better performing’ investment opportunities, like the kind that were offered by Harlequin Properties.Traded Life Policies, Carbon Credits, Film Investments may also make us squirm, but their accessibility through SIPPs underlines how flexible these wrappers are.ABI figures show us that individual pensions (and SIPPs) overall nosedived 84% 2012/13 following the first auto enrolment milestone, but strip out the group side and we observe that new contracts written by advisers have been growing fast: more than doubling over the next two years to 216k in Q4 2015, when 90% of individual pensions were SIPPs (75% of which were ‘insured’).The other interesting trend is the ongoing dominance of the independent advice channel,who represent 80% of SIPP sales by volume. There is an interesting dichotomy between insured and non-insured SIPPs. Non-insured SIPPs represent a third of the volume of insured but hold over 60% of SIPP AUM - indicating that SIPPs deployed by specialist wealth managers and wraps are attracting very wealthy customers.A look at the historical data shows that in the independent advice sector that we serve, SIPP recommendations have been fairly consistent over the years, including pre and post auto enrolment, but the premium value is increasing.A further consideration is cost. This was traditionally the product’s Achilles heel, where there was constant opprobrium directed at advisers who selected the more expensive product when not actually requiring the flexibility. As costs have continued to drop as technology has improved, there is less of this kind of criticism.SIPPS: evidencing your expertise using SynapticThe three key proofs of suitability that require research relate to:1. Features2. Price3. RiskHere is a quick demonstration of how the Synaptic Research Suite will provide you with the due diligence you may require, something that can be achieved quicklyand easily.Working with the client, and selectingfunds within our chosen asset allocation via Synaptic Fund Research, we are able to build a bespoke portfolio in the Portfolio Builder module:]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Suitability in regards to featuresThe following screenshot shows how a Synaptic Product research user could create a grid to compare and contrast the open market for SIPPs. Once assessed, the Synaptic methodology takes you through filtering and ranking, into a full suitability report.As with other product categories, working with Synaptic will provide SIPP recommendations with the audit trail showing the basis of the selection. The software will also allow manual input of notes to ensure all due diligence points are captured beyond the normal filtering and ranking process.Synaptic is also a fantastic tool for ‘looking up’ provider, product or fund details. Tens of thousands of fund fact sheets are downloaded annually by the thousands of advisers who rely on SynapticSuitability in respect of priceThe screenshot on following page from Synaptic Comparator indicates the keen competition at the head of the leader board that exists today. A SIPP solution, including platform, wrapper and portfolio (though not adviser charges) comes in at around 1% RIY.The regulator is rightly concerned at the quality of research and reporting in regards to establishing suitability. Synaptic Comparator is the research tool that allows you to perform your own illustrations; including setting the growth assumptions to match other providers’ illustrations allowing like for like comparisons. It is the only tool that receives details of platform, product and investment charges across a range of products with charges data that is reviewed and signed off by providers.In the independent advice sector that we serve, SIPP recommendations have been fairly consistent over the years, including pre and post auto enrolment, but the premium value is increasing.23The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsSuitability in respect of RiskThe following screen shows a series of stochastic projections from the Synaptic Modeller tool.This is the only tool that offers full access to the Moody’s Analytics stochastic engine, allowing you to project on existing as well as notional investments. Although you can customise Modeller, most use the default investment strategy provided off the shelf by Moody’s Analytics (formerly Barrie+ Hibbert). This aligns the Moody’s ATRQ with their risk Categories, the latter which are definedby their strategic asset allocations. A ‘Capacity for Loss’ quotient can be calculated for most investments, whether legacy or notional. These can be mapped against the Moody’s Risk model. You can then discuss investment outcomes with your client in terms of probability – in our view the only feasible approach given the huge range of possibilities.Analysis provided by Synaptic Comparator enables you to capture costs accurately thanks to the R.I.Y. calculation. I have modelled several scenarios: the first maps the probable outcomes generated by Moody’s default strategic asset allocation for the Balanced category (first graph or blue line).The second graph (or green line) shows the spread of outcomes when costs including platform, product (SIPP) AND Adviser charging are included.The third calculation (or red line) shows the projections for the investment strategy when inflation is taken into account. This is a difficult call to make as an adviser, which is why access to the industry leading modelling tool becomes very useful. The toll that inflation takes on investments is hard to accept – in Cash, my client is likely to have lost 25% of purchasing power (perhaps a lot more). My strategy is showing a 70% chance of beating the ravages of inflation over the term, but with the hope of significant additional upside. The work that needs to be done to reduce costs – cheaper technology, regulation, investment strategies – is essential in the (relatively) low inflation, low return environment we are in. Any contribution to the compound growth of our investment becomes very valuable.This is the only tool that offers full access to the Moody’s Analytics stochastic engine, allowing you to project on existing as well as notional investments.]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[The FCA requires you to explain the effects of inflation for your clients – something that is unsatisfactory using deterministic cashflow modelling plans. Including a Monte Carlo simulation is the only way forward! Can you do this?Drawdown facility makes SIPP an ideal pension vehicleSynaptic Product research will also provide the details of the leading propositions’ excellent drawdown capabilities. Pension freedoms have pushed the role of flexible drawdown to the forefront of at retirement planning, making the flexibility of a SIPP a powerful tool in this context. There are 56 different contracts from 13 Providers in Synaptic.Where clients require more control, including the ability ‘to own the relationship contact’ with Provider, the ability to ‘adjust income online’ as well as enjoy ‘automatic rebalancing’, then AEGON, James Hay and Transact lead the pack. Standard Life, Old Mutual and AXA Life have the best financial ratings, though questions marks are currently hanging over the long term platform strategies of some companies which should definitely be considered.The current icing on the cake for SIPPs comes from its IHT planning capabilities.We see that advisers are recommending that the SIPP be switched into slow drawdown and other sources of revenue to be exhausted before depleting pension funds. This can of course result in the SIPP being passed seamlessly on to beneficiaries. There is no guarantee that this will always be the case, but there is a good chance that the strategy will hold. Moreover this is a strategy that can and will really benefit middle Englanders at a time that policy is looking to support them when low interest rates are harming savers and the savings gap has become more of a political issue.This ability to create a financial legacy is also a primary driver for legitimate transfer out of group schemes, again something that will be attractive to a lot of advisers’ clients. The skill and experience of advisers will absolutely be required in these cases.Any firm that is concerned that their compliance regime may need a review in the current changing pensions and compliance climate should call us on 0800 783 4477.Source: Adapted from an article that appeared in the May edition of IFP magazine. Market statistics published by ABI and research statistics by Synaptic Research TeamThe FCA requires you to explain the effects of inflation for your clients – something that is unsatisfactory using deterministic cashflow modelling plans. Includinga Monte Carlo simulation is the only way forward! Can you do this?Eric ArmstrongProduct Marketing Synaptic Software Limited25The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26With a typical SIPP client facing 30 to 40 years in retirement, it’s crucial that adviser selects providers who have the best chance of being around for the very long haul.The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsSurvival of the Fittest bespoke SIPP ProvidersFor so long the SIPP industry has escaped the kind of intense scrutiny that other providers are typically put through and there is currently very little independent rating and benchmarking to assess the financial stability of providers. That’s until now!In 2014, we produced our first benchmarking report on the platform industry, with particular focus on financial performance, profitability and re-platforming. Our report anticipated much of the structural changes going onin the platform sector right now and have been credited for raising the bar on the way adviser conducted due diligence. So when SIPP industry veteran John Moret agreed to oversee our financial stability benchmarking exercise for SIPP providers, we were over the moon.It doesn’t exactly take a genius to figure out that the SIPP market is currently undergoinga sea-change driven by commercial and regulatory pressures on providers. New capital requirements (FCA Policy Statement 14/12) are due to come into force on 1 September 2016, and providers are already bracing themselves for the potential impact of an FCA crackdown on retained interests on deposits through greater disclosure or worse. Also we can expect even greater focus on investments–particularly those classified as non-standard. Furthermore, the need to upgrade technology and IT systems, implement tighter risk controls and meet increasing client demand off the back of Pension Freedoms will put even more pressure on SIPP providers. We have seen an increase in the pace of consolidation and M&A activities in the sector, and this trend is expected to accelerate even further.Lowest Common Denominator Is No Due DiligenceWhen we first muted the idea of doing this research, we spoke to a number of people in the industry. Most agree with us that this piece of work is both long-overdue and also rather timely. However, we had a number of people who weren’t particularly keen on the idea, perhaps for fear of what we might find if we start snooping around their businesses. Some]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[As the new requirements come into force, advisers can expect to see the consolidation of books of assets, with many providers disappearing from the market altogethertold us this is nearly impossible, given the number of small players in the sector.One reason given to explain away the need to scrutinise the financial stability of SIPP provider is that idea that, since providers are authorised by the FCA, then advisers should take it for granted the provider is financially stable. Thisis by far the lamest excuse for inadequate due-diligence I have come across yet. Believe me when I tell you I have heard quite a few of those in my time. The idea that advisers’ due diligence should be based on the lowest common denominator – i.e. being regulated by the FCA – is not only short of professional standards expected by the regulator but also well below client expectation.In its recent thematic review TR16/1[1], the FCA said it considered inadequate research and due diligence as two of the main causes of suitability failings. As a result, adviserdue diligence has never been higher on the regulator’s agenda. Accordingly, to meet their regulatory and professional obligation to clients, adviser due-diligence shouldput SIPP providers under greater scrutiny, with a particular focus on financial stability and longer term viability. Advisers must never take it for granted that just becausea provider meets the lowest common denominator of being regulated by the FCA, then that equates to being financially stable. It is one thing for a SIPP operator to be regulated by the FCA, it’s another for them the business to be run profitably with capital resources and scale required to remain in the market in the long haul.Most SIPPs remain in force for many years through and after retirement. With a typical SIPP client facing 30 to 40 years in retirement, it’s crucial that adviser selects providers who have the best chance of being around forthe very long haul. The longevity of SIPPs is a key attraction of this market for providers particularly given the inertia factor owing to the inefficiencies in the pension transfer market. These factors make it all the more important that the “right” SIPP is selected at outset.As the new requirements come into force, advisers can expect to see the consolidationof books of assets, with many providers disappearing from the market altogether. This will create anxiety for clients and could do some damage to the trust advisers have spent years building, not to talk of the administrative cost it adds to the adviser’ business. While most client assets will not necessarily be at risk as a result of these changes, some providers are sitting on toxic books of assets, which may fall foul of FCA and HMRC rules. The risk is that even clients with relatively standard assets may end up with providers that their advisers feel uncomfortable with in terms of cost, service or reputation, never mind the damage the uncertainty does to the relationship between adviser and client when a provider is acquired or exits the market. All of these raise a major due diligence challenge for advisers, both in terms of reviewing their existing provider and in selection new providers that are financially stable, who are likely to not only survive but thrive.This is exactly why we put this report together, to make the due-diligence process less burdensome for advisers and arguablyfor providers. The scoring system is rather stringent, for obvious reasons. We don’t award brownie points to provider for just meeting the minimum common denominator such as holding the minimum regulatory requirement. Instead we award points for keeping over above the regulatory requirement, which is considered good business practice. Our overall premise is that providers with track record of profitability, surplus capital resources (over and above regulatory requirement), above- average profit margins, healthy mix of assets and growing market share have demonstrated that their business strategy works and can be expected to not only survive but thrive in the increasingly competitive landscape. Providers who are loss-making or operating on thin margins and those holding the bare minimum capital requirement will struggle to absorb competitive and regulatory shocks; they are vulnerable to acquisitions by stronger players. For these providers, the light at the end of the tunnel is on oncoming train!Advisers can access a copy of the report atwww.finalytiq.co.uk/research-papers/Abraham OkusanyaPrincipal | FinalytiQ[1] TR16/1: Assessing suitability: Research and due diligence of products and services27The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[28The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsRetirement income: why the scale of your platform’s universe mattersThe introduction of pension freedoms in April 2015 created a new market of income-hungry investors eager to take advantage of the increased flexibility available for their retirement savings. For those with a SIPP, the new rules opened up the option to set up income drawdown as a way of receiving regular income in retirement or take cash from their pension pot, either as a one-off lump sum or via a series of smaller lump sums.Platforms responded quickly to the news of the impending pension changes by reducing charges on platform-based SIPPs and income drawdown products either before, or shortly after, the new rules came into effect last year. Ascentric, for example, took action back in the summer of 2014 to reduce ongoing administration charges for drawdown from £150 to £100, with no additional fees for clients looking to set up more drawdown agreements.This said, cost should not be an investors’only consideration when reviewing their options for a SIPP or drawdown product through a platform. One of the most widely acknowledged benefits for SIPP savers, who opt not to buy an annuity, is that they do not lose the flexibility to choose where their pension savings are invested, with the ability to select from a wide variety of investment vehicles.So an important additional consideration to cost for SIPP savers is the scale and variety of investment vehicles available through the platform they choose.Investment strategies have evolved since the introduction of the pension changes, adapting to the increased flexibility available to clients while still supporting their income and capital preservation requirements. The traditional trajectory for pension savings,for example, would usually involve a steady shift from equity based investments to less risky assets during the 10 years leading up to retirement, principally investing in corporate debt, government bonds and cash. However, with the increasing popularity of drawdown has prompted a change in investment strategy. Instead of savers de-risking their pension portfolio, under drawdown, it may be beneficial to prolong their exposure to riskier assetssuch as equity funds, therefore maintaining the opportunity for both income and capital growth. Alternative investments such as Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs), some of which target income through indices that focus on dividend paying shares, may be suitable for those looking to produce income in retirement too. Property funds also have the potential to pay an attractive income.The world of pensions is clearly changing the hunting ground for income, arguably makingit more important than ever for an adviserto consider whether a platform provides a broad enough investment range beyond the more traditional investment options. With unbiased and unrestricted access to over 3,000 funds and 667 ETFs alongside investment trusts, bonds, gilts, shares and cash, Ascentric’s universe of investments and tax wrappersis one of the widest available in the current platform market.Jon TaylorManaging DirectorFor professional adviser use only.The risks of the SIPP will depend on the investments chosen.Ascentric is a trading name of Investment Funds Direct Limited (IFDL), which is part of the Royal London Group and authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority No. 114432. Registered in England and Wales number 1610781, VAT number 368524427.]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[010 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 INDICATION OF THE REDUCTIONPension Freedoms:ARTWORK VERSION No.10/09/10 1PRINT COLOURS FINISHESCYAN MAGENTA YELLOW BLACKPLEASE READN.B. The colours on this artwork run out are for colour indication only.Refer to listed Pantone (PMS) specification or attached swatches where applicable for true colour representation.APlelasrtewdorukbisleacphperockveAdLLbydejktraialswofithecldieantetpgriivoernt.ofinalproduction.ANY changes made after this date are the responsibility of the client.Standard Life SPECIAL INSTRUCTIONSNicola ThomsonCore Master Logo - CMYK Positive DM/GHLisa Stillman5/05Standard Life RedesignSTL03using SIPP drawdown toIllustrator CS3SCALE MM: THIS RULER MEASURES 100MM WHEN ARTWORK IS 100% PLEASE NOTE IF VIEWING THIS ARTWORK AS A PDF IT MAY NOT BE TO SCALE. THE SCALE OPPOSITE WILL GIVE ANImplementatisupport full flexibilityAPPROVALonDateDesignDateA/C managementDateThe clientJim has recently retired at age 55, he has a small consultancy income of £9,000 a year and has five years to wait until his final salarypension of £25,000 a year comes into payment. He also has Defined Contribution (DC) savings of £200,000 in a personal pension and he plans to use this to top up his consultancy earning to give him £20,000 a year net, bridging the gap until he reaches age 60.and £2,000 from his pension fund). This equals the 2016/17 personal allowance so no income tax is payable• At 60, Jim receives his final salary pension and stops the drawdown income, leaving the balance invested for rainy day or estate planning purposesAll scenarios assume Jim receives his consultancy income of £9,000a year to use this as a rainy day fund, and keep for inheritance purposes. BeforeJim wants to maximise the funds left in his DC pot at age 60 as he plansScenario 1Scenario 2Scenario 3Tax-free lump sum taken-50,000£0£0Gross pension withdrawal required£13,250£12,470.60£2,000Regular income from Tax-free cash£0£3,117.65£9,000Total Gross income (taxable pension withdrawal + £9k earnnings)£22,250£18,352.95£11,000Personal Allowance-£11,000-£11,000-£11,000Total Taxable income£11,250£7,352.95£0Tax paid (20%)-£2,250-£l,470.59£0Total net income£20,000£20,000£20,000Balance left in pension£136,750£187,529.40£189,000Pension Freedoms it was the norm to use a bank account to do this.His pension provider tells him that withdrawing all of his DC savings will result in him paying £55,893 income tax in the current tax year – leaving him £144,107 in the bank*.The solutionThere are three options Jim could consider (see table overleaf):Scenario 1(Pre Pension Freedoms typical behaviour)• Jim takes all of his Tax Free Cash (TFC) up front – £50,000 and depositsit in his bank account• The balance of £150,000 is used to provide a regular taxable drawdown income• Income tax is payable of £2,250 a yearScenario 2(partial use of Pension Freedoms)• Monthly payments are made up of 25% TFC so the 75% balance istaxable (this is the UFPLS method)• £12,470 (£3,117.65 + £9,352.95) is crystallised each year to give a net payment of £11,000 on top of Jim’s consultancy income• Income tax of £1,470.59 is paid each yearScenario 3(using the full flexibility available under Pension Freedoms)Therefore, by choosing option 3 Jim doesn’t have to pay any income tax, keeps the funds in a tax-exempt environment (CGT, income tax and IHT) and is more likely to meet Jim’s needs compared to some of the less flexible options (annuity, capped drawdown or UFPLS). In addition, there is more left in the DC pot for future use.Alistair BlackHead of Financial Planning PropositionNotes• This case study takes no account of the adviser charge• There may be a charge for transferring to a drawdown arrangement• LawsandtaxrulesmaychangeinthefutureandtheinformationisbasedonourunderstandingatFebruary2016. • Investmentscangoupordown.Adrawdownarrangementwillneedtobereviewedonaregularbasistoensure• Jim gets a regular income of £9,000 a year from his tax-free cash that the pension fund can sustain the level of income that the customer is taking. Remember, that the fund couldentitlement• Jim only needs £2,000 a year to reach his £20,000 income target. Jim’s total taxable income is £11,000 (£9,000 consultancy incomerun out of money.• This is for information purposes only. Every person’s circumstances will be different and require advice. StandardLife accepts no responsibility for advice that may be formulated on the basis of this information. No guarantees are given regarding the effectiveness of any arrangement entered into on the basis of these comments.29The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[30The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsThe SIPPAs the ‘pension’ tax wrapper has become less synonymous with providing an income in retirement and increasingly one part of the broader planning process alongside other tax wrappers, so the self- invested personal pension (SIPP) has become increasingly valuable in helping investors fulfil their financial goals in the most tax efficient way.Financial advisers increasingly use cash flow modelling tools with their clients to establish and maintain a financial plan. The use of tax wrappers within this to achieve the most tax efficient ‘path’ illustrates how wide-ranging and flexible a SIPP can be in covering particular requirements.Typically from age 55 any amount of accumulated pension savings can be withdrawn to provide one-off or regular payments as required. Up to 25% of accumulated pension savings can be paid tax-free.It is now also possible that an individual’s pension fund can be passed down the generations without becoming subject to inheritance tax (IHT). For many this means that their SIPP will be the last wrapper to be accessed for income or other payments. ISAs, for example, provide tax-free income and typically are not IHT exempt so aSIPP investment would provide a better option when funds are required if passing pension savings on following death isa key requirement. Modern investment administration platforms such as that offered by Transact are ideal for managing investment and tax wrapper selection to optimise an investor’s financial plan. The Transact SIPP wrappers offer access to a very broad rangeof investments including shares, collective investment schemes, investment trusts, structured products and exchange traded funds (ETFs). These plans also include full flexibility in terms of taking benefits whether for the individual themselves or for their intended beneficiaries following their death.The pension rules are continually changing with a main trend being the restriction of what can be paid into an individual’s plans. £40,000 (including basic rate tax relief on contributions made by the individual) is the current annual input limit that applies across all schemes of which an individual is a member althoughthis starts to reduce for higher earners down to a maximum of £10,000. It is possible that the unused input allowance from the previous three years can be utilised once the currentyear’s allowance has been used. A £10,000 input limit also applies where an individual has taken income under the ‘flexi-access’ rules introduced in April 2015.An individual’s lifetime allowance (LTA) for pension savings will also impact on the amount of input. If this limit (currently £1m for those taking benefits from 6 April 2016 who do not have a protected higher limit) is exceeded then tax of 55% or 25% is applied totheexcessiftakenasalumpsumorasa pension respectively.These changes indicate a ‘direction of travel’ under which further restrictions (including the possible loss of tax relief on contributions) are likely so it is important that individuals make use of their current input allowance where they can to ensure that the benefits of a SIPP can be maximised.Brian RadboneHead of Technical]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[AJ Bell – from SIPPto full platformAJ Bell’s heritage is in the Self-Invested Personal Pension (SIPP) and Small Self-Administered Pension Scheme (SSAS) markets but today we are one of the leading full service platform operators, offering a wide range of products, extensive investment options and first class service, all at a very competitive cost.The platform market is extremely competitive. The investment in IT needed to maintain a robust, secure and scalable platform is an ongoing commitment. Platforms that have under invested in their technology in the past are reportedly now spending eye watering sums of money playing catch up.Over the years at AJ Bell we have been very focussed on maintaining a consistently profitable, stable and well capitalised business in order to maintain the sustained investment that I believe any evolving platform needs.Our evolutionAJ Bell Investcentre was launched in 2002 under the name Sippcentre. This exciting new proposition offered financial advisers a unique way to help clients reap the benefits of a low- cost online SIPP.The formula proved popular, and in 2007 we made it even more appealing by acquiring the stockbroker Lawshare (now AJ Bell Securities). By 2008 the extensive range of investments available was boosted with several new off- panel options.When we launched our ISA and GIA in 2011, Sippcentre became a true investment platform - albeit one with a name that did not quite reflect its new status, so today we are called AJ Bell Investcentre.AJ Bell todayAJ Bell is a financially strong, profitable company with no debt. We have an excellent track record of re-investing retained profitsto ensure our platform can help the adviser improve client outcomes, mitigate risk in their business and increase efficiency by saving time and reducing costs.Our most recent development was the acquisition of a small asset management operation which adds investment management services to our business. It gives us discretionary permissions as well as the ability to launch our own funds and build new investment solutions that advisers need to service their clients.Our initial intention is to launch a Model Portfolio Service, utilising passive investments as the underlying vehicles to keep costs low. The new service will enable advisers to offertheir clients a high-quality, low-cost portfolio service aligned to their attitude to risk.In addition, we continue to invest in the day- to-day functionality of the platform.We arein the process of improving the user interface and upgrading the calculation engine on our illustration tool, and work is underway to expand our range of data links to back office providers such as the Iress XPLAN and Intelliflo.We have also launched a major project which will result in a streamlined new business application process, and an improved look and feel for the website. We also intend to provide a wide range of new functionality, such as a Capital Gains Tax planning tool.All the investment, expertise and passion that made us a leading SIPP provider is now channelled into delivering high quality online investment services via ISAs, dealing accounts and offshore bonds, as well as our market- leading SIPP.Billy MackayMarketing Director, AJ Bell31The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[32The Synaptic Guide to SIPPsPension technical update - the extended definition of a dependantUnder existing legislation, a person must meet one of the following definitions in order to be classed as a dependant:• A spouse or civil partner of the member (either at the member’s death or, if the scheme rules allow, when the member became entitled to a pension under the scheme)• A child of the member under age 23• A child age 23 or over, who was dependent on the member at the time of the member’s death due to physical or mental impairment• A person who was not a spouse, civil partner or child of the member who, at the member’s death, was:- Financially dependent on the member- In a mutually dependent financial relationship with the member- Dependent on the member due to physical or mental impairment.All except one of the definitions depends ona person’s status at a fixed point in time. A person who meets one of those definitions cannot ‘lose’ their classification as a dependant. However, as the second definition is based solely on age, a child would no longer be a dependant upon reaching age 23.This causes problems when death benefits are paid in a form which involves ongoing income, such as dependants’ drawdown. Income from a dependant’s drawdown account can onlybe paid to a dependant; otherwise it is an unauthorised payment. Therefore children must usually stop taking income before their 23rd birthdays.Draft legislation is now in place to resolve this problem going forward. It will work by adding a new definition of a dependant as follows:• A child of the member who:- Has reached age 23- Was not dependent on the member due to physical or mental impairment at the time of the member’s death.This additional definition will only apply if a child has established a dependant’s drawdown account before age 23, allowing them to continue taking income as a dependant after reaching this age. It does not extend to other areas of the legislation. Therefore, other than where a child was dependent due to physical or mental impairment:• Children who are already 23 or over when inheriting benefits will still be classed as nominees, rather than dependants• Dependant’ annuities and dependants’ scheme pensions for children must still end at age 23• The existence of a child age 23 or over would not prevent the payment of a charity lump sum death benefit.Jessica ListPensions Analyst, Suffolk Life]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Is decumulation where the money is?With so much airtime given to pension freedoms – understandably so – and also the apparent lack of innovation across the market, we arranged a deeper look at what is available in the market – relating to platforms in particular. The reason for focusing on platforms, if reports are to be believed, is that platforms are seen as one of the leading solutions that will support the retirement market, in particular the provision of income for clients (and we have a platform!)For those with an interest in platforms, the findings are enlightening, even for the seemingly straightforward stuff.From a client’s perspective, obtaining income doesn’t have to be really complicated and must be delivered in a way they value. For instance, they may wish to have income supplied from across multiple tax wrappers on the platform but don’t want to receive lots of different payments in their bank account, preferring just one. But which platform can cope?So we commissioned the report but stepped back from carrying out the research ourselves, or writing the resulting report for that matter. There are some who would be quite happyto suggest ’foul play’ if we had. Instead, we turned to those well-known felines of Edinburgh for help.The lang cat (a consultancy based in Leith, Edinburgh, specialising in platforms, pensions and investments) researched fourteen adviser- led platforms at the turn of this year. If you would like a copy of ‘Income in retirement through platforms’, get in touch via Twitter @ZurichAlistair or @ZurichAdvisers, or ask your usual Zurich contact, and we’ll let you have it!The Zurich platform also ensures clients are always paid their income even when there is insufficient cash available. The lang cat stated “We think this is pretty cool; the last thing anyone wants is the client not getting a monthly income that’s required to pay the bills...because somebody forgot to keep the cash account healthy.”With the variety of responses in the report it does make me ponder which platforms are actually capable of delivering against the new flexibilities available to clients and advisers. After all, many (all) platforms reviewedhere were built prior to the introduction of freedoms. And as the lang cat pointed out “...clients typically spend a bigger part oftheir platform experience in retirement than accumulation.”Back in December we asked advisers who are part of the New Model Business Academy (NMBA):“Given the new pension freedoms, are you reassessing the platforms you use to ensure they will meet your client needs going forward?”Perhaps unsurprisingly, two thirds indicated they are. I wonder how this has changed following some of the direct and rather scathing comments made by the FCA following the publication of their due diligence findings in March.So on reflection, should platforms perhaps review their own processes, functionality and suitability in this new world before embarking on delivering new solutions?I will leave that one with you.Alistair WilsonZurich’s Head of Retail Platform Strategy33The Synaptic Guide to SIPPs]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Welcome to an exciting new era in investment management!P1 provides an integrated platform and investment management solution that is efficient and low- cost, without compromising on performance. Come and talk to us.01392 953079 info@p1-im.co.uk www.p1-im.co.ukP1 Investment Management Limited is an Appointed Representative of Prydis Wealth Limited, which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[35An investment proposition for advisers, built with advisers’ perspectiveJames Priday | Managing Director of P1 Investment ManagementIn 2012, Prydis obtained investment management permissions to increase the efficiency of our business, enhance our service offering and reduce overall costs for our clients.We did so after finding the process of using external discretionary managers inefficient, time-consuming and, in many cases, they were charging more than our ongoing financial advisory fees which did not seem equitable. I was struggling to see the value added to the client.Since 2012, we have established a robust investment process and have developed nine core model investment portfolios which span five risk levels and three primary objectives (income, capital growth and balanced).We also operate a bespoke service forlarger portfolios, or where one of the model portfolios does not meet the needs of the client. This has been a great success: We have built a strong track-record within our models, have increased the efficiency of our business, and reduced overall costs for clients.We, therefore, saw an opportunity to expand the offering beyond our own client base so that other advisory firms could benefit and P1 Investment Management was born.P1 is a stand-alone business from Prydis, but it will adopt the existing investment processes, model portfolios (including their track-records) and key investment management personnel. P1 will not have any financial advisers of its own and will be entirely discrete from our financial advisory business. It won’t deal with individual clients directly at all, thus protecting the trusted relationship you, as advisers have built up with your clients.Efficiency, low-costs, and enhancing the adviser-client relationship are the three cornerstones of P1’s proposition.Advisers will be able to access the full range of services directly through P1’s platform solution, and access our model portfolios through other investment platforms.Since 2012, we have established a robust investment process and have developed nine core model investment portfolios which span five risk levels and three primary objectives (income, capital growth and balanced).]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[36Why that fund for that client?Dan Russell | Managing Director | Verbatim Asset ManagementIt is surprising how often you meet fundamentalists in financial services when discussing portfolio construction. For every apostle of fund of funds there is a pilgrim for model portfolios, a disciple of DFMs or a sect for advisers’ own fund selection.Yet surely none of these broad churches is inherently right or wrong? There are some key questions that the fundamentalists who focus on just one primary solution should always ask:1. How does this fund match the journey of risk I have agreed with my client?Quantifying and qualifying risk with a client allows you to set their expectations of how much they could gain but how much they could lose, framing future conversations around performance regardless of market gains or losses.If you cannot clearly communicate to your client why and how the funds or portfolio you have selected will deliver within the parameters of their expected risk journey, you should not be using that solution. The same holds true for overall asset allocation.2. What’syourdocumentedapproachto fund manager research?Can you articulate how and why you arrived at using that particular fund, rather than a host of other similar funds that could have done the same? Do you know all the moving partsabout that fund? Can the manager buy what he likes within the fund or is he constrained by a mandate, and indeed does he stick to that mandate? The question really should be not]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[37Quantifying and qualifying risk with a client allows you to set their expectations of how much they could gain but how much they could lose, framing future conversations around performance regardless of market gains or losseswhy you chose that fund, but why didn’t you choose all the others.3. How will you cost effectively administer the portfolio?This might be done on a platform, a stand- alonetaxwrapperorevendirectlywiththe fund manager, but certain key tasks need to be undertaken. Rebalancing in line with the risk journey is one thing, but how will you do what used to be called switching but is now really just advice – every time you recommend a switch you recommend a client sells an asset, turns it into cash and buys another and this needs full disclosure and client agreement.4. Whoprovidesgovernanceandreview?Who is in charge of documenting your process, reviewing its suitability and ensuring that your firm sticks to this process? Sole practitioners may need outside assistance with this, whereas multi RI firms will need consistency across advisers.What good looks likeIf you start with the whole of the relevant market, use enhanced suitability questions to filter out unsuitable solutions, quantify risk and assess capacity for loss and then have aclear and documented investment philosophy that states why you use the solutions you use, then you will have a clear and credible process to share with clients, staff and the regulator. What’s more, you will be able to answer comprehensively why that client holds thatfund,regardlessofwhichbroadchurchof solutions you have put your faith in.That’s why we provide:• FPVerbatimPortfolios–multi-asset, risk managed, active funds with over 6 years’ strong track record of delivering performance.• VerbatimTotalClarityFunds–multi- asset, risk managed funds using passive instruments.• VerbatimDiscretionaryService–putting you in control of your own risk managed discretionary service, with 5 leading portfolio managers working for you within your advice process.• IndependentInvestmentCommittee–a team of experts overseeing the portfolios making sure the managers are delivering to the set mandate.• BusinessConsultancySupport–expert help to get your client proposition, central investment process and supply chain right.Should you be looking for a solution that does what you expect it to, feel free to email us on info@verbatim-am.co.uk or call us on 0844 967 0945 or you can visit our website at www.verbatim-am.co.uk, we look forward to helping you.The successful advisory firm now has a supply chain of solutions they can use which will meet their clients’ expectations and allow the adviser to focus on delivering financial plans that meet their clients’ goals.Supply Chain Solutions from VerbatimThe successful advisory firm now has a supply chain of solutions they can use which will meet their clients’ expectations and allow the adviser to focus on delivering financial plans that meet their clients’ goals.At Verbatim we believe our job is to provide solutions that do what they say on the tin.]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[38Where for defensive returns and sustainable income?John Stopford | Portfolio Manager | Investec Diversified Income FundInvestors seeking defensive returns and sustainable income could once rely on developed market bonds as a balance to their equity exposure. However, since the global financial crisis, the extreme monetary policies of central banks around the world has distorted government bond markets. So where can investors now turn? We believe that a diversified portfolio of quality income producing assets and a focus on limiting drawdowns could provide investors with a more sustainable, long-term solution.We believe income-seeking Multi-Asset funds can be divided along three lines:01. Thosethataredefensivebond- replacement strategies and those that are more growth-focused, riskier strategies;02. Thosethatgeneratemostoftheirincome naturally (via coupons and dividends) and those that generate most synthetically via derivatives (or capital where allowed);03. Thosethataredirectlyinvestedinthe underlying securities and those that are invested via a fund-of-funds approach, either fettered or unfettered.A defensive total return strategyWe believe that the Investec Diversified IncomeFundisdifferentiatedfromcompetitors because it is defensive, directly invested andfocuses on natural income. Being directly invested provides us with greater visibility and control over the portfolio which helps us to limit drawdowns.We also consider that natural income is more sustainable than synthetic income although synthetic income can havea place in the portfolio at different pointsin the cycle. The combination of these two approaches helps to reduce the volatility of both the capital and the income meaning that the strategy can be more defensive.Drawdown managementDrawdowns in the Fund have historically been better than many competitors’ and weBeing directly invested provides us with greater visibility and control over the portfolio which helps us]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[39Direct ownership of underlying assets, rather than a ‘Fund of Funds’ approach means that every single holding is chosen for its ability to meet our objectivesaim to manage drawdowns via a number of mechanisms. Rather than relying on asset class labels for cosmetic diversification weare structurally diversified across Growth, Defensive and Uncorrelated assets. We systematically hedge unwanted risks: for example we remove most of our EM currency exposure and we can tactically hedge risks such as equities. Using our Compelling Forces framework to compare opportunities across asset classes, we can focus on where we see the best investment opportunities, and our bottom-up focus helps us to identify individual securities which are not only attractive but which also add defensive characteristics.Quality, from the bottom upDirect ownership of underlying assets, rather than a ‘Fund of Funds’ approach meansthat every single every single holding is chosen for its ability to meet our objectives. Diversification within the Fund, active asset allocation and its focus on more defensive and higher quality investments within these asset classes help to reduce overall fund volatility. This, together with our bottom-up approach and focus on how asset class interact, means that, historically, the Fund’s volatility has been less than 50% of the volatility of UK equitieswhich is comparable with the volatility from a global developed government bond portfolio.We are potentially at a fork in the road, meaning that investors and their advisorsare left with the choice about what type of multi-asset programmes should form the foundations of their portfolios for the future. These, we feel, will have to have demonstrated an ability to pro-actively manage risk and deliver returns at reasonable costs.For more information about the Investec Diversified Income Fund please visit www.investecassetmanagement.com/difFor cosmetic diversification we are structurally diversified across Growth, Defensive and Uncorrelated assetsThe Investec Diversified Income Fund aims to fill the role that fixed income can no longer fill. A defensive multi-asset fund, it seeks to provide attractive income with long-term growth.• Attractive income – aims to provide 4-6% p.a.*• Sustainable income – global multi-asset portfolio seeking to grow capital• Lower volatility – historic volatility less than 50% of UK equities• Tax efficiency – classified as an ‘interest-paying’ fund• Actively managed – by co-Head of Multi-Asset Income Income John Stopford and team. *Gross of fees, over a 3-year rolling period. This is an aim and not guaranteed.THIS COMMUNICATION IS DIRECTED ONLY AT PROFESSIONAL FINANCIAL ADVISORS. IT SHOULD NOT BE DISTRIBUTED TO, OR RELIED ON BY PRIVATE CUSTOMERS. Past performance should not be taken as a guide to future returns. The value of investments can go down as well as up and your clients could end up with less than they invested. Your clients’ capital is at risk. English language copies of the Funds’ prospectuses, Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) and report and accounts are available from Investec Asset Management. The Fund may invest more than 35% of their assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state. The Funds are domiciled in the UK. The Fund Prospectus and Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) may be obtained from www.investecassetmanagement.com.]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[40Rathbone Multi- Asset PortfoliosDavid Coombs | Head of Multi-Asset Investments | RathbonesThe direct approach to current investment thinkingIn October 2015, for our range of risk-targeted multi-asset funds, we began investingdirectly in large-cap UK and international equities, as well as sterling investment-funds towards multi-asset portfolios, which considering our private client roots, has informed our move to direct securities as well.So what is our current thinking? Despitemarkets becoming extremely volatile thisyear, we don’t think the world is on the vergeof recession. At this juncture, economic datado not support this view. For that reason wesee market sell-offs as buying opportunities.Nothing has changed for our centralinvestment strategy. We expected volatilitythis year and have been vocal about this fordebt, high cash flows and global empires. Invariably, these giants of global marketsare based in the US. It helps that the USis currently the engine room of the world recovery of course. In our view, its consumers are best placed to benefit from the current low fuel prices, a strong dollar and industrial overcapacity in the East. We have been overweight the US for about three years now and we think the nation’s outperformance is not over yet but we are keeping careful watch over macroeconomic indicators.In conclusion, given where valuations are,on a three-year view, we remain optimistic. We will have to ignore the noise, and stick to fundamentals and our convictions.David is manager of the Rathbone Multi-Asset Portfolios. His views are his own and are not to be taken as investment advice.grade bonds, rather than accessing them through other actively managed funds. This has always been permitted, but it is now an explicit consideration. With the help of our highly-skilled and experienced research team, we have the ability to analyse and select stocks ourselves, and we can better control our exposure to sector, regional and the balance of risk within the pQortfuolio. Wtehave found that long-term themonths. Unfortunately, sharp drops in asseticcan be better executed too, including specificopportunities, offered by a range of diagnostics and treatments in the healthcare space, for example, and the proliferation of robotics, both in factories and in the home. We still use funds to access small and mid-sized equities, because we are happy to use the focused resources of managers that specialise in these areas.Added to the sound logic of this move, the concentration of fund purchases in the UK has worried us for some time. With ever bigger funds to select, our concern has been about liquidity and capacity issues. Added to this, we think UK managers are starting to struggle to capture alpha in large-cap stocks. There has been a move away from pure multi-managermatideasprices jar the nerves far more than vague but insistent warnings of choppy waters ahead. Stubbornly low oil prices have unnerved investors; however, while this is a negative, we feel it is more than outweighed by the positive boost to Western economies and, more specifically, to the consumer.Companies that continue to post earnings gains will be highly prized. Meanwhile, those that disappoint will be swiftly punished. In recent weeks, even the slightest hint of clouds on the horizon has led to sudden double-digit falls in some share prices.We like quality companies, those with tremendous brands, solid management, lowe to go here.Contact detailsFor further information about our Multi Asset FundsT / 020 7399 0399E / rutm@rathbones.com]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[After 21 years we still hold the key to complianceSYNAPTIC PRODUCT & FUND SOFTWARE• Providing independent and objective whole of market research. • Helping advisers navigate the challenges of compliance.• The cornerstone of compliance advice in the UK.• Integrates fully with the entire Synaptic Research Suite.For more information call us on 0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[42Risk and suitability? It’s time to access the real thingEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedIn our introduction, we talked about the possibility that the screws are beginning to turn in regards to the quality of proof of suitability that the regulator requires. Traditionally, it has been difficult to apply a consistent measure for risk, and we would argue that until themore sophisticated stochastic engines were made available, almost impossible. We know from recent FCA announcements, that they have been most unimpressed when looking at the files at various wealth managers - that the majority did not have sufficient research to evidence suitability.The fact is that many of these files will relate to the increasing levels of business introduced by advisers. We should all reflect however that ultimately it is the adviser that is responsible for advice, including suitability and therefore liable.Today, adviser firms must work through the liabilities that will emerge from due diligence relating to investment strategies that are not aligned. An ATRQ from one provider, feeding into a risk framework of another, cobbled with investment pathways defined by others is a recipe for disaster. The onus on the adviser is to be able to demonstrate suitability on an individual case basis – so costs, inflation andthe dynamics of risk need to be evidenced accordingly.The Synaptic Risk proposition has been growing the fastest in the industry as it offers several clear advantages:- Alignment to the Moody’s Analytics (formerly Barrie + Hibbert) A.T.R.Q. and risk categories- Integration with the wider Synaptic suite, meaning that:· accurate R.I.Y. figures can be incorporated into the projections including adviser charging· full flexibility in terms of accessing existing holdings through to building and managing bespoke portfolios- Ability to provide case specific stochastic evaluation of the possible effects of inflation- Ability to compare different risk strategies to help the client understand what their level of risk exposure actually means]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[43The effectiveness of the proposition is built on providing full access to the Moody’s stochastic engine, so probability graphs relating to investment outcomes can be provided on tap. This is not to be confused with the interactive ‘risk buttons’ that most software providers offer.Most risk methodologies in our industry rely, at least in part, on ‘qualitative overlay’ (opinion in other words). This is fine, and the excellent qualitative research available is essential, but this is not the same as objective assessment of risk. Pointing at a number 4 because it says so on the tin, is not a sophisticated assessment of the underlying risks that your client is facing in his particular circumstances.Another reason for having access to the controls is to ensure all the inputs are fully accounted for. The leading fund research packages do not access the correct charging structures at platform, product and share class level, and therefore cannot accurately describe the risk and reward of any given scenario. They can plot the past performance of a portfolio made up of a bunch of funds, but you shouldn’t expect to use this to represent the likely characteristics of your client’s actual scenario. If you go to a Provider for an illustration, you will only get a single view which will require additional research for compliance purposes.Many of the leading financial planners use cash flow planning software, which is very effective in looking at the various layers of a financial plan working together – but is less qualified to look at the immense variety of the different possible outcomes of any given scenario. This can only be effectively achieved by using stochastic analysis. What we know about pound cost ravaging today makes this so (volatility drag, poor sequence of returns and impact of regular withdrawals).Synaptic Risk RatingsThe following pages summarise where leading propositions sit when they are assessed by Synaptic Risk using a standard term of 10 years (unless otherwise stated). Inclusion of the Synaptic fund or portfolio risk fact sheet goes a long way to meeting the compliancerequirements in describing the risk profile of the product.We encourage all advisers to use these outputs alongside any qualitative research they are using. The Synaptic Ratings are fully aligned with the Moody’s ATRQ and investment strategy that is available online via a log in that can be provided for free – so just ask!Summary: a real suitability challenge exists for an independent adviser who:- can only assess a client risk evaluation using the methodology of a preferred provider or platform- uses risk assessments that can’t be compared like-for-like with different propositions or legacy investments- can’t incorporate accurate platform, product, portfolio or fund data with adviser charging and the effects of inflation into their researchIf you would like to sharpen your approach to risk and suitability please call us on0800 783 4477.Synaptic Modeller real life illustration showing probability graphs for a client’s investment scenario:1. Blue: Projection of the Balanced strategy (no charges or inflation)2. Green: Projection of our recommended scenario using Comparator costs for Cofunds / SIPP / Close Brothers Investment / 10 year term / 0.5% adviser trail3. Red: Scenario 2 (green) with Moody’s Monte Carlo simulation for the effects of inflation applied.]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Cautious MPS Income MPS Balanced MPS Growth MPS Global Equity MPSClose Bond Income Portfolio FundClose Diversified Income Portfolio Fund Close Conservative Portfolio FundClose Balanced Portfolio FundClose Growth Portfolio FundClose Managed Diversified Income Fund Close Managed Conservative FundClose Managed Balanced FundClose Managed Growth FundClose Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund Close DMS Diversified IncomeClose DMS ConservativeClose DMS BalancedClose DMS Growth1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 3444445 CF Canlife Portfolio III 5 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 5 CF Canlife Portfolio V 5 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 5 CF Canlife Portfolio VIICanlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 71 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 23 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 5CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation4 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Foundation Defensive Fund Cautious Fund Balanced Fund Growth FundF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM Navigator Distribution F&C MM Navigator Moderate F&C MM Navigator Progressive F&C MM Navigator SelectF&C MM Navigator Boutiques Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling)]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Risk Level 1 Short Risk Level 2 Short Risk Level 3 Short Risk Level 4 Short Risk Level 5 Short Risk Level 1 Medium Risk Level 2 Medium Risk Level 3 Medium Risk Level 4 Medium Risk Level 5 Medium Risk Level 1 Long Risk Level 2 Long Risk Level 3 Long Risk Level 4 Long Risk Level 5 Long Income1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Multi Asset AdventurousMulti Asset Allocator Adventurous Multi Asset Allocator Defensive Multi Asset Allocator Growth Multi Asset Allocator Strategic Multi Asset Allocator WorldMulti Asset Balanced Income Multi Asset DefensiveMulti Asset GrowthMulti Asset IncomeMulti Asset Income & Growth Multi Asset Open Adventurous Multi Asset Open DefensiveMulti Asset Open GrowthMulti Asset Open StrategicMulti Asset StrategicOpen WorldWealth BuilderMulti-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 71 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Diversified Income FundDiversified Growth FundMAP 12345 Managed Growth FundInvestec Cautious Managed Fund1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 5Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting risk.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[M&G Episode Allocation Fund M&G Episode Income Fund M&G Episode Growth Fund M&G Global Dividend Fund M&G Property PortfolioAdventurous Portfolio Income Seeker Portfolio Growth Seeker Portfolio Income Focus Portfolio Temperate Portfolio Growth Focus Portfolio Lower Risk Income Portfolio Lower Risk Growth Portfolio Protective PortfolioPremier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income PortfolioPremier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced PortfolioPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth PortfolioPremier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio1 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 23 4 5 MP3 3 4 5 MP50 3 4 5 MP4 3 4 5 MP5 3 4 5 MP63 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 5Portfolios3 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 5Premier Liberation IV FundPremier Liberation V FundPremier Liberation VI FundPremier Liberation VII FundPremier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market FundPremier Defensive Growth FundPremier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund Premier Diversified Fund1 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 2Funds3 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 51234512345123451234512345MP7 12345]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[PruFund CautiousPruFund Protected CautiousPruFund GrowthPruFund Protected GrowthPruFund0-30 12345 PruFund 10-40PruFund 20-55PruFund 40-80Dynamic 0-30Dynamic 10-40Dynamic 20-55Dynamic 40-80Dynamic 60-100WP Optimum ReturnFocused 0-30Focused 10-40Focused 20-55Focused 40-80Focused 60-100MPS Global GrowthMPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global IncomeMPSIncome 12345 MPS ConservativeRMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income Strategy 1Strategy 2Strategy 3Strategy 4Strategy 5Strategy 61 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 5RL Governed Portfolio 1 RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 RL Governed Portfolio 4 RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 RL Governed Portfolio 7 RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 RLGRIP1RLGRIP2 RLGRIP3 RLGRIP4 RLGRIP5(l)(s) (l)(s) (l)(s)1 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 41 2 3 455555555555555551 2 3 4 5MPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)1 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 512345123451234512345123451 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 5]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive PortfolioPositive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus PortfolioSchroder MM DiversitySchroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK GrowthSchroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5SantanderSantander Atlas 3 Santander Atlas 4 Santander Atlas 5 Santander Atlas 6 Santander Atlas 7 Santander Atlas Income1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 5CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset AllocationCautious / Personal InjuryModerately CautiousIncome 12345 Balanced 12345 Moderately Adventurous 12345 Adventurous 12345Vanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%123451 2 31 2 34 54 51 21 21 21 23 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 5]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Verbatim PortfoliosFP Verbatim Portfolio 3FP Verbatim Portfolio 4FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Income FP Verbatim Portfolio 6FP Verbatim Portfolio 71 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 5Verbatim VDSVDSJH3 12345 VDSJH4 12345 VDSJH5 12345 VDSJH6 12345 VDSJH7 12345 VDSJH8 12345 VDSRSM2 12345 VDSRSM3 12345 VDSRSM4 12345 VDSRSM5 12345 VDSRSM6 12345 VDSRSM7 12345 VDSRSM8 12345 VDSRSM9 12345 VDSRSM10 12345 VDSTCF3 12345 VDSTCF4 12345 VDSTCF5 12345 VDSTCF6 12345 VDSTCF7 12345 VDSTCF8 12345 VDSS&W3 12345 VDSS&W4 12345 VDSS&W5 12345 VDSS&W6 12345 VDSS&W7 12345 VDSS&W8 12345 VSDHR3 12345 VSDHR4 12345 VSDHR5 12345 VSDHR6 12345 VSDHR7 12345 VSDHR8 12345Verbatim RSMRRSM Model Portfolio 2 RSM Model Portfolio 3 RSM Model Portfolio 4 RSM Model Portfolio 5 RSM Model Portfolio 6 RSM Model Portfolio 7 RSM Model Portfolio 8 RSM Model Portfolio 9 RSM Model Portfolio 101 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Total Clarity Portfolio 3 Total Clarity Portfolio 4 Total Clarity Portfolio 5 Total Clarity Portfolio 61 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 5Verbatim Total Clarity12345(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further informationbefore recommending.About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC RISKProvides fund and portfolio risk ratings underpinned by the industry’s leading risk expertiseSynaptic Risk is an integral part of the Synaptic Suite available to all financial advisers. Offers objective research to complement your firm’s qualitative fund analysis.• ATRQ - The industry’s most widely used Attitude to Risk Questionnaire• Risk Ratings table - a comprehensive table of the providers’ funds and portfolios represented in the ratings, available to download and/or print• Risk Fact Sheets - all participating DFM, managed or model portfolio, multi-asset or other funds have unique fact sheets, these show risk ratings in decimalised format, risk metrics from the stochastic modelling and asset allocation data•• •An objective risk measure for your investment recommendations - achieved via access to the industry’s leading stochastic engine from Moody’s AnalyticsBetter advice outcomes - from superior risk analysis and managementAchieve ‘Informed’ consent – quantify possible investment loss and gain using a meaningful and consistent measurements of riskRISK RATING4 RISK RATING5SYNAPTIC SYNAPTICRISK RATING1 RISK RATING2SYNAPTICRISK RATING3SYNAPTIC SYNAPTICCautiousModerately CautiousBalancedModerately AdventurousAdventurousFor more information about Synaptic Risk please visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477You can use the Synaptic Risk Ratings to meet FCA requirements around risk and present to clients using attractive and comprehensive risk metrics.The Synaptic Risk proposition offers the leading risk analysis in a simple, complete package to assist your compliance and ensure buy-in from your clients. This will compliment any qualitative or volatility based research or analysis that you may be relying upon. And its free!Adam Byford, Managing Director, Synaptic Software LimitedWhat does it include?How does it work ?What difference will it make to my clients]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Objective risk managementUnlike any other best advice tool, Synaptic Modeller offers full access to the Moody’s Analytics risk management tool. Now is the time to strengthen your due diligence around risk and suitability using Synaptic’s metrics for risk, Capacity and Tolerance for Loss.Synaptic Modeller is part of the Synaptic Research suite that includes Synaptic Product and Fund, Synaptic Comparator and Synaptic Webline. All can be accessed through single log on, payment and agreement. *Offer includes option for Synaptic Contract Enquiry service, allowing you to maintain holdings information from Providers, including up-to-date valuations. (Subject to £75 setting up fee).Synaptic Modeller Special Deal• Knowyourclient,understandtheirappetiteand tolerance for risk• Storeclients’detailsincludingtheirriskprofile• Modelinvestmentoutcomeswithactualholdings*using Moody’s Analytics stochastic engine• Create,manageandriskassessportfoliosandfunds• IncludesindustryleadingATRQ• Fullrangeofreports• Workefficientlyandaccurately• UsedbyawiderangeofnetworksandIFA'sTo watch our Risk Profiling and Fund selection video, visit the quick links section of our website www.synaptic.co.ukFor more information and to claim your discount on Synaptic Modeller call 0800 783 4477 now.Deal informationOffer ends 30th June 2016, Synaptic Software Limited reserve the right to withdraw this offer at any time, depending on availability and demand. Minimum contract term 18 months. Additional discounts may be available for bulk requirements, or additional software modules. Existing Modeller contracts, including any existing obligations will not be affected by this offer.month £15 per(reduced from £50 per month) for full portfolio andrisk management]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52Synaptic – Finger on the PulseTiina Stephens | Operations Manager | Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Software is actively trying to understand what makes our customers tick and continuously respond to customers’ feedback accordingly. We care about honest and open dialogue with our customers and are keen to ensure that there are ongoing conversations regarding our products and services to ensure that we keep our finger on the pulse.The best features of Synaptic Webline are the ease of use and the quick results.No one becomes an industry leader without listening to the customer. Customer-perceived quality is a leading driver of our business success. Previously Synaptic Software has introduced free software training as part ofa software licencing package, and training videos to benefit our customers (based on your feedback in previous annual customersatisfaction surveys) as well as continuously adjusting how we communicate to and with our customers. These are just a few examples of how we have changed our internal processes to ensure that our clients get the best value and benefit from the software tools. The financial services industry is notoriouslytime poor, our customers are pushed todeliver more value to their customers with less time and resource. Having the righttools and skills in place can drive value and productivity and provide better outcomes to our users and their customers. At Synaptic we pride ourselves in effectively managing our business and continuously using our internal specialist market knowledge to drive effective outcomes to the industry. This said, we do not know everything and that is why we wantto continue to engage with our customers in order to keep our finger on the pulse regarding what you think of our products and services.Our customer feedback programme isnot only an annual survey, but an ongoing conversation. We understand how valuable]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[53Our Relationship Manager at Synaptic is doing a great job; he is very approachable and demonstrates a good level of industry knowledge.those personal relationships between our relationship management, technical support, customer services and you are, and thatis exactly how we want to keep them. The feedback provided from these conversations influences our product and service strategy.A snapshot of the current thoughts across our customer base provides us with great insight on how we can improve the value and the outcomes for our customers. We have partnered with Investor in Customers (IIC), who are one of the UK’s biggest Customer Experience consultancies and have been working with many household names (National Trust, Legal & General) since 2006 to continuously improve their customers’ experience.The IIC runs a yearly assessment based on feedback from clients and employees, the main areas of the survey are understanding customer needs, delivering products and services which meet those needs, delivering first class service and engendering loyalty. The assessment gives us at Synaptic an insight into our customers’ experience and enables us to improve our product and service offering.We would like to invite you to take part in our customer feedback programme – and will be approaching our customers with regards to the experience questionnaire in the next few months. As ever, we would be very grateful for your time, this is a great to fill the questionnaire in. This is a great opportunity for us to make sure we really get what makes you tick and that we match our productsand services to your needs. We are driven bygetting things right first time, being easy to do business with, and enhancing our quality relationships. We can have the most rigorous software testing regime and provide quicker agile development, but at the end of the day, our product quality will still be measured in customer-perceived quality.We invite all of our clients to share regular feedback with us – we promise to listen and act on each piece of feedback passed overto us to continuously improve the products and services we offer to benefit our clients.If you would like to send us feedback or discuss any of our products and services, please contact our Customer Service Team on customerservices@synaptic.co.uk or speak to any member of our team.“Support team member was fantastic and sorted everything out in one call - she explained and showed me everything on the system and I fully understand where it went wrong, so if it happens again i’ll know for next time without having to call”]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[A NEW DIRECTIONFOR PROTECTIONBright Grey has now become Royal London. While our name and look has changed, our vision for protection remains the same. We’re committed to providing cover that matters and a great experience for you and your clients. And we’re going to keep building on the good stuff as Royal London. That way we can grow our relationship and keep us both moving in the right direction.The Royal London Mutual Insurance Society Limited is authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority. The firm is on the Financial Services Register, registration number 117672. It provides life assurance and pensions. Registered in England and Wales number 99064. Registered office: 55 Gracechurch Street, London EC3V 0RL44AD0995]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[55How trends in healthcare will start a protection revolutionGwilym Morrison | Senior Analytics Manager | Royal LondonAt the Centre for Biomedical Informatics in an affluent suburb of the San Francisco Bay Area city of Palo Alto, a revolution in healthcare is being fashioned.Within these walls, researchers are detecting and diagnosing rare diseases using data. They have trained machine learning algorithms to be able to spot complex patterns in the health records. This allows them to assess the risk of any particular individual having a potentially life threatening condition by passing their health records through the trained algorithms. It’s hoped that this will result in a cheap and efficient way of screening for rare diseases, including certain forms of cancer, post-stroke complications and even to detect undiagnosed injuries in professional football players.They’re also able to use these algorithms to predict which patients are at risk of relapse or complications after a hospital visit. Applied before the patients have been discharged, medical staff can arrange for additional care and support for those that are most at risk.New sources of data, such as electronic health records and patient treatment profiles, combined with advanced techniques like machine learning are heralding a new data- driven age in medicine. Over the next decade, these trends will revolutionise medicine.They’ll address some of the most fundamental issues in healthcare today, such as shortages in primary care staff and the treatment of complex chronic disorders that are becoming increasingly common. Data-driven medicine will also feature much more tailoring and personalisation of treatments to individualsThe implications for protectionHealthcare analytics are addressing the same questions as those we’re interested in from a medical underwriting point of view. Both are about assessing the risks of future medical events occurring. Life insurance can use these same techniques to underwrite individuals. And just as healthcare analytics is personalising medical solutions, underwriting analytics based on machine learning will allow the personalisation of the underwriting journey.In the very near future it will be possible to tailor underwriting requirements, including questions, to individuals based on applying machine learning to their health data.The effects of all this on the protection industry are likely to be profound. The tailoringof underwriting to individual customers is likely to result in dynamic application forms and journeys, giving a much-improved customer experience. New channels will appear andnew customers will be encouraged to buy protection by innovative propositions led by this data-driven underwriting. It will also allow providers to offer cover to individuals with conditions that mean they would otherwise struggle to find cover.Data and analytics are set to transform many other activities in the protection industry, including pricing, customer insight, fraud detection, product design and marketing.This is an exciting time to be working in analytics in protection. The underlying technology has reached a state of maturity that allows relatively easy adoption. Richer and more comprehensive sources of data are also now available. Our expectation is that most providers in our industry will be making significant investments in this area over the next few years.This is a Royal London promotion.]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[56Page needs logo and brand colCritical Illness – The life lottery the UK loves to playAndrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskIn the family of insurance I like to think of Life, Critical Illness and Income Protection as three grown up brothers. Life insurance is the smooth, successful, slightly lazy older brother. Income Protection is mummy’s boy – smothered with love and able to move back home whenever things get too hard. Critical Illness is the middle child – just getting on and doing his thing, getting into a scrape every now and again but charming it’s way through the situation.If you were new to the UK and read the trade or general media you would not think that Critical Illness outsold Income Protection by 4x in 2015. Over £112m of new business CI premiums were written in 2015. People like to buy this product – no matter how much time we spend telling them that they should really buy something else.Seven Families has been a rare, superbly co- ordinated industry campaign to put the focus on Income Protection. It has succeeded in telling stories rather than explaining statistics, and showing that what we insist on calling Protection is really People Insurance.By comparison it is hard to find a positive article about the Critical Illness product that isn’t a direct advert for a company’s product. Any articles on Critical Illness in the national press are stories where something has gonewrong for the customer and their claim has been declined.Clearly “Man Bites Dog” is a better news story than “Dog Bites Man”, and I fear the day that “Insurer Pays Claim” makes front page news. Nevertheless the lack of a general narrative as to why Critical Illness is still a relevant, popular product is confusing. In simple terms increasing CI sales by the same % as IP sales would mean more people had People Insurance.The industry has taken the view that it should unite to try and grow the Income Protection market. By contrast for Critical Illness we seem to assume that the size of the marketis established, and everyone concentrates on fighting to retain and increase share rather than growing the market.Do we really think that we have saturated the market for Critical Illness? Are people really happy just to hack away at other propositions around definition tweaks and numbers?The groupthink that pervades our industry means that too often people tend to silence their real challenges with Income Protection. While they see the sensible values of the product there are fundamental issues that still exist to varying degrees in IP products today.o]]></page><page Index="57" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours57We should build on the human instinct that people want to protect themselves (and their families) against the big scary things happening in life, and come together to share and promote these Critical Illness stories.- The rewards aren’t big enough to sell it - “it’s harder to sell – so I want more commission”- The claims triggers aren’t perceived to bescaryenough-“jointpainandstress? I won’t ever let myself get something like that”- Occupation definitions are confusing - “what other occupations could I really do?”- The underwriting process is complicated, and penal -“I got an exclusion for twisting my ankle playing football”- Uncertainty about claims payments and state benefits - “can you guarantee this won’t affect my state benefit”- The name is rubbish - “it protects SOME of your income IF YOU’RE SICK”- The monthly nature of claim payment means the figures look low – “£1,500 a month? I’d rather have £150,000 up front”Compare these points to Critical Illness- The name is great (even if not especially accurate)- The claims triggers are scary and real- The headline claim amount is on a different scale- You get a lump sum to spend however you want without interference from insurersI believe these are the reasons that CI will continue to hugely outsell IP, and when you hear claimant’s stories I am very comfortable that it does so.I’vebeenluckyenoughtohearmanypowerful testimonials from people who have received Critical Illness payments. Two of the most memorable were at a FOCUS (Faculty of Claims and Underwriting Scotland) event.A lady who had breast cancer talked of how much the money had helped her survive a loss of income, as well as paying for the things you don’t think about – hospital parking fees and the like.A gentleman who had prostate cancer was clear that he viewed himself as lucky –not just to have survived his scary diagnosis of prostate cancer, but lucky to have got a big payoutfor it. He had written his bucket list and was living his dreams as a result of the payment – thriving not surviving.His story divided the room – and has divided people I have shared this with ever since. Marketeers saw potential as a new way to sell the product, and turn the conversation away from illness and suffering. Many technicians were genuinely outraged at this and questioning the validity of an indemnity product being used in this way.To me the key thing is getting stories like this in front of future clients out there – stories that don’t stop with the cheque but showwhat happened next. We need to share how the money transformed their and their family’s lives in whatever real, honest ways it did.We need to embrace the continuing popularity ofCriticalIllness.Weshouldbe telling everyone in their 30s and 40s with a young family who doesn’t have the product that “people like you typically buy this”.The latest Swiss Re Term and Health Watch figures shows an increase in IP sales of 11% to 107,302 and a decrease in CI sales of 7.6% to 430,127 in 2015. The relative success of 10,000 more IP sales highlights what can be done. We need to make sure that we don’t get so distracted by making the case for our little darling IP that we forget to talk about it’s middle brother.We should build on the human instinct that people want to protect themselves (and their families) against the big scary things happening in life, and come together to share and promote these Critical Illness stories.COVER ME NOW]]></page><page Index="58" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[58Income protection – it’s time to think differentlyJustin Harper | Head of Intermediary Marketing | LV=How protecting your client’s income can ensure good customer outcomesThe LV= Risk Reality Calculator: an adviser’s perspective“The LV= Risk Reality Calculator is a great tool which I use to help introduce protection needs to my clients. Many of them expect to discuss their life cover but often do not realise the far greater need for income protectionand critical illness cover. The calculator is quick to use, easy to understand and personalised for each client. A great tool which has become an intrinsic part of my protection chat.”Income protection (IP) can be more difficult to recommend compared to other types of cover. Clients think ‘it won’t happen to me’ and for some advisers, critical illness and life insurance are perceived as the easier sale.Industry figures speak volumes: critical illness sales outstrip IP nearly five to one , despite long-term sickness being the biggest risk we’re all exposed to.The 7Families initiative and continued provider focus has placed more emphasis on IP, and latest figures suggest sales for the first half of 2015 were up 16% compared to 2014. However, more work needs to be done.Putting income at the forefront of the advice processAt LV=, we encourage advisers to protect clients against all eventualities and recommend a full protection plan: income protection, critical illness and life insurance. We also suggest talking about ‘scenarios’, the likelihood of the event happening and how clients can be financially prepared.Think about the LV= Risk Reality Calculator. Advisers need just four basic details (age, sex, smoker status and retirement age) to calculatethe likelihood of clients:• Being unable to work for two months or more (due to illness)• Suffering a serious illness• Dying• And the probability of any of these happening before retirementThe calculator doesn’t mention ‘products’ and instead focuses on the chances of these events happening. Talking about scenarios (long-term sickness, suffering a serious illness) at thestart, then confirming the chances of them happening, should make it far easier to then introduce the solution.We recently surveyed more than 700 advisers to find out their views on IP. Of those who regularly sell it (500 advisers), 25% usethe Risk Reality Calculator as part of their recommendation process3.Our research also identified budget planners as the most popular tool when recommending IP, helping commitments and how income is the thing that holds it all together. Another popular way of showing clients how much they have to lose is to use an income shortfall calculator. It shows clients what their income would fall to if they didn’t have the right cover in place and had to rely on state benefits alone.www.riskreality.co.uk/gen]]></page><page Index="59" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[59www.shortfallcalculator.lv.comDINKYs, DINOs and the growing IP opportunityYou might have heard of DINKYs (Double Income, No Kids Yet), but what about DINOs (Double Income, No Options households)? DINOs are households of co-habiting couples who are dependent on both incomes to make ends meet, and there are an estimated 3.2 million in the UK , highlighting the traditional family model (dad works and mum stays at home to look after the kids) has changed. The financial risks for DINOs are very real: a couple, both aged 30 have a 64% chance of one of them being unable to work for two monthsor more before they retire , representing a significant IP opportunity for advisers.Ski downhillRecommending cover to protect against all eventualities is fine in principle, but for some clients, simply isn’t affordable. If price is an issue, there are ways to bring down the cost - we call it ‘skiing downhill’ at LV=.• Choose a ‘budget’ plan. These products can be significantly cheaper than ‘full’ IP and operate a limited claim payment period – two years with LV=.• Increase the waiting period. It’s a good idea to base cover on how long your clientcan wait before their policy pays out - looking at employer sick pay entitlement or savings is a good place to start.• Reduce the cover. What monthly IP benefit does your client need, rather than want? If some outgoings aren’t vital, you could recommend a lower level of cover with your client cutting out non-essentials whilst they’re claiming. Or, if your client’s partner works and contributes to the household income, you could recommend enough cover to pay a regular outgoing or debt (like the mortgage or rent)• Reduce the IP term. Does your client need cover for a particular period only? You could look at ending the policy in line with their mortgage for example.• Recommend decreasing life and critical illness. If your client has a repayment mortgage, recommending decreasing life and critical illness cover should free up some budget for IP.Wake up to IP: Part TwoLast year, more than 2,000 advisers attended our Wake up to IP events. Designed to help overcome common objections against IP, the seminar programme was supported by one- to-one ‘conscience coaching’ from the LV= account management team.The events explored the state benefit system, helping advisers understand the complicated claim assessment process. For example, the Employment Support Allowance application form is 57 pages long, and end-to-end, measures higher than 21⁄2 giraffes.Some of the advisers who attended saw a significant uplift in their (LV=) IP business, andour latest research suggests there is still plenty of appetite for more training events.So, we’ve updated the content to make it even more compelling, and real, for 2016. Events this year will focus on helping advisers deliver good customer outcomes, and give them even more support and tools to recommend cover to protect against all eventualities.Let’s make a commitment and talk about protecting income in a different wayIP doesn’t have to be the poor relation of the protection family. If you’re struggling with getting recommendations over the line, or simply feel like refreshing your existing advice process, visit the LV= Adviser website www.lv.com/wakeuptoip, where you’ll find our Risk Reality Calculator, as well as adviser support and tools.1 Mintel, based on 2014 policies sold2 Gen Re’s Protection Pulse, 20153 LV= income protection research, conducted February – March 2016 4 Both incomes to survive’ press release. Research by OpiniumResearch on behalf of LV=, October 2015.5 Results based on a non-smoking male and female couple bothretiring at age 65 as calculated by the LV= Risk Reality Calculator]]></page><page Index="60" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[60Scottish Widows Protect:helping advisers to meet the needs of modern protection customersJohnny Timpson | Financial Protection Market & Industry Affairs Manager | Scottish WidowsIn March 1812, a number of eminent Scotsmen gathered in the Royal Exchange Coffee Rooms in Edinburgh, to consider setting up ‘a general fund for securing provisions to widows, sisters and other females’ impacted by the Napoleonic wars. Out of this Scottish Widows’ Fund and Life Assurance Society – Scotland’s first mutual life office – was formed.Much has changed in the intervening years, but the need to help others protect against the unexpected is as relevant today as it was back then. What has changed is how this protection should be delivered to meet the needs of modern customers. Our new intermediary protection proposition Scottish Widows Protect, is a flexible menu-based proposition that offers both personal and business solutions, and supports financial advisers in offering holistic financial planning to meet the changing needs of modern clients.Since the financial crisis in 2008 the outlook has felt more uncertain for households and businesses, with the subsequent fragile recovery impacting both employment and the housing market. We know the here and now tends to dominate when it comes to assessing our own needs and spending. However itis this uncertainty that makes it even more important to have an appropriate plan in place to protect homes and families.To support financial advisers when theyhave those financial planning conversations with clients we’ve developed a dedicated protection website with support materials, tools and calculators to help bring the need for protection to life. We’ve also built in flexibility to meet clients’ changing protection needs with Scottish Widows Protect offering a range of covers that can be mixed and matched as required.Scottish Widows Protect is an online proposition, built based on intermediaries’ feedback and designed to meet their needs. It offers, among other things, underwriting outcome tools, pipeline tracking, editable trust documents with email submission, andpost-sale flexibility. Our service support has dedicated face -to-face and phone- based intermediary protection sales teams, a pre-submission underwriting helpdesk and individual case owners who take end -to -end ownership of each and every case.We also want to help intermediaries ensure their clients stay protected, with a customer engagement team that acts proactively to contact customers at risk of lapsing. Our annual plan summary also provides advisers with a great opportunity to revisit clients to review their protection needs and build an ongoing relationship.Through our underwriting, Scottish Widows Protect aim to provide instant decisions and access to immediate cover to help give clients peace of mind. We have over 16 years experience in developing automatic]]></page><page Index="61" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[61To support financial advisers when they have financial planning conversations with clients we’ve developed a dedicated protection website with support materials, tools and calculators to help bring the need for protection to life.underwriting rules, one of the most mature rule sets, allowing us to offer decisions for the majority of cases. We also have over 100 years collective experience within our underwriting team who write those rules. When an application is made online, we can capture over 10,000 different types of disclosures which can be instantly assessed by a bank of over 2,000 rules. This is something that is impossible to re-produce in a paper based application.Where we do ask for evidence, although we’re able to capture full disclosures during the online questionnaire, we only target the evidence we need to provide timely decisions. For cases that require manual underwriting an individual case manager is allocated, andif further information is needed to supportan application a tele-underwriter will contact clients which often means not having to contact their doctor, and speeds up the application process.Thankfully the proportion of people who have to make a claim is relatively small, but this means that many intermediaries have never experienced a claims process. That’s why Scottish Widows’ heritage and history of paying claims can be reassuring – we paid out our first claim in July 1816 and last year we paid out £875k per day in life and critical illness claims.To ensure clients are supported throughout the claims process, they will be given a claims assessor who will stay with them throughout the process. This gives them consistencyin support at a very difficult time. We also offer clients’ access to Scottish Widows Care, provided in association with RedArc, which offers emotional support and practical advice to clients and their families from the start of the claim process.From May 16th Scottish Widows Protect is available through Webline. We’re confident that this new offering meets the age old need to help protect against the unexpected, but also supports intermediaries in providing choice for their clients.About The AuthorJohnny has over 37 years’ business development experience in bank, independent intermediary, direct, partnership and joint venture distribution channels. Before joining Scottish Widows in 1987 Johnny workedfor Commercial Union. His current role is supporting the development of financial protection need awareness, advocacy and advisory capability within Scottish Widows Protect. Johnny has been a member of numerous protection industry taskforcesboth past and present, bringing his wealthof experience and unique insight and knowledge to bear. Most recently he’s represented Scottish Widows on the Seven Families Project, leading the Industry Affairs Workstream.About UsScottish Widows is the life, pensions and investment provider of the Lloyds Banking Group. The company was founded in Edinburgh in 1815 and today provides a product range that includes life cover, critical illness, income protection, pensions, annuities and savings and investment products to more than 6.4 million customers.Scottish Widows Protect launched in 2015 and offers a range of protection solutions specifically designed for the intermediary market. A flexible menu-based proposition it offers both personal and business solutions, and supports financial advisers in offering holistic financial planning to meet the changing needs of modern clients.For more information on Scottish Widows Protect please visit our Protect Centre where you can find out about the products we offer, our underwriting approach, and access our online tools and calculators.www.scottishwidowsprotect.co.uk]]></page><page Index="62" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[62We’ve improved: Synaptic WeblineStuart Carmichael | Head of Proposition | Synaptic Software LimitedStuart Carmichael presents the latest version of the industry’s favourite Protection and Annuity quote and e-apply portalSynaptic Webline has been a market leader for some years now, positioning itself at the forefront of technology, committed to making the process of buying Protection as smooth as possible. This means that Webline powers some of the most successful Protectionsales businesses in the country, either fully integrated into their own back office and sales process, or in the broker portal.Overall in the UK, Protection sales have not shown a lot of growth over recent years, something that troubles us all in the industry, but Webline has countered this trend to the extent that it helps facilitate up to 20% of UK term business. In 2015, there were over 8million quote requests, representing a 68% increase from 2014. We are proud of this contribution to the insurance that protects our nation’s families, and are keen to build further on this success. That’s why as a company we are investing heavily to continue to improve Synaptic Webline and cement its status as the nation’s favourite portal. We are looking forward to several announcements later this year of innovations that will be made available to our customers, that we believe will revolutionise Protection sales and significantly increase the levels of Protection cover across the land.If you are thinking about how to improvethe way you sell Protection products, please contact us to discuss your requirements. The new Webline user interface is available at no extra costs (rrp. £11 per month, per firm). You may even discover that you can gain access free of charge if you subscribe to any of our other premium tools.New Synaptic Webline designUsers will find all of the pre-existing functionality in the new version, in a fresh and clear layout. We think the refinementto the dynamic tables will help advisers and brokers save time and money when compared to similar services.respectively.Some Webline featuresThe “profile” for your account can be tailored to your needs, including:• setyourownprovider/productpanel• setcommissionsacrificelevels,byproductandprovider• createadditionallog-insforeachuserinyourfirm(atno extra charge).• auto-populationoflog-inandclientdataMulti-Benefit toolIf the adviser chooses to quote against more than one cover type, the system automatically assesses if that combination can be supported by a Multi-Benefit product.The service will then allow the adviser to see the cost comparison of multiple standalone products versus a single Multi-Benefit product premium, which could be a more time and cost effective solution for the client.]]></page><page Index="63" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[63The next two screens show results for Income Protection and Level term respectively.Whether you are:- An existing Synaptic customer that has never used Webline- An existing Webline user who has forgotten their log in details- A Protection adviser wishing to upgrade their portalRegister for a free 30 day trial, or contact us on 0800 783 4477 and we can help.We would also love to know what you think about the changes we have made and any other changes you would like to see. Please call our support team on 0800 028 0033 (option 1) or email us at support@synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="64" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[A NEW BREED OFMODEL PORTFOLIOSAs the markets continue to face high volatility; now more than ever Advisers stand to benefit from working with specialist investment managers to support their investment process and manage clients’ money.FE Invest offers a new breed of risk optimised model portfolios targeted at the complete range of investor risk profiles. Our approach leverages the efficiency of cutting edge technology with the oversight of experienced professionals to deliver an optimal investment service that will add real value to your business and your clients.www.feinvest.netCONTACT US ATenquiries@financialexpress.net or 0207 534 7667 BOOK A FREE DEMO]]></page></pages></Search>