<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q2 2017Selection of industry features for the professional adviserEdition highlights 4 new Synaptic Research propositions:• NEW Synaptic Risk Ratings now available in Synaptic Product and Fund• NEW Synaptic Income modelling and Drawdown tool• NEW Cover Me Now - guaranteed premium, immediate cover for Term protection• NEW Synaptic integration with Intelligent OfficeRise and Rise of ResearchResearch gaining the prominence it deservesInside...Investment Strategy Analysis›› Russell Investments ›› BNY MellonDue Diligence›› FinalytiQ›› Rayner Spencer Mills›› Tavistock Wealth›› Vanguard AM]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC SOFTWAREGet your Protection clients on risk immediately with themost efficient process available in the market!Cover Me Now is a brand new protection on-boarding system, powered by familiar Webline technology. It offers an Adviser-facing platform and has been designed with the customer firmly in mind. By combining Synaptic Software’s digital know-how with a guaranteed priced life insurance product, this new portal delivers a step-change in Adviser efficiency and creates a hassle-free Customer experience.Cover Me NowNew Cover Me NowClient DetailsI’m covered!Product Details17 Medical QuestionsResultsE-applyApply On RiskResultsPayment DetailsClient DetailsUnderwritingCurrent JourneyAwait DecisionProduct DetailsMedical Questions(30-40) SignIllustrationDeclarationFor more information about Cover Me Nowplease call 0800 783 4477 or visit www.synaptic.co.uk/covermenow]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[How to hook a high net worth client 04 Nick French, Russell InvestmentsWhy a multi-asset approach can help to 06 protect you from the threat of inflationPaul Flood, BNY MellonReview to a Kill 08 Mark Polson, the lang catMyth-busting the active versus 10 passive debateL&G Investment ManagersThe good, the bad and the ugly 12 Henderson RoweFinding the value in Value 15 Alastair Mundy, Investec Asset ManagementReal life investing: F&C MM Lifestyle 16 Fund RangeBMO Global Asset ManagementIntelliflo’s Intelligent Office now 18 integrates with Synaptic research software Stuart Carmichael, Synaptic Software LimitedThe New Synaptic Research Tool 20 Looking after other people’s money 22David ‘Dan’ Norman, TCF InvestmentsWhat a difference an ‘M’ makes 24 David Holloway, RathbonesUsing Investment Trusts 26 Ben Conway, Hawksmoor InvestmentManagementWhy does trying to “time the market” so 28 often fail?Ben Raven, Tavistock WealthNatural yield: a totally bonkers retirement 30 income strategyAbraham Okusanya, FinalytiQHow do you select a DFM? 32 Geoff Mills, Rayner Spencer MillsTakeovers and investing for the long term 34 James Nield, Thesis Asset ManagementFCA Asset Management Review: Great 36 news for investorsRichard Withers, Vanguard Asset ManagementNEW! Get your Synaptic Risk Ratings here 40 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Risk Table 42Income Protection: cover that works when 50 your clients can’tAviva5 things that will change about the way 52 protection policies are underwritten in thenext 5 years (and a couple of things that won’t)Andrew Wibberley, Alea RiskCover Me Now – 54 Protection Cover as it should bePaul Quarendon, Synaptic Software LimitedWhen the regulator began to publish its thinking about suitabilityin previous reviews, a core requirement was put square centre: good research. Judging by several current headlines, e.g. ‘Fears grow over advisers’ investment due diligence’ (Money Marketing 27.04.17), you’d think some parts of the industry were only just switching on to the value of good (Synaptic) research.This seems so simple, but perhaps it’s not. We are aware of heavily marketed tools used by advisers where the charging datais frequently incorrect, but use of the outcomes from the research which are routinely wrong are considered acceptable. Sometimes it feels like our industry is performing in an examination where getting the answers wrong doesn’t matter.In regards to research and risk, I went toa large industry event recently where the director of a well know research house was presenting, explaining that the role of an investment committee was ‘to take a view’ on the likely growth of different asset classes in order to effectively set asset allocations for different risk categories. We all know of course that this is not how it works. Research analysis of successful investment strategies teaches us to avoid undue speculation, including the kind that make ‘calls’ on major trend inflection points.A good story is not the same as good research – which must inform the full range of viable outcomes.Good research builds in contingencies, monitors progress, allows adjustments to be made where necessary and sets the tolerances for ongoing losses at sustainable levels to allow long term benefits to accrue.At Synaptic we have been thinking about the importance of good research in the contextof our new retirement income modellingand drawdown illustration tool (currently undergoing testing and available Q3 ’17). Retirement planning is such an important area to get right, so there is no room for sloppiness that could undermine the best possible advice and outcomes for customers due to poor data, poor methodology or poor replicability.We are delighted also to be announcingthe arrival of the Synaptic Risk Ratings into Synaptic Product and Fund, so all advisers can benefit from the Synaptic risk metrics when dealing with ‘Capacity for Loss’. Check it out!Abraham, who features in this edition, is controversial, but his detractors fall away when they fail to challenge his research which is deep and serious. Further proof if any were needed that research is truly the ultimate weapon.Eric ArmstrongEditorContact DetailsSynaptic Software LimitedFusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AASales: 0800 783 4477To sign up for Connection magazine visitwww.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Hardmannaomi.hardman@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969The Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expresses throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.CONTENTSResearch is gaining the prominence it deserves3]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4How to hook a high net worth clientNick French | Managing Director, Head of Wealth Management | Russell InvestmentsTax crackdown by HMRC will not deter advisers from focusing on high-net-worth segment.The high-net-worth (HNW) space has become a little toxic. According to a National Audit Office report in November, one-third of the UK’s HNWs are currently subject to an HMRC inquiry into their tax affairs. Worryingly for advisers, HMRC has floated proposals to sanction those who market schemes.Will these moves make the HNW segment less attractive to financial advisers?Leveraging existing HNW clientsHNW clients are prized by financial advisers the world over and the increased scrutinyis unlikely to change this. In fact, the desire to attract HNW individuals has neverbeen stronger given their rising numbers and growing needs. In the light of the tax clampdown, advisers will consider how they provide services, but they are unlikely to withdraw services altogether.Why are HNWs so prized? Well, not onlydo they have sizeable pools of money to manage, but they represent a marketing tool that enables advisers to gain access to other HNWs and further pools of money.In addition, while HNW clients may materialise after the sale of a business or other windfall, further transactions often follow over the years. This puts the adviser in pole position to help the client manage subsequent transactions and the cashflows from them.Show your competenceSome advisers have no HNW clients. Given the networking potential from leveraging a single such client, making considerable efforts to capture one seems a reasonable business proposition.It pays to consider their real needs, rather than perceived needs. They may at some stage want access to exotic investments, but this is unlikely to be an immediate priority. In fact, any kind of investment pitch as an opening gambit is probably unwise: if all you do is manage a client’s money, yourAny kind of investment pitch as an opening gambit is probably unwise: if all you do is manage a client’s money, your relationship with them is likely to ebb and flow with the markets.]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[5It is essential to have a professional team in place and a clear plan to attract HNWs. If you look at your competitors and think they got lucky, that they were there at the right time and in the right place, you have probably drawn the wrong conclusion.relationship with them is likely to ebb and flow with the markets.In our opinion, a successful, longer-term wealth management relationship is underpinned by more fundamental needs. Many HNWs are juggling many financial and non-financial issues. Some are utterly unprepared for any potential hiccup in their lives. So the starting place is the will, insurance, strategic financial planning, tax, pension vehicles and, only after that, investment strategies.If HNWs can clearly see they will feel more comfortable as a result, trust starts to develop.How to provide a complete serviceOf course, there is little point in offering to organise the lives of HNWs if you are not set up to fulfil the task.Some advisers have created teams of professionals to help entrepreneur clients in particular. This may involve partnering with a business valuation specialist, a corporate financier, a private banker and lawyers.The business valuation team allows the entrepreneur to value the business away from the scrutiny of the marketplace and fix any shortcomings to increase the value of the business before a sale. The corporate financeteam assists potential buyers by providing financing and moving the deal along at the right speed. Overseeing the transaction are the lawyers who are familiar with the whole team. The proceeds of sale are managed by the adviser, possibly partnering with an asset manager such as Russell Investments, who can advise on short and longer-term needs.Unearthing prospectsPutting all this into practice requires identifying clients who require complete wealth management.Sometimes, of course, a client channel will develop from an existing client or clients. When developing new channels, it makes sense to assess which industries are growing or have undergone strong growth.The HNW is different from the mass affluent channel in that it is insufficient to be friendly and honest. While these qualities help, more important for HNWs is useful information delivered clearly, in a timely manner and allied to practical assistance.Take dentistry, which has become a growth industry in the UK as middle class wealth has increased and as more people are unable to access NHS dentistry. Dentists are entrepreneurs and have business needs,including insurance, benefits and pension needs for staff, retirement planning, tax filing and succession planning.Private dentists tend to wear a lot of hats and need help juggling key tasks. Advisers can win their trust by creating services to meet some or all of these needs and making the entrepreneurial dentist’s life easier.Conclusion – make a plan, and use itIn short, to succeed in this space, it is essential to have a professional team in place and a clear plan to attract HNWs. If you look at your competitors and think they got lucky, that they were there at the right time andin the right place, you have probably drawn the wrong conclusion. Most have made considerable effort to understand client’s real needs and serve them better as a result.www.helpingadvisers.co.uk For financial advisers only.This document is issued by Russell Investments Limited, a company incorporated in England and Wales under registered number 02086230 and with its registered office at: Rex House, 10 Regent Street, London SW1Y 4PE. Telephone +44 (0)20 7024 6000.Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority, 25 The North Colonnade, Canary Wharf, London E14 5HS. UKR-2017-04-06-0488.]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[6Why a multi-asset approach may help to protect you from the threat of inflationPaul Flood | Lead manager of Newton Multi-Asset Income FundMounting inflationary pressures mean increasing numbers of investors are looking to protect themselves by adopting a multi-asset approach to investing, says Newton portfolio manager Paul Flood.investors to widen their search for yield across a growing range of asset classes. This ever more urgent hunt for yield might be leading them into assets with characteristics they may not necessarily understand and, as a result, they might be exposing themselves to higher levels of risk.Despite these risks, Flood believes that the current climate presents investors with strong opportunities via multi-asset investing. He thinks multi-asset investing is as much about the assets investors do not own, as it is about those they do own, which can display attractive qualities. Key to investment success in the current climate will be the ability to access assets that can offer some degree of inflation proofing.Flood thinks this is not always possible when investing in mainstream equities and bonds, nor indeed when one diversifies into less mainstream areas such as high yield bonds. Historically, Flood notes that equities have provided inflation protection over the long1 https://www.ft.com/content/a0c3fce4-d0e2-11e6-b06b-680c49b4b4c0 2 Jan 20173 https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/03/bank-of-england-rate-cuts-2017-growth-forecast-inflation 3 Nov 2016 4 Bloomberg figures as at 28 February 2017term, but he believes this is not guaranteed, and in the current climate where UK 10-year government bonds are yielding 1.1%4, fixed- income investors may not be compensated for the corrosive effects of inflation. Within high yield bonds, the extra yield paid to investors to compensate them for the higher risk of owning the debt of a less secure company, known as the spread, has compressed to such an extent that investors will have to be highly selective in this asset class if they are to avoid significant losses.Fiscal policy on the agendaFlood sees fiscal policy as firmly back on the agenda as the UK transitions away from a deflationary environment. This, he notes, is encouraging investment managers to spend more time identifying inflation-linked assets and to prioritise the ‘inflation proofing’ of their clients’ portfolios as best they can.So what are the inflation-proofing options available for investors? Newton advocates a multi-asset approach based on rigorous stockAs the UK prepares to leave the European Union, a post-Brexit weakening of the pound is just one development sparking investor concerns about rising inflationary pressures1.The headline rate of inflation measured by the Office for National Statistics (ONS) is expected to rise to about 3% from a current rate of 1.8% this year, and the Organisation of Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) has also warned that rising inflation will hit British households2.The Bank of England has separately forecast that inflation will accelerate above its 2% target in 2017 and 2018 before falling back in 20203, increasing the chances of an interest rate hike within the next few months.Increasing riskAccording to Paul Flood, lead manager of Newton’s Multi-Asset Income Fund, a fund that aims to deliver a sustainable monthly income, both inflationary concerns and the current low- return environment have encouraged many2 https://www.theguardian.com/business/2017/mar/07/food-inflation-doubles-uk-shoppers-feel-pinch 7 March 2017]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[7Unlike cash and most conventional bonds, assets with inflation-linked contracts can be attractive for long-term savers because their investments have a degree of inflation protection built in.selection and suggests that within a multi-asset portfolio, exposure to assets such as renewable energy and infrastructure, which have very little sensitivity to the economic cycle, can afford a degree of inflation protection to investors.According to Flood, another potential benefit of multi-asset investing is the ability to allow wide diversification, which helps to balance risk and return across a range of assets over time.Inflation protectionFlood believes that for those looking to save, and especially for those looking to save over the longer term, protecting assets against the potential ravages of inflation is paramount. Unlike cash and most conventional bonds, assets with inflation-linked contracts canbe attractive for long-term savers because their investments have a degree of inflation protection built in.However, Flood cautions that the sheer range of multi-asset investments on offer ultimately calls for a cautious approach to asset allocation and, where necessary, expert advice. He believes investors need to be careful how they allocate their investments and to try to avoid exposure to overvalued assets, or those with overlapping exposure.The Newton Multi-Asset Income Fund aims to do exactly that. Newton’s long-term global thematic approach to investment adds rigour to the investment process and lends itselfto the identification of valuation anomaliesin global markets. Having a single portfolio management approach, where the portfolios are directly invested rather than being funds of funds, gives the fund manager full flexibility atboththeassetallocationandsecurity selection level. This allows Flood to focus on specific securities where he believes valuations and income-generating potential are most attractive.For the increasing number of investors looking to protect themselves from the rising inflation threat, while at the same time seeking to generate a sustainable income, an unconstrained multi-asset approach with the flexibility to access the most attractively valued opportunities is worthy of serious consideration.For more information, please contact BNY Mellon:www.bnymellonim.com+44 (0) 207 163 8888 salessupport@bnymellon.comIMPORTANT INFORMATIONPast performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments can fall. Investors may not get backthe amount invested. For Professional Clients only. This is a financial promotion and is not investment advice. For a full list of risks applicable to this fund, please refer to the Prospectus or other offering documents. Before subscribing, investors should read the most recent Prospectus, financial reports and KIID for each fund in which they want to invest. Go to www.bnymellonim. com. Investments should not be regarded as short-term and should normally be held for at least five years. The Fund is a sub-fund of BNY Mellon Investment Funds, an open-ended investment company with variable capital (ICVC) with limited liability between sub-funds. Incorporated in England and Wales: registered number IC27. The Authorised Corporate Director (ACD) is BNY Mellon Fund Managers Limited (BNY MFM), incorporated in England and Wales: No. 1998251. Registered address: BNY Mellon Centre, 160 Queen Victoria Street, London EC4V 4LA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Newton Investment Management Limited (Newton) is authorised andregulatedbytheFinancialConductAuthority. Newton,BNY Mellon Centre, 160 Queen Victoria Street, London EC4V 4LA. Registered in England No. 1371973.Any views and opinions are those of the investment manager, unless otherwise noted. Portfolio holdings are subject to change, for information only and are not investment recommendations. To help continually improve our service and in the interest of security, we may monitor and/or record your telephone calls with us.BNY Mellon Investment Management EMEA Limited and any other BNY Mellon entity mentioned are all ultimately owned by The Bank of New York Mellon Corporate.BNY Mellon is the corporate brand of The Bank of New York Mellon Corporation and its subsidiaries. Newton Investment Management Limited (Newton) is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Newton, BNY Mellon Centre, 160 Queen Victoria Street, London EC4V 4LA. Registered in England No. 1371973.Issued in the UK by BNY Mellon Investment Management EMEA Limited, BNY Mellon Centre, 160 Queen Victoria Street, London EC4V 4LA. Registered in England No. 1118580. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. INV00785, 31 Aug 2017Newton Multi-Asset Income Fund IA Mixed Investment 20%-60% Shares IA Mixed Investment 40%-85% Shares IA Flexible InvestmentNote: 15 February 2015.Source: Lipper, 31 March 2017. Inst W Net Acc share class, net of 0.63% annual management charge.Fund performance calculated as total return, including reinvested income net of UK tax and charges, based on net asset value. All figures are in GBP terms. The impact of an initial charge (currently not applied) can be material on the performance of your investment. Further information is available upon request.]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[8Review to a KillMark Polson | Founder | the lang catI was looking back through some stuff from roughly this time lastyear in preparation for writing this quarter’s column, mainly to makesure I wasn’t repeating myself. It’s nice to have the chance to write forpeople, but you have to be a bit careful. Plagiarism is not cool, kids,even of yourself.Anyway, what I found was that the platform sector was in a bit of a lull. Everyone was mucking around with boring old legislation and regulation, and nothing much was happening. Oh, there was going to be a referendum, but everyone knew how that was going to turn out and it was all going to be fine.Spool forward a year and things couldn’tbe more different. We’ve got M&A activity. We’ve got an explosion in bespoke deals. We’ve got digital advice and investing services mixing things up a bit. We’ve had a rash of pricing changes. And we’ve got an FCA probe into platforms and their wily ways coming up.This last is really interesting, and judging by the rictus-like grins on the faces of many providers, that’s ‘interesting’ in the sense of ‘please, make it stop, it burns, IT BURNS, IT HURTS SO MUCH.’We wrote two years ago that ‘platforms are dead’. And yes, we were trolling, but onlya little bit. A troll-ette, you might say. In fact, much of what we wrote about at that time still resonates now, and has an echo in what we know so far will be in scope for the platform market review.We felt that platforms as a sector had become moribund and had failed to live up to their promise. They had disrupted the industry, that’s true, but were more than overduebeing disrupted in their turn. In their desire to capture the middle ground, they had begun to look more and more alike. Functionality had converged, with a massive arms race resulting in a surfeit of bloated, borderline unusable systems. There was little if anything in there for clients – reporting in particular sucked so hard that it, in fact, blew.Few providers were willing to stand out in terms of pricing – and those that did,especially at the sharper end, were the recipients of snarky nonsense from others about deep pockets and sustainability and why it was good for clients to pay twice as much for exactly the same thing. And all were silent on perhaps the biggest failingof all – why a sector which was designedto let investors access ‘institutional’ style share classes of funds continued to pile investors’ money into schmucky retail classes, superclean or otherwise.We also found (and have continued to findin further research waves) that many adviser platform-enabled propositions are seriously expensive, weighing in at over 2%. Vertically integrated propositions are often worse than that. In a lower-for-longer return environment, for us that’s just too much.To us, this was a full-blown existential identity crisis for the sector in which we made our coin, and which we really wanted to be vibrant]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[9Either the platform industry can get its house in order or the twin pressures of disruptors and regulators will save it the bother.and exciting for years to come. So we wrote what we wrote, and dealt with the inevitable deluge of narky calls and emails about how XYZ platform wasn’t dead at all, thank you very much, just look at its rosy cheeks and so on and so on.And – predictably – not much happened. The Earth rotated on its axis. We all got a bit older. Everyone got on with whatever they were doing before. I perfected a tortilla recipe with chorizo I’ve been trying to get right for a while, and worked out the chords to ‘Shipwreckers’ by James Yorkston (who gave the lang cat its name).And now we have the platform market review. Its thrust? To find out if platforms – across direct and advised – are offering value for investors (not advisers) and if the marketis working in an orderly fashion. Along the way it may ask such questions as ‘Why Use A Platform If You’re Just Holding A Multi- Asset Fund?’ and ‘How Come You All Charge The Same, Except The Fixed Fee One?’ and ‘Why Aren’t Funds Quite A Lot Cheaper On Platforms If You’re Doing All The Aggregating Of The Trading And That?’. These are good questions and ones which need answering.You can expect a bit of disruption as a result of the review. That’s a good thing, if potentially administratively inconvenient. But the herdingwe’ve seen in terms of functionality, service and price; the cosy cabal which has seen pricing revert to the mean of 30-35bps across nearly all the market in the last six months is ripe for a shake-up, and that will be to your clients’ benefit. Note I say ‘your clients’ – these are the people who pay for platforms, and who need to derive much more benefit from then than they do currently.Incidentally, I always like to put a wee plug for our hosts in, and this is as good a point as any – although I don’t know why, it’s not like they pay me to write this stuff. But if you’re looking for a whizzy tool to do lots of comparison stuff in light of disruption and that, Synaptic has one. There. Done.In closing, I’d like to offer up a trend we see increasing considerably over time. We did a wee paper recently with a nice bunch of folks called SEI, who are the technological power behind such fun-loving cats as True Potential, Best Practice’s Fusion Wealth platform and Tilney. The paper was called ‘Level Up’ and you can download it free from SEI’s website.Its thrust was that for firms who are growing very fast or who are at scale already (we can fight about what that means, but let’s go for £500m AUA or more at the moment), retail, ‘nilla advised platforms are not necessarily offering enough control and customisation.If you want the platform you use to looklike you and no-one else, from investment proposition to admin flow to risk management and middle office reconciliations, then you need to start to look a bit wider.There is a growing market (which of course SEI is part of, as are Pershing, IFDL and others) of firms who are providing a sort of enterprise version of platform architecture for firms who want it the way they want it and no other way. This comes with costs and responsibilities and risks, of course, but as advisers firms grow, acquire others or are acquired themselves, that £500m AUA point doesn’t seem so far away in many cases.There are lots of reasons to go down thisroad – and some not to – but the key thing for our purposes is that this approach, used right, allows you to reinvent the platform industry as you want it to be rather than as it is. And that includes fundamental changes in how you use asset management.So it’s all going on. Either the platform industry can get its house in order or the twin pressures of disruptors and regulators will save it the bother.Visit www.langcatfinancial.co.uk for more from Mark and the rest of the lang cats.]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[10Myth-busting the active versus passive debateJustin Onuekwusi CFA | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementThere are many things in life where you’re going to be asked to pick a side. Who are you supporting in the rugby this weekend? Pepsi Max or Diet Coke? Can I still support the UK in Eurovision this year despite Article 50? When it comes to the active versus passive investment debate, it can feel like there are a lot of assumptions being made which support one side over the other and at times, not a lot of evidence to back these up.We intend to ‘bust’ some of these myths and provide some much needed clarity into the conversation. Instead of picking a side, we’ll aim to identify the specific benefits of each style and what investors should be on the lookout for.Myth 1: You get what you pay for‘Star fund managers’ is still a phrase that you hear quite often from within the investment management industry and sometimes even from particularly keen end-clients. The portfolio managers who consistently manage to deliver sector or market-beating returns and therefore command above-average annual fees in return for their virtuosity. We all know that even slightly higher fees can dramatically erode long-term returns but if my guy’s a market- beating genius, surely I end up better off, right?There are actually two distinct problems with this assumption. The first is the idea that without the benefit of hindsight, an investor can identify these geniuses of the future (aprocess which requires extensive, expensive and skilled manager research resources which many find it difficult to deliver upon); and secondly, the sheer level of outperformance required to overcome the compoundingeffect of those higher fees. For all the work that goes into trying to solve the first problem, it is actually the latter which we would argue is the most important.IA Flexbile Investment, 10 year track record higher 10IA Mixed Investment 40-85,10 year track record higher 10return9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1return 9lower return 08 7 6 5 4 3 2 1lower returnFigure 1: Active manager performance by fee decile0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 101 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10lower fee Fee DecileIA Mixed Investment 20-60, 10 year track recordhigher 10higher feeFee DecileIA Mixed Investment 0-35, 10 year track record9 88 77 66 55 44 33 2211lower returnlower feehigher feereturnlower returnhigher 10 return 9lower feeFee Decile higher feelower feeFee Decile higher fee1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 101 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10Performance Decile Performance DecilePerformance Decile Performance Decile]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11Investors should always ensure that they are aware of the changing conditions which might affect their potential returns.Figure 2: Percent of Institutional Fixed Income Managers Outperforming the BenchmarkSource: S&P Dow Jones Indices LLC, eVestment Alliance, CRSP. Data as of Dec. 31, 2015. Past performance is no guarantee of future results. Chart is provided for illustrative purposes.If we take a look at the mixed investment landscape over a period of ten years andsplit the funds on the basis their fees (see Figure 1), those who command the highest in annual management charges are amongst the worst performing. In charging above-average fees, these fund managers are setting the performance bar so high for themselves that they are almost guaranteed to underperform the average manager in the sector. Although we are not looking specifically at fund managers looking to outperform a benchmark here, it is clear that investors will fare far better over the longer term by investing in managers who charge comparatively less each year. Passive multi-asset managers are not immune to this dynamic either; however, given their generally low annual fees they do start in a stronger position.Myth busted: It’s not that lower-cost funds are always going to outperform but when the bar’s lower, you’re more likely to clear it.Myth 2: Index is the best for everything!There are some weird and wonderful indices out there. For those who want to beatthe peat there’s a Whiskey & Spirits Index (WSKY). If you feel like betting that the Vegas house will win, there’s the Dow Jones US Gambling Index. And for the health-conscious, there’s even a Solactive Obesity Index (and an ETF tracker with the rather tongue-in-cheek ticker SLIM). For those investors who swearby passive funds and passive funds alone, it can seem like they are all that’s required in constructing a well-diversified portfolio. Low cost, low maintenance, no hassle, right?However, there are many asset classes where active management is the better choicefor most investors. In the fixed interest space, it might surprise many to learn that active managers thrive in a number of these sub-asset classes (see Figure 2). In global high yield debt, active managers stormed ahead of their comparative index with 85% of them delivering outperformance (alpha). In investment grade, 70% of managerswere able to achieve alpha over and above their passive counterparts. Where market ingredients (liquidity, market capitalisation, cost efficiency, benchmark construction) aren’t optimum, active managers are often better placed to take advantage of these inefficiencies.Myth busted: In some instances, circumstances favour active management over passive. Investors should always ensure that they are aware of the changing conditions which might affect their potential returns.For further information:Call: 0345 070 8684* Email: fundsales@lgim.com Visit: lgim.comImportant NoticeThis is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons.The value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise and investors may get back less than they invest.Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. * Call charges will vary.]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12The good, the bad and the uglyby Henderson RoweWell, Mr Trump’s first few months have certainly been exciting, andhe has even managed to be polite to Theresa May and Vladimir Putin. Economic reform is central to his popular appeal and the market itself has taken a shine to the prospect of an end to ear-popping asset inflation, bottom hugging interest rates and yawning chasms of inequality.Would it be such a bad thing for the worldif America became great again? The trick is going to be managing this without triggering civil war, exploding the debt mountain(s) or grinding world trade to a halt. Luckily we have a Congress positioned to prevent the more outlandish errors and we wish the ‘Great Man’ well. Fingers crossed.Views on the impact of Trumponomics fall into three camps: the Good, the Bad and the Ugly.The GoodTrump promises a regulation bonfire and firehose of infrastructure spending with tax breaks for companies onshoring jobs to the USA. A ‘yuge’ stimulus programme that has sent energy, banking and industrial stocks higher even before it starts. His economic advisory team includes Peter Thiel andElon Musk and even the liberals running tech stocks are salivating at the prospect of overseas cash piles repatriating tax free.According to Goldman Sachs, $150 billionof the $780 billion anticipated S&P 500 buy-backs in 2017 will be driven by overseas cash coming home, liberated at last from repatriation tax. S&P 500 firms are expected to repatriate around $300 billion of their$1 trillion total overseas cash this year. This estimate is based on historical precedent. Following the Homeland Investment Act (HIA), US firms repatriated around 30% of their total overseas cash in 2004.If a tax reform package with the simple goal of boosting domestic investment is passed in 2017, it could feature restrictions on cash usage, so capital spending and cash M&A may experience major boosts. This would be bullish for US equities and may even allow earnings to play catch up with slightly stretched valuations.An investment and buy-back bonanza beckons and growth expectations are rising in tandem across sectors. If the US is kick-started strongly enough, it may even drag the rest of the world up with it, especially those countries that still manage to run a current account surplus with the US. As for protectionism, The Donald is simply righting imbalances skewed unfairly against the US and enshrined in incompetent treaties, so the reshaped world will have more free-trade, not less.]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[13If the US is kick-started strongly enough, it may even drag the rest of the world up with it, especially those countries that still manage to run a current account surplus with the US.The BadNot everybody takes such a rosy view. Trump’s protectionist ideas and anti-free trade rhetoric fly in the face of traditional Republican ideology, not to mention Classical Economics. In the unlikely event Trump manages, despite the opposition of Congress and his own Trade Secretary, to fully implement his protectionist agenda, the conventional view is that we would see a trade slump. And if the Fed makes a policy mistake as well, hiking too soon, too much or maybe too late, there could be a perfect storm.Since taking office in early January, Trumphas moved swiftly and published four controversial executive orders targeting immigration, NAFTA, the Wall and the Trans- Pacific Partnership. As Washington becomes more inward looking, we might see a changing of the guard in many regions, leading to greater political unrest and weaker economic outcomes. Trading barriers, tariffs and trade wars generally result in ‘lose-lose’ outcomes for all parties. Against this, Trump’s team are very aware of the Great Depression and its roots in the 1930 Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act’s trade slump and it looks as if he is paying attention to what his senior appointmentsare saying. In any case, Congress will block anything too unconventional.The UglyTrump’s many critics claim he is an erratic, inconsistent, ignorant redneck bully who does not tolerate differences. And that isjust for starters! They see him as completely unsuited to any level of political command,a crazy maverick who will wreck everything. The market does not mind if his decisions are morally right or wrong, but it does demand clarity. If the crazy version of Trump emerges as the real thing, then we are in trouble. Not least, Mr Trump has a love affair with debt and is not afraid of using bankruptcy to deal with it.Trump’s own account of himself, for example in ‘The Art of the Deal’, is of a fluid, opportunist and very active businessman, a dealmaker used to hiring and firing and appointing good teams. What has wrong-footed observers is that he is not seeking political or any other form of approval, but is very goal oriented. Taking him at his word, his aim is to restore US hegemony. His detractors argue he hasa vast array of sinister personality disorders. It remains to be seen whether he tackles the Washington and other Swamps or creates new ones. We lean towards the positive view, but keep an open mind.Henderson Rowe manage the portfolios within the Verbatim Discretionary Service.Henderson Rowe is a highly individual, boutique wealth manager, which blends passive instruments to balance market exposure and stock-picking to add value.Founded in 2002 by majority shareholders Charles Aram, chief executive and Giles Rowe, chief investment officer, the firm currently manages £250m of assets. The firm currently employs 20 people, of whom 17 are investment professionals.Verbatim Asset Management provide market leading risk managed investment solutions including active and passive fund of funds, model portfolios and a unique discretionary service.Our guiding principles:• We build investment solutions designed to meet clients’ expectations.• We deliver investment performance within clear risk mandates.• We operate to the highest of ethical and regulatory standardswww.verbatimassetmanagement.co.uk Email: info@verbatim-am.co.ukPhone: 0808 12 40 007]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[The Suitability SuiteRisk . Costs . Due diligence . Best adviceProof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research• The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costsSynaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reportingSynaptic ComparatorDetailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculationsSynaptic RiskA.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfoliosSynaptic ModellerModels investment outcomes for new existing holdings. Manage and assess investment riskProtection and Annuity quotes and on-line applications Synaptic Webline (including enhanced annuities)Synaptic Suitability offer £140 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp is £226Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.SAVE OVER£125 PER LICENCE]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[15Finding the value in ValueAlastairMundy | HeadofValue | InvestecAssetManagementAlastair Mundy, Head of Value at Investec Asset Management, is a leading value/ contrarian investor who has been running the Investec Cautious Managed Fund for over 14 years. In what remain volatile, low growth markets he providesan insight into his Value team’s current thinking, including some of the key investment themes running through the portfolio that contributed to excellent performance in 2016 and that he believes could be key throughout 2017.In managing equities within the Value portfolios that Alastair runs, he and his team have followed the same value/contrarian investment approach for over 14 years. They seek out companies with low share prices, but which have characteristics that suggest they will recover. These companies’ underperformance could be due to poor management, over expansion, excessive competition or economic weakness. Alastair’s skill as the portfolio manager is to seek those companies which will turnaround their fortunes and avoid those that will not. He then blends these equities with other assets with the aim of reducing the impact of the volatility inherent in equities andto protect the Fund and investors against unforeseen risks.Following a number of years where investors had favoured other areas of the market, Alastair’s value/contrarian investment style had an excellent 2016 – in a year whichwas characterised by some of the most significant political events in decades and, as a result, market uncertainty. Here we provide some insight into several key investment themes that are currently running through perhaps Alastair’s best-known fund, the Investec Cautious Managed Fund and that Alastair believes could have an impact onthe value/contrarian investing capability throughout 2017.Theme 1: Central bank credibility is under threatAs existing policies lose their effectiveness, central banks are struggling to generate growth. And the debt keeps building.Actions:• Zero exposure to medium and long dated conventional bonds• Bond allocation at minimum permitted• Exposure to precious metals and preciousmetal shares• Exposure to Norwegian KroneTheme 2: Banks look attractiveBanks are offering a favourable risk/return trade-off with valuations at multi-year lows.Action:• The banks sector is the largest sector weighting on the portfolioTheme 3: US equities are expensiveUS equities are expensive, and balance sheets and corporate profitability are vulnerable.Actions:• The portfolio is short the S&P 500 • We are still identifying US equityopportunitiesTheme 4: There’s value in ValueValue funds have underperformed momentum and growth over the last few years, but the environment has been improving.Action:• The equity portfolio has a distinct bias to cheap stocks which have underperformedIf you would like to hear more about Alastair’s Value themes, please contact your usual Investec Asset Management representative.www.investecassetmanagement.com/CMF Broker Helpline: 0800 389 2299Email: enquiries@investecmail.comInvestec Asset Management, 31 March 2017. The portfolio may change significantly over a short period of time. These are not a buy, sell or hold recommendations for any particular investment. The Fund may invest more than 35% of its assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state. The Fund Prospectus and KIIDs may be obtained from www.investecassetmanagement. com. Telephone calls may be recorded for training and quality assurance purposes.]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[16Real life investing –F&C MM Lifestyle Fund RangeBMO GlobalAssetManagementIt is 10 years since the launch of our pioneering F&C MM Lifestyle Funds.A decade in which they have navigated a credit crunch, a worldwide economic downturn, a European debt crisis and numerous other market shocks.10 years across which they have delivered investment returns within definedrisk parameters. The F&C MM Lifestyle range contains five whole-of-market, risk-targeted multi-manager funds. The asset allocation and volatility constraints of the funds are designed to align with client risk profiles 3-7 on Dynamic Planner and canalso be mapped to the output of other risk profiling systems. This includes Synaptic Risk Rating Service covering strategic and tactical asset allocation scores.FSA 'Treating Customers Fairly' (TCF) initiativeTeam assume responsibility for managementAUM£880m**10year anniversary2017Tactical tilts introduced180+combined years in investment120+combined years in fund selectionThe team celebrate 20 years together2016FCA Financial Advice Market Review (FAMR) tackles the advice gapBrexit1st funds to be aligned to the stochastic model output of Dynamic PlannerFSA Guidanceon Assessing Suitability increases emphasis on attitude to risk and capacity for lossthF&C MM Lifestyle Funds launched1st in the UK*In a fast moving world,tilts were introduced in recognition of thepotential benefits of overlaying strategic asset weightings with tactical adjustments to reflect the team’s top-down assessment of prevailing conditions.2010Retail Distribution Review (RDR) transforms the pricing and servicing modelFederal Reserve announces 2nd round of QEF&C MMLifestyle Foundation added to the range2013RDR ready pricing, futures used for the first timeThe funds are managed by one of the most experienced and highly regarded teams in the business. Each portfolio contains carefully selected active funds alongside passive vehicles – a blend that aims to strike the balance between cost-effectiveness and performance potential.2014 2015Focus on centralised investment propositions20062007 20082009Clean B Inc shares to support New Model Advisers2011New asset classes introduced and weightings adjustedEuropean financial crisis2012Physical ETFs onlyThe TCF initiative sought to improve outcomesfor retail customers by enhancing the quality and consistency of advice and service. We developedthe F&C MM Lifestyle range in order to provide a robust outcome orientated investment solution.Credit crunch1st use of passive fundsRisk mapped to all main independent profilersLehmans bankrupt, market crash, quantitative easing (QE) beginsUK starts QEQE3 announced by Federal ReserveFCA replaces FSAEuropean rates into negative territory*1st in the UK targeted to Distribution Technology Dynamic Planner **BMO Global Asset Management as at 24.03.2017]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[17“Investing is a journey – one in which individuals are likely to have focused objectives and a clear idea of the route they want to take. Our F&C MM Lifestyle Funds were designed to help you help your clients along the way.”Rob Burdett, Co-head F&C multi-manager teamPerformance and risk outcomesThrough a combination of asset allocation, fund selection and careful portfolio management, our aim is to deliver the best possible investment returns for each risk profile. The chart shows annualised returns and volatility since the launch of the clean share class (B Inc) for each fund.Risk and reward – annualised returns(annualised return is the average return each year over a given period)Alignment deliveredperforming within defined parameters12 10 8 6 4 2 0F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive FundF&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12Volatility % (Risk)F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation FundN/AApr 08N/AApr 10N/AApr 12Apr 14Apr 16Source: Lipper Hindsight as at 31.01.2017. % Growth total return, net of fees, in sterling. Since Launch dates of clean share class as follows: Foundation B Inc 02.12.2013, Defensive B Inc 28.07.2009, Cautious B Inc 27.07.2009, Balanced B Inc and Growth B Inc 16.07.2009.Source: Distribution Technology, 31.12.16. F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation Fund was not launched until 2.12.2013.Past performance is not a guide to future performance. Stock market and currency movements means the value of investments and the income from them can go down as well as up and investors may not get back the amount originally invested.© 2017 BMO Global Asset Management. All rights reserved. BMO Global Asset Management is a trading name of F&C Management Limited, which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. CM12708 (04/17). UKReturns %]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[18Intellifo’s Intelligent Office now integrates with Synaptic research softwareStuart Carmichael | Head of Proposition | Synaptic Software LimitedA bug bear for some years for users of both Intelligent Office, the leading back office software provider and Synaptic Research, the leading provider of product and fund research software to advisers has been the lack of formal integration between the two systems.This has been remedied with the recent agreement between the two companiesto make an integration part of the current evolution of the Intelliflo suite into a more ambitious technological project linking additional aspects of their customer’s business processes. Synaptic will benefit through the greater access that Intelligent Office users will have to Synaptic Research.It has certainly been the case that some adviser firms have felt constrained in their use of the default research tools available with their preferred back office system, so we at Synaptic are looking forward to this obstacle disappearing to provide new opportunities to re-engage.The full integration will be launched in September 2017.xHow it works• The design allows Intelligent Office users to download a Synaptic Suite ‘app’;• The ‘app’ will initiate a link through to Synaptic and will pass the client data (including holdings) across to form the foundation of your research;• Any reports or downloads that are produced will be copied into the Intelligent Office database and stored against the client record.Forthcoming eventsSynaptic will be appearing at the ‘Change the Game conference’, the first to be held in Manchester 13th June and the second to be held in London on 20th June to promote the integration to Intelligent Office users.Screen shows one of the Synaptic product landing pages, including access to calculators and admin functionality.]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[19The Synaptic Research Suite is the best way of embedding the professional research that you need to differentiate your business from generic or more widely accessed research.Intelliflo usersThe regulatory screws are turning and recent thematic reviews around suitability (FC16/1 particularly) indicate the importance that the FCA is attaching to good research, a ‘culture of challenge’ in firms and focus on risk and cost.This year’s FCA business plan provides the following warnings:1. Advisers need to be clearer on charges. ‘Relatively few advisers are transparent about their pricing’. Synaptic Comparator is the only tool that provides total solution cost / R.I.Y. calculation using accurate charging data verified by the providers.2. Pressure on platforms. The FCA intends to be ‘investigating competition between platforms’ to see if they offer ‘value for money’. Synaptic Comparator provides accurate illustrations in this area.3. The regulator will do more to ensurerecommendations ‘are risk-appropriate’. Synaptic Risk proposition, including Synaptic Modeller, are supported by the soundest and most accessible research in the industry, from Moody’s Analytics.The Synaptic Research Suite is the best way of embedding the professional research that you need to differentiate your business from generic or more widely accessed research.For Intelliflo users who are not currently Synaptic users, or wish to trial additional Synaptic tools, please contact us on 0800 783 4477, and speak to one of our team for any assistance you may require in activating the Synaptic ‘app’ in Intelligent Office.Synaptic offer ‘best advice’ research tools that will now integrate into your company’s work-flows and provide a repeatable, consistent and compliant approach to all aspects of investment and protection advice.You will be able to use Synaptic software to meet and evidence the FCA’s requirements for suitability across the major advice areas – features, price and risk.Intelliflo integration deal offer: any Intelliflo user who contacts us in 2017 Q3 or Q4 will be eligible for the full Synaptic suite at £99 per month (RRP is £246 per month. Apply for full terms).Call 0800 783 4477 for more details.S Y N A P T I CWEBLINESynaptic Research SuiteSynaptic Comparator provides full charges analysis at adviser, platform, product and portfolio level. Accurate calculation of ‘Reduction in Yield’.Synaptic Risk offers client risk profiling and portfolio and fund risk ratings for full investment risk management.Synaptic Modeller is a financial planning tool providing access to Moody’s Analytic’s stochastic engine. Will provide probability based projections and full risk management to existing holdings and recommendations.‘Whole of market’ research and suitability reporting from the industry’s leading product and fund research application. Now with integrated Synaptic Risk Ratings.Protection and annuities quotation portal offering electronic submissions.]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[20NEW Synaptic research tool for retirement income modelling and drawdownAs we all know Osborne’s pension reforms were a big game changer for financial services. A shift of perspective to ‘beyond retirement’ has increased the requirement for advice for retirees. This important shift is reinforced by the demographic mega-trend of large numbers of baby boomers arriving at retirement.The favourable conditions that have followed this happy cohort through life (free education, cheap housing, secure jobs with good wages and pension entitlement) make for a lively at and post retirement market, and advisers will reap the benefits of servicing these customers for the next few years.Two things. Firstly advisers must ensure that they are up-skilled to deal with advice in this area – the regulator has announced some concern about ‘competency’. Secondly equip themselves with the resources and tools to provide quality retirement advice: -• strategies for providing income vary and need to be understood;• management of risk is much more challenging due to implications around sequence loss, shift in risk tolerances, so a different approach must be assumed;• maximum withdrawal rates need to be studied and research by luminaries such as Bergen, Kitces, Okusanya should be explored. These point to short-comings in some of the conventional wisdom shared by advisers,as well as describe some less-well-known strategies that could help your customers.In response to the new market dynamics, and to specific requests from customers, we are proud to release a new tool for advisers to assist them in advising clients in respect to retirement.The new tool is designed to illustratethe impact of choices around retirement income, including drawdown. Synaptic has the industry’s leading research team, whose unique data sets input into the new tool. We believe that our new tool is able to do more and provide greater assistance to customers than rival offerings. The new tool will also provide actual quotes on annuity income plus accurate illustrations on investment scenarios.Product Features• Complete income analysis and cost comparison for retirement needs, including suitable drawdown solutions• Simple easy to use, intuitive system supported by market leading calculations engine• Results include basic income tax calculations of 20%, 40% and 45% and basic NI calculations.• Separate income tax calculations for Scottish residents.• A full audit report is available that details all data input and any manual adjustments that may have been made by the user for use by file checking/compliance.• State Pension calculation included, generated from clients’ DOB and gender using government calculations.• Provides the ability to fully profile a client’s income in retirement both regular and ad-hoc.• Also provides to override profiled income with a single annual amount to rapidly return an indication of whether that income is achievable.• Provides the ability to add existing income sources- Drawdown- Annuity- Bank Account- Defined Benefit Pension- Earnings- Collectives- ISA- Bonds- Property- Shares- Other (Mandated free text field to ensureadviser captures income type)]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[21The new tool will also provide actual quotes on annuity income plus accurate illustrations on investment scenarios.• Quickreportfunctionalityenablestheuserto create a snapshot report of the different scenarios created.• MortalitycalculationutilisesdatafromtheOffice of National Statistics and will allow the user to override if necessary.• IncomeResultspresentedineasytounderstand graphs- Withdetailsofmaxincomeavailablegiventhe fund size and term- Withdetailsofinvestmentrequiredtogetto desired income level- Includesannuitycomparisonusingmarket leading Webline technologyFirst screen shows income summary screen. Second screen shows Fund Value and final screen shows real illustrations from providers for possible execution.• Onceanincomescenariohasbeenmodelledthe user can then adapt and edit easily and quickly• Whenthefinalscenariohasbeenagreedthe platform for holding that money is analysed utilising the award-winning Comparator costs and charges engine- Costisanalysedateverylevelofmultiple wrappers- Fulldrawdownproductrangerepresented- Personal Pension Drawdown and SIPP – using charging information collected and verified by product providers- Switchinganalysis- Manageandbuildportfolios- Resultsshowfundlongevity,RIYandallchargesassociated with the investment and anywithdrawals over the specified time period.- Reportsgeneratedcanbeshortcomparisonreports or full reports detailing income profiles and charts plus analysis of costs and charges.If you would like to see the new tool orrequest a trial please contact us on0800 783 4477 or visit www.synaptic.co.uk for more information.]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[22Looking after other people’s moneyDavid Norman | CEO | TCF Investment and MAPSThis is the first in a series of articles that will look at the key considerations for designing, building and running a Centralised Investment Proposition (CIP). It is based on my experience of supporting some 100 firms who sought ideas, input and challenge to their current processes.The articles will look at:1. The importance of having an Investment Philosophy and Process, and highlight some challenges around asset allocation.2. The documentation and processes needed – terms of reference, segmentation, investment committee, etc.3. Bringing the strands together and looking at due diligence, screening, short lists, and risk management.The foundationsThe FCA referred to CIPs in the finalised guidance issued in July 2012 “Assessing suitability – replacement business and centralised investment propositions”. Itis still an excellent start point for those looking to create a CIP and provides some excellent good and poor practice examples to draw from.Another key step is to think about the audience that the CIP is aimed at – many firms I have worked with end up with two versions:a) an internal document or set of processes that is used by the firm to ensure it is delivering consistent good outcomes and b) a simple client facing document that can be used to show the value of the process tocustomers (too many firms have excellent investment propositions but fail to articulate the value to customers).Thinking about the firm and its background, the intermediaries that you work with and the type of clients you have or are targeting is also important. The way you articulateyour CIP, and indeed what are appropriate instruments, will be different if you deal with professional introducers and high net worth entrepreneurs, or if you only deal directly with elderly retired people. But it is always worth keeping it as simple as possible (and that takes time!)Asset managers will have a document that outlines their core beliefs and how they implement these beliefs – an Investment Philosophy and Process. It is a simpleidea – once you know what you believe (Philosophy) it is relatively straightforward to implement it (Process). Trying to runa process without having the guiding philosophies in place is nigh on impossible and risks delivering inconsistent outcomes. The key for adviser firms is to be able to evidence their beliefs. The importance of costs, the key role that asset allocation plays in long-term returns, and the fact that diversification helps deliver a better risk adjusted return might feature.An Investment Philosophy and ProcessCreating a simple investment philosophy folder that stores these beliefs and critically the evidence for them would be a good first step – and something that product / risk tool providers will be able to assist with. This might be updated annually.A simple checklist example is shown in figure 1.Figure 1: Investment Philosophy ChecklistPHILOSOPHYEVIDENCELong term returnsBarclays Equity StudyImportance of asset allocationBrinson, Beebower, Hood and othersImportance of costsFCA Asset Management Study / MorningstarDiversification“Quilt” Chart (below)Link between risk and returnRisk profiling tool providerActive and passive or blendProduct providers / internet searchImportance of risk profilingAdviser own wordingNeed for a planAdviser own wordingTax and accessThe value of tax planningPre-funding (esp. for model portfolios)Platform due diligenceIt is worth recording examples of how the adviser adds value at each of these steps. This can be used in client facing material / reports, for example: the value of running optimised diversified portfolios – to maximise the return for each client’s given risk profile; the value of using some passive elements to reduce the overall costs (perhaps in the more efficient markets); the return boost provided by using]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[232017201610 years20 years50 years114 yearsUK Equity13.52.53.76.05.1UK Gilts8.74.34.53.11.4UK Corp Bonds9.53.1UK Index Linked16.64.34.4Cash-2.1-1.30.61.30.82014201310 years20 years50 years114 yearsUK Equity17.45.04.15.55.1UK Gilts-9.62.53.52.51.2UK Corp Bonds-1.01.8UK Index Linked-3.92.73.2Cash-2.3-0.51.31.50.8the right tax wrapper for each asset class to maximise use of income, savings and gains tax allowances.Don’t forget your value!Figure 2. is a simple “quilt” chart that shows how an equally weighted portfolio performs in relation to 12 different IA sectors over12 years. This is a good piece of evidence for your investment philosophy as well as a good visual sales aid to use in client facing documents.It is important to have a terms of reference (ToR) for your investment committee / meetings (more later). Quarterly meetings seem most popular but this varies by firm type (those with Discretionary permissions will be more frequent). Several firms reviewa different element each quarter by rotation e.g. Q1 - Investment Philosophy / ToR update and performance review, Q2 - Platform Due Diligence, Q3 - Equity Instrument Review and portfolio performance review, Q4 - Bond and Property Instrument Review.Figure 2. Diversification Quilt ChartRisk tools typically use some form of optimisation model (e.g. mean variance optimiser) to construct an efficient frontier from which the risk and return can be derived. The tools use long-term asset class return, volatility and correlation assumptions to attempt to build the optimum portfolio for each level of risk (as measured by volatility). This derives the strategic asset allocation benchmark for portfolios.Risk tools and asset allocation assumptionsThe assumptions used by most optimisers are based on some form of historic data. These may be adjusted for expected future returns to make them more forward-looking than just backward-facing. It is helpful to understand and document these assumptions. The investment committee would wish to sense check these assumptions as the data that is used as inputs to these tools is critical to the output. Small changes to long-term return assumptions can make substantial changes to the asset allocation for a given risk profile.It is also important that advisers understand whether the optimiser outputs are real (after inflation) returns or nominal.The Barclays Equity Gilt Study is a good source of long-term returns but care needs to be exercised. The 2014 study (using 2013 real annual returns %pa) for UK asset classes is shown in Figure 3.Figure 3. Long-term real UK asset class returns. source: Barclays 2014Using 10, 20 or 50-year data would have seen the higher risk portfolios seeking the higher volatility and higher returning asset classes – equities.The excellent returns in bonds over the last 10 years (since the credit crunch) drivenby ever falling yields and the impact of Quantitative Easing (QE), has now tipped the return balance over ten and twenty years in favour of Gilts over Equities. While the very long data, over 50 years, still shows equities having higher returns.Figure 4. shows the real returns for various UK asset classes in the Barclays Equity Gilt Study 2017 (2016 data).Only 4 years after 2014 there is a significant change in 10 and 20 year returns and a reversal in what might be considered the best long-term asset class.Figure 4. Long-term real UK asset class returns. source: Barclays 2017Being able to review this data and updating your investment approach accordingly is a key part of an Investment Committee role. It may be that the decision to outsource to managers that can make tactical decisions away from the strategic benchmark would be a key part of an adviser’s proposition to help mitigate this potential backward-looking data issue.Next stepsFuture articles will look at documentation for ToR and investment committees, some ideas around segmentation, insource and outsource decision making and due diligence / screening.Email: david.norman@tcfinvestment.comMost advisers and planners will be using a risk profiling tool to assist with their investment decision-making for clients. In simple terms that there are two discrete steps: first to assess the risk profile of the client (attitude to risk, capacity for loss, need for return over inflation etc.), then to match this risk profile with a suitable asset mix.]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24What a difference an ‘M’ makes – M(odel) vs M(anaged) portfoliosDavid Holloway | Marketing Director | RathbonesDecisions and actions around the regular rebalancing of portfolios are of course important, as is the timing of the adjustments, particularly when markets are volatile.Unlike ‘model portfolio’ solutions, whichmight only deal monthly or quarterly, and therefore miss opportunities to deal at the best prices, clients of the new Rathbone Managed Portfolio Service will benefit from the daily and continuous management of our award-winning Rathbones multi-asset funds (Manager David Coombs has won the best manager in the Citywire Mixed Assets - Absolute Return GBP category at the 2017 UK Awards), and the experience of a team that has demonstrated positive returns through different market conditions.Consider last year when model portfolios allocated to property funds in advance of Brexit, but were unable to make adjustments after the shock Brexit vote. By the time rebalancing dates came around, the UK’s largest open-ended funds had locked their gates amid massive outflows. A further disadvantage is portfolios are always done at a specific date and time, which puts them at disadvantage – they all rebalance at the same regular dates, so other people in the market know they’re coming – and they are locked-in for months, regardless of what happens.Most people are more concerned about losing money than making high returns. Unlike many of our competitors, our fund managers havea clear target for risk as well as returns, giving them explicit boundaries for the appropriate level of risk that they can take. There is a range of six strategies to suit different appetites for risk and return; from ‘low’ through to ‘high; targeting ‘6-month LIBOR+2%’ (cash plus) through to ‘CPI+5% plus’ (inflation plus over 5%). It offers a private client level of reporting, and we believe that this combination will prove an attractive addition to Rathbones’ range of investment services.Some advisory clients want service and bespoke advice from an ongoing relationship with their Discretionary Fund Manager. Others, working with their investment adviser, are clear about their goals and want a simple and straightforward execution-only investment service - less personalised for now, but without sacrificing the balance of quality, relevance and value that is currently missing from this area of the market, heavily populated with ‘model portfolios’.The Rathbone Managed Portfolio Service complements our other offerings to clients, from single strategy funds to bespoke discretionary portfolio management. It’sa service brought to you by Rathbone Investment Management offering, for a £15,000 minimum investment, a range of strategies that invest in existing in-house, multi-asset funds managed by RathboneUnit Trust Management. In doing so, we draw together expertise from across Rathbones and capturing the best ideas from the broadest possible global universe of individual securities and funds, we look to provide that within a set of risk parameters.You can never get this degree of timely and flexible investing from a one-size-fits-all model portfolio, so why hope for it when an alternative is available?This year we are likely to see continuing uncertainty, providing opportunities that active managers can exploit, both in stock selection and asset allocation, continuously. Against this backdrop, investors will require their investments to be managed in a way that will secure returns in real terms – growth and protection on the downside.We can tell you much more about the Rathbone Managed Portfolio Service; please call our team on 020 7399 0399 or email ifaservices@rathbones.comaCautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus Equity Equity PlusReturn target Cash plus Inflation plus Inflation plus Inflation plus Inflation plus Inflation plusRisk level Low Medium Medium Medium Relatively high HighObjective Growth Growth Income Growth Growth Growth6 month LIBOR CPI (Consumer Target return +2% Price Index)+2%CPI (Consumer Price Index) +3-5%CPI (Consumer Price Index) +3-5%CPI (Consumer Price Index) +4-5% PlusCPI (Consumer Price Index) +5% PlusInvested in RMAP fundsRMAP Total Return RMAP Total return and RMAP StrategicGrowthRMAP Strategic IncomeRMAP Strategic GrowthRMAP Strategic RMAP Enhanced Growth and RMAP Growth Enhanced GrowthDynamic planner rating]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Taking our managed portfolio service to a new level:— an execution-only service; tailored to client needs— access to go anywhere, daily and continuous active management— decisions informed by our extensive investment resources— competitive pricing— availableinarangeoftaxwrappers: ISA, SIPP, offshore bondsFor more information, please contact our intermediary services desk on 020 7399 0399, email ifaservices@rathbones.comor for more information, please visit rathbones.com/financial-advisersRathbone managed portfolio service25Important informationThis document is published by Rathbone Investment Management Limited and does not constitute a solicitation, nor a personal recommendation for the purchase or sale of any investment; investments or investment services referred to may not be suitable for all investors. No consideration has been given to the particular investment objectives, financial situations or particular needs of any recipient and you should take appropriate professional advice before acting. The price or value of investments, and the income derived from them, can go down as well as up and an investor may get back less than the amount invested. Rathbone Investment Management Limited will not, by virtue of distribution of this document, be responsible to any other person for providing the protections afforded to customersor for advising on any investment. Unless otherwise stated, the information in this document was valid as at January 2017. Rathbone Brothers Plc is independently owned, is the sole shareholder in each of its subsidiary businesses and is listed on the London Stock Exchange. Rathbones is the trading name of Rathbone Investment Management Limited, which is authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority. Rathbone Unit Trust Management Limited is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Registered office: Port of Liverpool Building, Pier Head, Liverpool L3 1NW. Registered in England No. 01448919. The information and opinions expressed herein are considered valid at publication, but are subject to change without notice and their accuracy and completeness cannot be guaranteed. No part of this document may be reproduced in any manner without prior permission. © 2017 Rathbone Brothers Plcrathbones.com/financial-advisers @Rathbones1742Rathbone Brothers Plc]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26Using Investment TrustsBen Conway | Senior Fund Manager | Hawksmoor Investment ManagementAs well as investing in “open-ended” funds (such as unit trusts and OEICs, which allow daily inflows and outflows), Hawksmoor’s Funds of funds (Hawksmoor Vanbrugh and Hawksmoor Distribution) also invest in “closed-ended” funds, also known as investment trusts.These vehicles give a manager a fixed amount of capital to invest, which is raised via an Initial Public Offering (IPO). This portfolio is valued on a regular basis, but is owned via the investment trust structure, which itself is traded like any other listed company’s shares. This means that themarket’s valuation of the investment trust can diverge (both positively and negatively) from its valuation of the portfolio resulting in the trust trading at a premium or discount to the implied valuation of the underlying portfolio.The closed-ended nature of investment trusts allows fund managers to invest in more illiquid assets than he or she might otherwise be able to invest in via an open- ended fund as there are no inflows that might dilute (or outflows that might disrupt) the make-up of the portfolio. This enables us to gain access to a far wider pool of investment opportunities within our two Funds of funds, Vanbrugh and Distribution. In turn, this gives us access to asset classes that might behave very differently from, and are valued more cheaply than equities and bonds that are typically held in open- ended funds. Owning assets that performin different ways at different times (i.e. that have low or negative correlation) assists greatly with portfolio construction. If we only owned assets that always acted in thesame way, we would have a portfolio that potentially could suffer much larger swings in value than would otherwise be the case. By owning cheap assets that behave differently we can dampen these swings in value without sacrificing performance. Over recent years the performance of traditional assets, such as bonds and equities, have becomefar more positively correlated and so being able to access different asset classes via investment trusts has materially improved our performance relative to much larger funds of funds that only invest in unit trusts and OEICs.We can also exploit inefficiencies in investment trusts and the fact that they trade at premia and discounts to our advantage. We often purchase them at a discount (effectively buying a pound worth of assets for less) and hope to sell them at a narrower discount or even a premium. This return is in addition to the underlying return we receive from the portfolio’s gain in value.Owning assetsthat perform in different ways at different times (i.e. that have low or negative correlation) assists greatlywith portfolio construction.]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[27Being able to access different asset classes via investment trusts has materially improved our performance relative to much larger funds of funds that only invest in unit trusts and OEICs.Of late, the weakness in the pound has encouraged overseas buyers to opportunistically purchase cheap sterling assets.The types of assets we hold via investment trusts include loans, private equity, property, asset-backed securities and more illiquid parts of global equity markets (such as “Frontier Markets” and “micro-cap” equities). It would be a mistake to think that these investments necessarily involve taking extra risk. Quite the opposite can be true. Consider private equity as a case in point. The two words often conjure up images of greedy financiers charging high fees and ruining the companies they invest in. While the run up to the 2007-be the consumer favourites of the future,as well as providing exciting technological advancements in fields such as biotechnology with accompanying improvements to the treatment of human illness. We have long held exposure to such private equity funds and have managed to acquire them on significant discounts via the investment trust space. Further, the companies owned within these portfolios have, on average, delivered far superior earnings growth to those available on the publicly-traded equity markets. Of late,narrowing discounts and resulted in them being one of the world’s best performing asset classes in 2016.An investment in one of Hawksmoor’s Funds gives you access not only to one of the best–in-class active funds, but also to a whole array of attractive asset classes that you might not otherwise be able to invest in thanks to our specialist expertise in investment trusts. It is this combination, among other positive attributes that we hope to tell you about in further articles, that has led to both Funds being among the best performers in their sectors – both over the long-term and over the past year.For information on Hawksmoor’s range of investment services, please contact:Robin O’GradyHead of Investment Sales robin.ogrady@hawksmoorim.co.uk 07468 697900Disclaimer for financial advisers onlyUnless otherwise specified, Hawksmoor Investment Management Limited is the source of all data. All information contained in this material is current at the time of issue and, to the best of our knowledge, accurate. Your clients should consult the prospectus and Key Investor Information Document (KIID) before deciding whetherto invest. Please note that the value of investment and the income derived from them may go down as well as up and an investor may not receive back the amount originally invested. Anypast performance figures are not a guide to future performanceAuthorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. HA19012008 crisis did undoubtedly uncover some unhealthy practices by poorly-run private equity companies, these proved to be the exceptions rather than the rule. Indeed, if run properly, private equity plays a vital role in any capitalist society by giving life blood (capital) to early-stage and strongly growing companies that might otherwise struggle to get established and achieve their potential. Such companies can go on tothe weakness in the pound has encouraged overseas buyers to opportunistically purchase cheap sterling assets. Privateequity investment trusts have been an area of particular interest to these buyers and recently a takeover bid for one of these trusts from a US company has focused attention on the whole asset class. In addition to strongly performing portfolios, our investments in this area have consequently benefitted from]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[28Why does trying to “time the market” so often fail?BenRaven | Director | TavistockWealthHad you invested in the FTSE All Share Index at the start of 1997, and held your investment for 20 years, you would have celebrated New Year’s Eve 2016 with a profit of +268%. An average annual return of approximately 5%, compounded over a quarter of a century. Few, if any, would be disappointed with that return whatever their risk appetite.Over that same period, thousands ofactive fund managers have attempted to out-perform indices. These active fund managers charge a premium (usually their Annual Management Charge) and attempt to generate ‘alpha’ for their investors.Alpha is the return achieved in excess ofthe benchmark. The IA Flexible Investment Sector reflects the performance of active managers seeking to outperform the equity markets. Whilst not all of these invest solely in the UK, there are high correlations acrossglobal equity markets and the return of the IA Flexible Sector over the 20-year period was +239%.So why is it so difficult for active managers to outperform an index? I have previously explained the punitive, and hidden, charges involved in running an active mandate. Charges make life extremely challenging for an active manager, but there are still those whose funds can absorb them and achieve alpha. The questions are just how good dothey have to be, and does that represent a sound investment?The 20 years in question comprised 5,216 trading days. The active managers identified their highest conviction trades, incurredthe trading charge for implementing them, and waited for the binary outcome; would the value of their position go up or down? Sometimes the move was logical, other times it seemed to defy logic. The better managers won on trades more than theyCharges make life extremely challenging for an active manager, but there are still those whose funds can absorb them and achieve alpha. The questions are just how good do they have to be, and does that represent a sound investment?]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[29The problem is that not all trading days are equally important and if you aren’t invested on the most important days, the impact can be devastating.lost. However, the problem is that not all trading days are equally important and if you aren’t invested on the most important days, the impact can be devastating. So how significant are the most important days out of 5,216?The FTSE All Share Index made +268% over 5,216 days. If you had tracked the index, and missed just the 5 best days (0.10% of the days) your return would have reduced by almost half to +153%. If you missed the 10 best days (0.19%) you would have gained +99%; missing the 20 best days (0.38%) reduced the return to +31% and missing the best 25 days (0.48%) would have seen you barely break even at +9%.Perhaps most astonishingly, if you were unlucky enough to miss the best 30 trading days (0.58%) you would have lost money with a return of -8%. That is to say you could have been invested for 5,186 of the5,216 days, or 99.42% of the time, and you would have lost money. Meanwhile the person that remained fully invested throughout, would have made +268%.Whilst there are undoubtedly some extremely capable investment managersin our industry, nobody has the abilityto predict the future. Timing the market consistently over a long time-frame is practically impossible and attempting to do so can detrimentally impact the returns on offer. In order to maximise one’s long-term investment return there is a compelling argument for populating a portfolio with long-only index-tracking, or Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs).Assuming the portfolio is well diversified, managed daily and structured in the most cost and tax efficient manner, investors can remain invested 100% of the time and reap the benefits on offer.Pay a fund manager to “time the market” (in the hope of achieving alpha) and money can be lost simply by being “out of the market” on only a small number of days that are usually impossible to predict. Using our example, had you missed out on just 30 days in 20 years you would have lost money.Conversely if you had just sat tight your initial stake would have almost quadrupled! Markets can bounce back very quickly after a sell off and remaining fully invested can lead to significantly better performance over the long run.Source of data: Tavistock Wealth Limited and MoneyWeekFor more information about Tavistock Wealth:tavistockwealth.com Linkedin.com/company/Tavistock-wealthMarkets can bounce back very quickly after a sell off and remaining fully invested can lead to significantly better performance over the long run.]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[30Natural yield: a totally bonkers retirement income strategyAbraham Okusanya | Principal | FinalytiQOne of the most common questions I receive about retirement income planning is, how realistic is the idea of relying on natural yield in one’s portfolio to meet retirement income needs. The rational is that by relying on the natural yield from their portfolio, retirees can avoid drawing on their capital or selling fund units, thereby avoiding the dangers of sequence risk.The natural yield approach contrastswith the total return approach, which essentially ignores the difference between capital growth and dividends, and instead seeks to draw income from both in a sustainable way.The natural yield approach is bandied about by some asset managers, who promise ‘stable natural yield’ to retirees. So it’s no surprise that the industry and consumer financial press is awash with articleson natural yield. A recent article in The Telegraph sums up the approach rather nicely: “The idea is to ignore the fluctuating capital value of a portfolio and only take the natural yield. An original £100,000 investment might dip to £80,000 or rise to £120,000 in terms of value, but investors should resist the urge to touch the capital.”The trouble is, this approach is bonkers for several reasons.• Dividend and bond yields fluctuate over time. This means that a retiree’s actual income will change significantly from year to year. This creates an unacceptable level of volatility in their income and makes budgeting nearly impossible.• Once adjusted for inflation, natural income is highly unlikely to meet the spending pattern of most retirees, bar the very wealthy.• Proponents of a ‘natural yield’ retirement strategy have offered little empirical evidence to back their theory. They erroneously focus on recent percentage yield of the FTSE 100 or FTSE All Share. Most retirees are more likely to have a portfolio consisting of bonds and shares, at the very least. And it’s crucial that any retirement income strategy works over a very long period and under various market conditions, including the extreme ones!The Big TestSo in this research, I set out to examine the natural yield approach to retirement income, using empirical data. This time, I’ve used the Barclays Equity Gilt Study (BEGS) dataset from 1900 to 2015, which decomposes equity and bond returns into capital growth and income yield.• I created a portfolio consisting of 50% UK equities and 50% gilts, which is rebalanced annually.• I examined the real natural income ona £100,000 portfolio for retirement periods starting in 1900,1905,1910,1915 .... to 2005 and 2010. I also included a retirement period starting in 2008, just to take my total number of scenarios to 20!• Based on the dataset, I looked at a retirement period of 30 years. Retirees starting after 1985 haven’t completed the full 30 year period yet, so I’ve presented]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Real Natural Income Yield From £100,00 Initial PortfolioFirst Year, Lowest, Mean and Highest Real Income Yield for Each Retirement Period31their results for the period covered so far. For instance, a retirement period starting in 1990 (Class 90) has had 25 years so far and a retirement period starting in 2000 (Class ’00) just 15 years!• The real natural income is the natural income from the outstanding portfolio, adjusted for inflation. I work on the basis that no income is taken from the capital and the retiree relies entirely on the natural income of their portfolio.• No fees/taxes are applied to the portfolio. Obviously, the net natural income would likely be lower after fees/ taxes and the key points hold regardless.The ResultThe chart below shows the real natural income from the portfolio over the subsequent 30 year period (or less where applicable i.e. retirement dates starting after 1985).income over the entire retirement period. I also show the ‘income volatility’ in %, which is the standard deviation from the mean income over each retirement period.The implication is that a retiree living off natural yield may or may not start off with a decent income in the first year of their retirement. But they should expect their income to fluctuate like a yo-yo from one year to the next. And once you add in the effect of inflation, this yo-yo effect (income volatility) is simply unacceptable for most retirees.Chasing YieldOf course, a proponent of natural yieldwill argue that a natural yield portfolio will specifically overweight high-yield assets such as high-dividend equities, commercial property, REITs and high-yield bonds.A recent paper by Vanguard lays bare the flaws of this thinking but I want to pick out these key drawbacks• High-yield asset classes such as commercial property/REITs, high-dividend equities and high yield bonds tend to have large drawdowns, particularly during stressful market conditions. The chart below shows the cumulative total returns during the global financial crisis (12 October 2007 to 9 March 2009) of major asset classes, including high-yield ones during the financial crisis of 2008.As you can see, income yielding asset classes experienced larger losses. It’s crucial to remember that, even if the income yield in percentage terms on these asset classes remains consistent (which they mostly don’t), the actual income received by the retiree in £ is still affected by the large capital drawdown.• Over-weighing high-yield asset classes invariably increases concentration risk and reduces diversification in the portfolio.• There is some empirical evidence to suggest that high dividend stocks tend to outperform over the very long term. But this is more likely to be due to value premium (i.e. equities with a low price- to-dividend ratio or frankly low price- to-anything ratio). Fortunately, there are better ways to capture value premium than price-to-dividends. Using price-to- earning or price-to-book is a far more effective way to achieve this.• The strategy relies heavily on the ability of the manager(s) to select high-yield stocks, bonds, property, before the fact, consistently over the very long retirement period. Good luck with that one.The implication of all this is that a natural yield approach is a bonkers retirement income strategy for virtually all but very wealthy retirees, who mostly rely on other sources of steady income.www.finalytiq.co.uk www.twitter.com/AbrahamOnMoney abraham@finalytiq.co.ukAs you can see, regardless of the retirement date, a retiree relying only on natural income experiences a significant fluctuation in their income from year to year.Take for instance, our Class 1900 who started their retirement with a natural income of £4,550. By the second year, their inflation adjusted income fell to £3,897 and by the 5th year it was £3,005. But their troubles were only just beginning; by their 20th year in retirement, their real income yield had fallen to £1,024! I know no retiree on the planet who would consider these levels of fluctuation in their annual income to be acceptable.In the second chart below, I show the first year’s natural income, as well as the lowest, the mean and the highest real natural]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[32How do you select a DFM?Geoff Mills | Director | RSMRAs part of our evolving services for IFAs, we have now extended our range of RSMR ratings to cover the discretionary fund management (DFM) sector.The ever-shifting economic environment overthe last few years has proved difficult for many investors, professional or otherwise, and has required a significant amount of patience and skill to seek out areas that can offersome return.Use of DFMs has increased in popularityas a way of helping to take away some of the stress of selecting assets, allowing the adviser to focus on the many other areas of financial planning.Yet the choice now available means that selecting the right option from the marketis increasingly difficult, and when taking account of the breadth of complex investment instruments used to form solutions, the apparently simple approach has become all the more complex.So why did we do this?Our new designation has been developed in response to adviser demand for additional clarity in the selection and use of DFMs. The rating is supported by our DFM matrix and factsheets, and our detailed DFM profiles.The DFM rating indicates that we have assessed the whole proposition against our methodology, and are happy to endorse its use. Of course under a DFM umbrella there can be a number of services, from bespoke portfolios to more generic unitised fund ranges. Where we have rated a DFM, we have effectively rated all of the services that fall within that.As part of our preliminary work in the creation of a rating for DFMs, we wantedto understand more about the market, and how it was viewed. In order to do this, we completed a survey with our adviser clients, which revealed some useful information about how they viewed the DFM market.Firstly, we wanted to understand the size of the market, and we found that 80% of the adviser firms currently use DFM services for some of their clients, and of these, nearly two-thirds expected future levels of DFM business to increase. Just 5% felt that volumes would decrease.Only 22% of the adviser firms felt that their needs could be met from a single DFM, and the remaining 78% are using or would use more than one. ‘Full’ discretionary services were used far more than model portfolio services (MPS) – around three times as much.We then wanted to look at how advisers choose their DFM provider, and the following summarises the highest scoring criteria:• the investment structure, processes and resources of the DFM – 93%• size and reputation of the DFM management team – 83%Finally, we wanted to understand if an RSMR rating that was awarded to DFMs meeting a required standard of investment capability would be useful, and a unanimous 100%of firms confirmed they would – of which two-thirds said they would value such a rating very highly. This was a clear confirmation that development of an investment-focused rating was desirable.]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[33The first and most important step in this process is to determine the investment experience and expertise of the DFM and their ability to sustain the highest levels of achievement over the medium to longer term.Our approachOur approach to the provision of ratings in the DFM market is very similar to that used for single strategy and multi-asset funds, but with the specifics modified to take accountof the DFM market. In all these areas, we apply a straightforward, robust, repeatable process using appropriate criteria to arrive at a balanced view of the overall proposition.There are many important factors to be researched and assessed. We believe that the first and most important step in this process is to determine the investment experience and expertise of the DFM and their ability to sustain the highest levels of achievement over the medium to longer term.Our approach to DFM rating, as with allour ratings, places far greater emphasis on qualitative factors which reflect the integrity and effectiveness of the investment structures and processes, rather than judging primarily on performance.We provide fact sheets and other documentation about rated firms and our selection criteria to advisers, as evidenceof the robust and rigorous process we have carried out. These will assist with recording of stages in the due diligence process and in the development of any client-facing material.Support material for advisersAll of the support material is available on the Research Hub – http://members.rsmgroup. co.uk – and is summarised as follows:DFM rating – only DFMs that have successfully passed our rigorous and robust methodology will be awarded our coveted‘R’ designation. In giving this rating, we are confirming that our research shows the DFM to have a sound investment process and that our analysis of the performance and risk of the DFM is in line with our expectations. This designation, and the methodology used can form the basis of your due diligence.DFM factsheet – this gives you background information and a concise opinion on each proposition which can help you to narrow down your selection, and can be used as part of the justification for your choices.DFM matrix – to help further with comparing the DFM propositions, we have put together a matrix which will allow you to easily see and compare the rated DFMs, giving basic details in areas such as financial strength, services offered, assets under management etc.DFM profile – along the lines of our successful fund profiles, this will be an in-depth document providing full details of the investment processes that are in place, the team that manage the money, and their backgrounds and expertise.With the introduction of the new DFM rating, we have made our adviser support even more comprehensive. As covered earlier, all our ratings are founded on a strict methodology that considers performance and risk measures but places a greater emphasis on the ability of fund managers and investment providers to continue to deliver performance in the years ahead based on our in-depth research and face-to-face meetings with them in the UK and across the globe.www.rsmr.co.ukEmail: geoff.mills@rsmgroup.co.uk Research Hub – members.rsmgroup.co.uk Twitter: @RSMRTweets / @thegeoffmills]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[34Takeovers and investing for the long termJames Nield | Investment Manager | Thesis Asset ManagementWhat do BAA, BG, SAB, P&O, ICI and ARM have in common? They are all UK companies which have been the subject of takeovers, in all but one case by overseas buyers. Three of these transactions rank in the largest ten UK acquisitions in history.The table opposite provides some outline details of these transactions; others inthe last ten years or so include Boots, O2 and Corus, not to mention the series of transactions involving UK banks during the financial crisis. Even now Sky is the subject of an offer from its related company 21st Century Fox, having previously been in talks with News Corporation. So let’s look at the factors which motivate buyers and sellers alike. Do these deals genuinely ‘add value’? Should investors buy shares in companies on the basis that they might be takenover for a premium valuation? Are there common themes which run through the transactions mentioned here and the others which are not?Market valuesAnyone who keeps an eye on markets will know that share prices fluctuate on a daily/ hourly/minute by minute basis. So does that mean that on such a short term basis investors are altering their views on the value of the particular company? Of coursenot. As in any other market the behaviour of buyers and sellers is driven by a large number of factors. These include the oft quoted human sentiments of ‘fear and greed’; the availability of alternative (more attractive?) investment opportunities elsewhere; the investment time horizons of the respective market participants; the presence of a particularly large buyer or seller whomight influence the price; regulatory andtax matters. The list goes on. In all these takeovers the deal has taken place at a price well above that prevailing in the market before its announcement. On the whole investors demand this compensation for missing out on potential future growth in the company, and they ultimately show theiracceptance of the deal by voting in favour of it (or not as the case may be). So how can a corporate purchaser justify paying a price well above the market’s prevailing valuation, and with the benefit of hindsight have they been right to do so?Short versus long termOne explanation of a company’s ability to pay a higher price than normal day to day investors relates to a discrepancy in theway that the various parties’ performanceis assessed. Almost 60% of all quoted UK shares are owned by institutional investment managers. While the underlying investors may well be private individuals, their funds are pooled and invested on a collective basis.]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[35At Thesis we screen the FTSE 350 using a proprietary process, the top quintile output of which gives our research team a universe of 70 companies to analyse on a fundamental basis.There are many benefits to this approach but one of the downsides relates to time horizons.Institutional investment managers are paid by their clients to outperform the market. Investors can become impatient during periods of underperformance which can lead to a tendency for short-termism. Analysisof investment performance on a quarterly or even monthly basis can incentivise such managers to accept offers from corporate acquirers at prices below their genuine opinions as to valuation.Corporate managers on the other handcan often take a longer term outlook.Many companies exist for decades and decades and their fortunes can be built on strategic decisions which have a multi-year perspective. While the directors of companies are not immune from short term pressures (from shareholders for example), they can use this timescale mismatch occasionally to their advantage.A prime example of this is the acquisitionof UK software company ARM Holdingsby Japan’s SoftBank. In the immediate aftermath of the EU referendum result the ARM share price did not suffer as badly as many, however sterling did and this may well have proven the catalyst. Markets gave the result the ‘thumbs down’, selling sterling against most other currencies. At one point sterling had weakened by over 20% against the yen, making a UK acquisition for aJapanese company all the more attractive.I am certain that the referendum resultwas on the agenda for discussion roundthe SoftBank board table but one can only assume that the long term, strategic benefits of the transaction outweighed any concerns relating to the UK’s political status in Europe. Short term market behaviour (in this casein currencies) can facilitate longer term corporate strategies.ControlAnother reason for takeovers taking placeat a premium is that control of the entirety of a company itself has a value relative to owning a small part of it. Management control allows the acquiring company to set the strategic outlook for the business, and often the combination of the two businesses will enable one or both of them to do things they could not have done before. The much vaunted management synergies highlighted in corporate transaction documents often have a meaningful value and these can only be realised with full ownership. This is not limited to cost savings but can also involve the sharing of information/technology/ processes etc to enhance the products or services offered by the combined entity. These are benefits that can only accrue toa corporate acquirer rather than a minority shareholder, providing another justification for such deals.ThesisAt Thesis we screen the FTSE 350 usinga proprietary process, the top quintile output of which gives our research team a universe of 70 companies to analyse on a fundamental basis. The end result, following further qualitative analysis, is around 30 direct UK equity holdings across most client portfolios. This approach has exhibited twin benefits typically: investment performance and lower overall portfolio costs. Our approach is based on the notion that ‘good companies produce good results, good results produce good performance.’ We may well benefit from the premium delivered by an acquisition of one of our companies in the future. If a corporate acquirer sees the same merits as us then so much the better, but in the meantime we stick to our process and expect these companies to deliver positive returns nonetheless.Sources: Office for National Statistics; The Daily Telegraph; International Business Times; Reuters; Financial TimesEmail: james.nield@thesis-plc.com]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[36FCA Asset Management Review: Great newsfor investorsRichardWithers| Headofgovernmentrelations|VanguardEuropeThe FCA is undertaking the biggest review of the UK asset management industry for many years – and we agree with many of their initial findings.The Financial Conduct Authority (FCA), which regulates the financial services industry in the United Kingdom, published its interim Asset Management Market Study last November. Running to some 208 pages, the report represents the most detailed regulatory examination of the UK’s asset management industry for many years. It’s an interesting read and contains a number of criticisms of the industry.The FCA gave asset management companies until February to respond. Vanguard submitted a detailed response, covering a variety of topics. I’ll highlight three of them here.1. Costs are too highWe agree with the FCA that the cost of investing in the UK is too high. Like many industries, fund management benefits from economies of scale. That is to say, a £1 billion fund is not necessarily ten times as expensive to run as a £100 million fund. At Vanguard, our whole business model is built on this principle. We offer high-quality, low-cost funds, which deliver good results to investors, helping us to attract and retain assets, which give us economies of scale, so that we can lower the cost of investing further, and so on.However, the rest of the industry doesn’t operate on the same model. Competition has started to drive fund charges lower, but the industry needs to do more. We believe that lowering the cost and complexity of investing is the best way to improve the long-term financial health of the UK population.2. Performance is not good enoughEvery pound that investors pay in charges isa pound out of their potential returns. Hence, high costs act as a brake on fund performance and – counter-intuitively for many – lower- cost funds tend to outperform their higher- cost peers.We believe that lowering the cost and complexity of investing is the best way to improve the long-term financial health of the UK population.]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[37We’ve gone as far as suggesting that all funds should carry a health warning along these lines: Warning – Check how much you are paying – High fees will harm your long-term returns.Across the industry, too many funds fail to live up to their performance targets, partly as a result of the charges that they levy. Moreover, even those managers who do manage to outperform in a given year seldom manage to repeat the feat consistently.Since passive investing has started to become more popular, there has been an ongoing “active vs. passive” debate. We think this debate is outdated and should be reframed as high cost vs low cost. Why? Because research has consistently shown cost to be the best predictor of relative returns.In fact, we’ve gone as far as suggesting that all funds should carry a health warning along these lines: Warning – Check how much you are paying – High fees will harm your long- term returns. We’d also like to work with the FCA in designing a rating system to make it easier for investors to understand the relative cost of a fund. Red/amber/green rating badges seem to work well in other industries.3. Investors need better informationTo make informed decisions, investors need to have access to information they can understand. However, research we’ve recently conducted with Opinium LLP showed that investors don’t feel they have access to clear information. As a result, many investorsstill base their investment decisions on past performance, which has been shown to be a poor predictor of future success.Rather than focusing on past performance, we believe that investors will improve their chances of success if they are encouraged to think about the return they require in order to meet their goals. Selecting a low-cost fund designed to produce their required return, and then having the discipline to tune out short- term noise, will further improve their chances.Aligned with the FCAIn summary, we agree with much of whatthe FCA says. Consumers will benefit from having access to better products with lower charges, and clearer information that allows them to make informed investment decisions. If the industry is truly customer-focused it will prioritise achieving progress on these fronts. We look forward to continuing to engage with the regulator and our peers on the topic.If you found this article interesting, you can read more commentary from Vanguard on our website: www.vanguard.co.uk/adviser/ adv/adviser-support/adviser-library/ research-commentaryImportant Information:Vanguard Asset Management, Limited only gives information on products and services and does not give investment advice based on individual circumstances. If you have any questions related to your investment decision or the suitability or appropriateness for you of the product[s] described in this document, please contact your financial adviser.The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.Across the industry, too many funds fail to live up to their performance targets, partly asa result of the charges that they levy.]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SUPPORTING YOURDEFINED BENEFIT ADVICESTART TO FINISHFROMEXPERT SUPPORTOur online DB advice resource centre offers:• Special Edition Defined Benefit TechTalk • guides for you and your clients• overviews, checklists and a case study.TVAS REPORTWe offer TVAS reports as part of our start-to-finish expert support, helping you make compliant recommendations for your clients.FLEXIBLE PRODUCT SOLUTIONIf transferring is right, our flexible Retirement Account offers:• a simple service charge• a suite of investment solutions• online features and tools to support clients to and through retirement.Find out more at scottishwidows.co.uk/defined-benefitor email our specialist team on DBsupport@scottishwidows.co.ukHELPING YOU MAKE THE MOST OF CHANGEThis information is for UK Financial Adviser use only and should not be distributed to or relied upon by any other person.Scottish Widows Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 3196171. Registered office in the United Kingdom at 25 Gresham Street, London EC2V 7HN. Authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority. Financial Services Register number 181655. 26405 04/17]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[40RISKNEW! Get your Synaptic Risk Ratings here - at no extra costEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedThere is a terrific debate going on around the role of research (following on from FCA 16/1). It reflects the increasing importance of managing investment risk, the corresponding role that risk plays in a portfolio and how risk-based decisions about asset allocation are taking centre stage in determining investment strategies in firms.There is no bigger consideration than riskat the current time – which makes the fact that there is a lack of objective, quantitative research to support advisers in this area more surprising. It is timely therefore for Synapticto extend the reach and depth of its research around risk, and publish their Synaptic Risk Ratings as an integral part of the Synaptic Product and Fund research tool package (which can be found in the investment product are of the tool).Reflecting the fast growth of this research area within Synaptic, counting over 20 fund groups, discretionary investors and wealth managers, Synaptic Risk Ratings will now be directly accessible in the day to day research of over 8k Synaptic software subscribers. This represents that most significant enhancement of the Synaptic proposition since the launch of Modeller several years ago.In providing advisers access to the Moody’s Analytics (formerly Barrie + Hibbert)’s riskframework, Synaptic already offers perhaps the most accomplished resource in managing investment risk. There are many reasons why Moody’s treatment of risk is pre-eminent:• Capture of potential downside. We can use hindsight to review the historic predictions and see that they have been accurate over many market cycles;• Capture of ‘tail risk’, including the 2008 ‘Great Depression’;• Ongoing due diligence. The capital market assumptions are what define the rules that underpin the model, and determine whatis ‘feasible’. Moody’s model is constantly being reviewed and evaluated (internally and externally by the large institutions that rely on Moody’s expertise for their own forecasts).At any one time there is rash of commentators declaring ‘that things are different now’; that the bond bull market is dead; that the S&P is overvalued and therefore non-investable; thatinflation will be rampant in 18 months time; that any one of many faddish ‘insights’ should determine your asset allocation. Heed these and you may be compromising your clients’ long term prospects. Good stocks may decline but they will also recover. Fads will leave you dead in the water - well diversified portfolios built using established research based principles will prevail. Stick to the Moody’s Asset Allocation model.The beauty of the stochastically generated, probability based projections, such as those that underpin the Synaptic Risk Rating service, is that you can quantify the extent of likely losses – which of course is what is the FCA wants you to do, empirically, according to its notion of Capacity for Loss.In Moody’s world for example, a Cautious investment strategy is one that ‘risks’ losses ofupto5%ina‘bad’year–thatistosaythe ‘bad’ year that is mathematically projected to occur once in a term of 20 years of investment.]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[RISK41Synaptic Risk Rating will provide the bedrock in terms of suitability - as it is unique in the industry as an objective and consistent measure for investment risk.Screen below shows format for new Synaptic Risk Metrics, incorporating RSMR commentary.Screen below shows Synaptic Product and Fund grid with Synaptic Risk Rated funds and portfolios. See column ‘Minimum gain’ for ‘Capacity for Loss’ quotient.The concept of ‘capacity for Loss’ is the most useful tool for an adviser if correctly measured. Even those invested in the 2008 downturn were fine as long as they didn’t cut and run.If their adviser had correctly judged their ‘capacity for loss’, they would have been within the Moody’s tolerances for loss and back on track. Too much risk in their portfolios andthey would have certainly imploded, with a (legitimate) complaint ensuing.What are the Synaptic Risk Ratings?• On a quarterly basis, Moody’s updatetheir Economic Scenario Generator, the mathematical, probability based model that underpins the Synaptic Risk Ratings.• The risk rated funds and portfolios are re-run through the updated model, projecting on the underlying asset allocation, taking into account the interaction of the various asset classes making up the investment in the multiple scenarios.• The results from these calculations allow Synaptic to calibrate the existing fundsand portfolios against the Moody’s model, attributing a risk category to the investment, as well as a ‘decimalised’ number, ranging from 1.0-5.9, offering in effect 50 steps, or grades of risk exposure.• Obviously with the Synaptic approach, users can freely access the risk profiling questionnaire, Risk Categories and descriptions.• Users who use other systems than Synaptic or Moody’s for aligning risk can still include a Synaptic Risk Fact sheet with their compliance submission. The Capacity for Loss figure, which is the published as the ‘5% minimum gain’, or ‘one in 20 years loss’ is just as relevant a measure outside of the full Synaptic system.How should they be used?• The Regulator requires that a recommendation should be suitable on an individual basis. The metrics published as part of the Ratings can be related to any case. No recommendation should be made according to a single measure, but the Synaptic Risk Rating will provide the bedrock in terms of suitability – as it is unique in the industryas an objective and consistent measure for investment risk.Call us on 0800 783 4477 to gain access to the free Synaptic Risk Profiling Questionnaire, or visit www.synaptic.co.uk for more information.]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[F&C MM Lifestyle FoundationF&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) F&C MM Navigator Distribution F&C MM Navigator ModerateF&C MM Navigator ProgressiveF&C MM Navigator SelectF&C MM Navigator BoutiquesCarmignac Portfolio Capital Cube Carmignac Portfolio Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Emergents Carmignac Portfolio Grande Europe Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Commodities Carmignac Portfolio Capital Plus Carmignac Portfolio SécuritéCarmignac Portfolio Investissement Carmignac Portfolio Global Bond Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Discovery Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Entrepreneurs Carmignac Portfolio Euro-PatrimoineCautious MPSIncome MPSBalanced MPSGrowth MPSGlobal Equity MPS Cautious Passive+ Income Passive+ Balanced Passive+ Growth Passive+ Global Equity Passive+CF Canlife Portfolio III CF Canlife Portfolio IV CF Canlife Portfolio V CF Canlife Portfolio VI CF Canlife Portfolio VII Canlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 7Cautious Moderately CautiousBalanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Dynamic Passive 1 Dynamic Passive 2 Dynamic Passive 3 Dynamic Passive 4 Dynamic Passive 5Close Bond Income Portfolio FundClose Managed Income FundClose Managed Conservative FundClose Managed Balanced FundClose Managed Growth FundClose Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund Close DMS Income PlusClose DMS ConservativeClose DMS BalancedClose DMS GrowthClose Diversified Income Portfolio Fund Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Balanced Portfolio FundClose Growth Portfolio FundMulti Manager Income 1 Multi Manager Total Return 1 Multi Manager Total Return 2 Multi Manager Total Return 3 Multi Manager Income 2 Multi Manager Income 3 Multi Manager Total Return 4 Multi Manager Income 4 Multi Manager Total Return 5 Multi Manager Income 5Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios MI Hawksmoor VanbrughMI Hawksmoor DistributionDefensive Cautious Balanced Growth Aggressive DistributionDynamic PassiveMulti ManagerAccess the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-riskDiversified Income Fund Diversified Growth FundMAPManaged Growth FundInvestec Cautious Managed Fund]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Multi-Index Income 6MP3 MP50 MP4 MP5 MP6 MP7Adventurous Portfolio Income Seeker Portfolio Growth Seeker Portfolio Income Focus Portfolio Temperate Portfolio Growth Focus Portfolio Lower Risk Income Portfolio Lower Risk Growth Portfolio Protective PortfolioFundsPremier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market FundPremier Defensive Growth FundPremier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund Premier Diversified FundPremier Liberation IV FundPremier Liberation V FundPremier Liberation VI FundPremier Liberation VII FundPortfoliosPremier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income PortfolioPremier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced PortfolioPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth PortfolioPremier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[PruFund CautiousPruFund Protected Cautious PruFund GrowthPruFund Protected Growth PruFund 0-30PruFund 10-40PruFund 20-55PruFund 40-80Dynamic 0-30Dynamic 10-40Dynamic 20-55Dynamic 40-80Dynamic 60-100WP Optimum Return Focused 0-30Focused 10-40Focused 20-55Focused 40-80Focused 60-100Cautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus EquityEquity PlusMPS Global Growth MPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global Income MPS IncomeMPS ConservativeMPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)Strategy 1 Strategy 2 Strategy 3 Strategy 4 Strategy 5 Strategy 6RMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic IncomeBespokeManaged PortfoliosMulti Asset]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[RL Governed Portfolio 1 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 7 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 (s) RL GRIP 1RL GRIP 2 RL GRIP 3 RL GRIP 4 RL GRIP 5Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive PortfolioPositive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus PortfolioRussell Secure PortfolioRussell Cautious PortfolioRussell Conservative PortfolioRussell Moderate PortfolioRussell Balanced PortfolioRussell Progressive PortfolioRussell Adventurous PortfolioRussell Growth PortfolioRussell Aggressive PortfolioRussell Aggressive PlusRussell Defensive Assets FundRussell Investments Real Assets Fund Russell Investments UK GrowthRussell Investments International Growth Russell Investments MA Growth 1 Russell Investments MA Growth 2 Russell Investments MA Growth 3 Russell Investments MA Growth 4 Russell Investments MA Growth 5 Russell Investments MA IncomeSchroder MM DiversitySchroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK GrowthSchroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[CautiousIncomePersonal Injury Moderately Cautious BalancedModerately Adventurous AdventurousThesis Optima Income Thesis Optima Balanced Thesis Optima GrowthCommercial Freehold FundVanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%ACUMEN Conservative Portfolio ACUMEN Income Portfolio ACUMEN Progressive Portfolio ACUMEN Adventurous Portfolio Tavistock PB PROFILE 3 Tavistock PB PROFILE 4 Tavistock PB PROFILE 5 Tavistock PB PROFILE 6 Tavistock PB PROFILE 7 Tavistock PB PROFILE 8 Tavistock PB IncomeTW PROFILE 3TW PROFILE 4TW PROFILE 5TW PROFILE 6TW PROFILE 7TW PROFILE 8 Tavistock PROFILE 3 Tavistock PROFILE 4 Tavistock PROFILE 5 Tavistock PROFILE 6 Tavistock PROFILE 7 Tavistock PROFILE 8]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[PortfoliosFP Verbatim Portfolio 3FP Verbatim Portfolio 4FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth FP Verbatim Portfolio 6FP Verbatim Portfolio 7FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 IncomeVDSVDSJH3 VDSJH4 VDSJH5 VDSJH6 VDSJH7 VDSJH8 VDS RSMR 2 VDS RSMR 3 VDS RSMR 4 VDS RSMR 5 VDS RSMR 6 VDS RSMR 7 VDS RSMR 8 VDS RSMR 9 VDS RSMR 10 VDS TCF 3 VDS TCF 4 VDS TCF 5 VDS TCF 6 VDS TCF 7 VDS TCF 8 VDS S&W 3 VDS S&W 4 VDS S&W 5 VDS S&W 6 VDS S&W 7 VDS S&W 8 VDSHR3 VDSHR4 VDSHR5 VDSHR6 VDSHR7 VDSHR8Total ClarityTotal Clarity Portfolio 3 Total Clarity Portfolio 4 Total Clarity Portfolio 5 Total Clarity Portfolio 6RSMRRSM Model Portfolio 2 RSM Model Portfolio 3 RSM Model Portfolio 4 RSM Model Portfolio 5 RSM Model Portfolio 6 RSM Model Portfolio 7 RSM Model Portfolio 8 RSM Model Portfolio 9 RSM Model Portfolio 10(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further information before recommending.About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Synaptic Risk is an integral part of the Synaptic Suite available to all financial advisers. Offers objective research to complement your firm’s qualitative fund analysis.• ATRQ - The industry’s most widely used Attitude to Risk Questionnaire• Risk Ratings table - a comprehensive table of the providers’ funds and portfolios represented in the ratings, available to download and/or print• Risk Fact Sheets - all participating DFM, managed or model portfolio, multi-asset or other funds have unique fact sheets, these show risk ratings in decimalised format, risk metrics from the stochastic modelling and asset allocation data•• •An objective risk measure for your investment recommendations - achieved via access to the industry’s leading stochastic engine from Moody’s AnalyticsBetter advice outcomes - from superior risk analysis and managementAchieve ‘Informed’ consent – quantify possible investment loss and gain using a meaningful and consistent measurements of riskRISK RATING4 RISK RATING5SYNAPTIC SYNAPTICRISK RATING1 RISK RATING2SYNAPTICRISK RATING3SYNAPTIC SYNAPTICSYNAPTIC RISKProvides fund and portfolio risk ratings underpinned by the industry’s leading risk expertiseYou can use the Synaptic Risk Ratings to meet FCA requirements around risk and present to clients using attractive and comprehensive risk metrics.CautiousModerately CautiousBalancedModerately AdventurousAdventurousThe Synaptic Risk proposition offers the leading risk analysis in a simple, completepackage to assist your compliance and ensure buy-in from your clients. This willcompliment any qualitative or volatility based research or analysis that you may be relying upon. And it's free!Adam Byford, Managing Director, Synaptic Software LimitedFor more information about Synaptic Risk please visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477What does it include?How does it work ?What difference will it make to my clients]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50Page needs logo and brand colIncome Protection: cover that works when your clients can’tAccording to the Aviva Protecting our Families report, currently only 13% of families with dependent children have income protection, yet 43% say an absence from work of 3 months or less would leave them struggling financially.This protection deficit represents an opportunity to support clients by exploring how they would protect their income if they became unable to work due to illness or injury – and it’s something we’re keen to help advisers address.Bitesize chunksWe know that these conversations are complex, that’s why we’ve been looking at supporting advisers with a broad range of market insight and transforming it into bitesize chunks that can be absorbed quickly. The aim of this is to allow you to build meaningful conversations with your clients and really help them understand how income protection can offer a financial lifeline in a time when families have had to tighten their belts.We’ve looked at areas such as:• The importance of taking out an income protection policy• Facts, figures and focus points – how you can engage clients in income protection conversations• What you need to know about the income protection market• How our Income Protection+ proposition can help you and your clients‘Straight forward and seamless’Income protection needn’t be about lengthy application forms and poor claims pay-out rates. We’ll show you how straight forward and seamless it really can be through harnessing digital solutions, such as iGPRTM and interactive underwriting, to help make managing protection as simple as possible. All this means you can spend more time understanding and meeting your clients’ individual needs. As for claims, in 2015 we paid over 92% of individual income protection claims.137.3 million working days lostThe Office of National Statistics predicted that in 2016 an estimated 137.3 million working days were lost to sickness or injury in the UK. This will be made up from a combination of minor conditions and longer term illnesses with our average individual income protection claim, that was still in payment at the end of 2015, lasting for 9 years.Visit aviva-for-advisers.co.ukAs an adviser, you know that income protection can help financially protect against unforeseen events. Visit aviva-for-advisers.co.uk to review our income protection case study video, statistical fact sheets and much, much more – to get plugged in to protection and switch on your client conversations.Aviva Life Services UK Limited. Registered in England No 2403746. Aviva,Wellington Row,York,YO90 1WR.Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Firm Reference Number 145452o]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[oursGet plugged in to Income ProtectionSwitch on your clientconversationsComplicated, time consuming, expensive... These are just some of the misconceptions that clients sometimes have when it comes to Income Protection. Let us help you bust the IP myths and provide the bite-sized stats and information to highlight the value of Income Protection and start useful conversations with your clients.VisitJ13055-AL52003-1016.indd 1Aviva-for-advisers.co.ukRetirement Investments Insurance HealthtRoetfirienmdenot uItnvmestmoernets Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirementInvestments Insurance Health Retirement Investments Insurance Health Retirement Investments Insurance Health Retirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance HealthRetirement Investments Insurance Health Why choosesIannsurce HealthentRetirement Investments Insurance Health Income Protection+? Please note: This guide provides brief summaries of the cover and options available. For full details you must read the policy summary and policy conditions.RetiremInvestmentIncome Protection from Aviva Mrs Wallis’ story27/10/2016 16:03AL 52 016 04/2017 © Aviva plcRetirement Investments Insurance Health]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52Page needs logo and brand col5 things that will change about the way protection policies are underwritten in the next 5 years (and a couple of things that won’t)Andrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskThere will be more variable premium policies for other conditions and benefitsProducts launched this spring from The Exeter and Royal London show the way – allowing people with medical conditions to be rewarded for improving their health. These new style products are both fully underwritten up front but then have the premium amended each year based on a single risk factor of BMI (for weight) or HBA1c (for diabetes).Many will be watching how advisers andthe public respond to these products. If they seem to take hold expect a slew of similar products, based around wearables and other health technology to enable the premiumsto be more subtly varied. The real hope with this is that rather than tweaking premiums for Life cover, it allows insurance to be offered to people who otherwise would not have been able to get it. People like type 1 diabetics such as Theresa May for income protection, for example!The binary approach of non medical limits to evidence gathering will be replaced by a more granular, risk based approachNon medical limits are one of many “features” that are still embedded in the protection process from days of yore. These stepped limits relate solely to age bands and sum assured to identify a group of customersto get evidence on before acceptance. This method is outrageously unsophisticated compared to methods applied to evaluate high risk applicants in other areas of the financial services world.In the medium term expect companies to move from tables to algorithms, bringing in more factors in order to judge the risk and whether it makes economic sense to get other evidence. Of course the type of evidence obtained is likely to change too – not just from paper to electronic GPRs but to more discrete testing as the quality of information held bya GP continues to deteriorate within a morefragmented NHS. The overlay of risk presented and usefulness of evidence considered should become more subtle and precise. As with most advances the challenge will be to do more with less – to target the evidence well enough that the predictions get better to mean less inconvenient testing and lower prices.There will be more information and interaction with answers givenToday insurers seek congratulations for being polite enough to let a customer know why their premium has increased. In the futureI expect more to not just to embrace that minimum element of respect, but go beyond this. The answers given are a potential wayto start tailoring future dialogue – focusing health or travel guidance depending on what is known about the customer. Specialist advisers are currently leading the way with this – it will be interesting to see whether it is ultimately advisers or insurers who invest and make a difference in this space.Contrary to some surveys and many adviser’s wishes there will still be a load (if that is the collective noun) of underwriters in the future.o]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours53The one size fits all model is no more likely to fit for insurance than it is for any other retail model. Each individual’s prioritisation between time, price and product quality will vary and the best journey for them should flex accordingly.There will be more distinct approaches from insurersThe one size fits all model is no more likelyto fit for insurance than it is for any other retail model. Each individual’s prioritisation between time, price and product quality will vary and the best journey for them should flex accordingly. Insurers and tech companies need to get much closer to the front end triaging that provides the oil in existing journeys –the “so how healthy are you generally” type question that pushes them down one route rather than the other.Journeys like Cover Me Now offer a great solution for a healthy individual who wantsa good price and product in quick time. Approaches for other niches including lives with specific medical conditions are also likely to be developed.There will be more underwriting of older livesFor all the toes being dipped in insurtech waters there is a more compelling short term case for growth from an increase in Life, CI and IP products being sold to people who are retiring later in life. This should mean a differentemphasisinquestionsreflectingthenorms – for example asking “what medication are you taking” rather than “are you onany medication”. It will also require more understanding of the early signs of dementias and other conditions that affect people more in their 50s and 60s than 30s and 40s.Genetics won’t have radically changed the (insurance) worldAdvances in understanding of genetics are as rapid as they are excitingly transformative. This presents huge opportunities for medical science but the imbalance of knowledge caused specifically by genetic testing poses a large theoretical future risk to insurers. This gets talked about frequently – particularly regarding Critical Illness policies when insurers are putting prices up (although less so when customers are pushing for prices to go down for life insurance).There may be some areas where there are spikes in Critical Illness claims from a generous wording that gets picked off with later genetics advances. But the overall landscape will not create a catastrophic imbalance of knowledge requiring us to rethink the model altogether. Rather I see the deeper understanding of the interactions between genes and environment meaningthatpeopleappreciatebetterthanever the variety of factors that cause and prevent conditions occurring. This may lead to a wider approach to underwriting, including more lifestyle factors – whether sought through questions or data from wearables rather than giving up altogether and adopting guaranteed policies more broadly.Underwriting will still existContrary to some surveys and many adviser’s wishes there will still be a load (if that is the collective noun) of underwriters in the future. The roles will evolve and more understanding of customers and their behaviours required to fulfil all the requirements above – but we’ll be here for a while yet, whether you like it or not!For more information on Cover Me Now see the article on pages 54 & 55 or visit www.synaptic.co.uk/covermenowCOVER ME NOW]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[54COVER ME NOWCover Me Now - Protection Cover as it should bePaul Quarendon | Product Manager | Synaptic Software LimitedProgress can sometimes be measured in small steps, but the arrival of Cover Me Now into the market place marks a major step forward in an industry, which for years has been struggling to improve its customer engagement and sales performance.Uninsured debt in our country should keep Advisers and Providers up at night, butdo they need to be with new onboarding systems making insurance a lot easier to access? Protection needs to become a more integral part of the holistic advice conversation, leaving the customer in no doubt that they are risking so much for their family should the worst happen.There are bright spots however - Critical Illness definitions being regularly updated to make it more relevant and accessible to all consumers, and even growth in sales of Income Protection!So, talking of streamlining on-boarding processes and new horizons, Cover Me Now is now into its second month. While still in its infancy, I thought it prudent to remind you of the important role it can play in protection discussions.• The journey is offered with Covea Life, who have designed their Cover Me Now Term Life product especially for this new portaljourney. Currently only available to The Right Mortgage Network, it offers a simple sales journey that avoids cumbersome underwriting, visiting providers’ extranets for further form-filling, tele-underwriting••••interviews or further correspondence of any kind.Applicants must be able to answer 14 simple yes/no health questions to be offered a guaranteed premium with immediate cover. Over 70% of applicants will be successful in meeting these criteria.As is traditional, premiums will vary according to age, term, smoker status and cover amounts, but there are many ‘sweet spots’ where cover will be cheaper than other providers’ prices.Indicative quotes obtained from the underlying Webline technology will also pull through into the results page to ensure you see a full range of options.Modern technology and professional styling ensures a slick, easy to use interface that will deliver a fast and comfortable journey and completion of application.“Buying life cover should be easy and hassle-free for both the Adviser and the Customer. Cover Me Now ticks all the boxes!”Paul Quarendon, Product Manager, Synaptic Software]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[COVER ME NOW55The newly launched Cover Me Now journeyQuote Application processKey Health QuestionsResults - Cover Me Now guaranteed premiums with indicative premiums from range of providers immediately beneath.Synaptic is a major player in the Protection Portal space with an infrastructure that manages the sourcing and delivery of protection quotes from the key providers in the UK Insurance market. Around a fifth of UK Term products alone are facilitated by Synaptic’s Webline portal technology.Having proved the concept of providing the Cover Me Now product works, Synaptic is keen to explore how this new on-boarding process can benefit our existing customers, and also new firms who may have a requirement to streamline the sales process.Call now on 0800 783 4477 to discuss how you could benefit from Cover Me Now, or visit our website for further informationwww.synaptic.co.uk/covermenow]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[lgim.comAs one of the world’s largest investment companies, with total assets of £901.9bn*, we believe we have a huge responsibility. Not just to our clients but to society as a whole. That’s why we use our voice to encourage companies to act positively. To build a stronger, more principled investment world. In part because we believe that good corporate governance protects the long-term prospects of our investors. But also because it’s the right thing to do.*As at 31.12.16. Includes assets managed by LGIMA, an SEC Registered Investment Advisor. Data includes derivative positions and advisory assets. Legal and General Investment Management is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.We don’t just take a passive role in the companies we invest in.We make ourselves heard on behalf of our investors.]]></page></pages></Search>