<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q1 2016Selection of industry features for the professional adviserSee inside for Synaptic Risk Ratings• Proof of suitability is easy with Synaptic• Own suitability and risk before suitability and risk own you • Synaptic contract enquiry service, Marie AylwardSynaptic guide to ethical investing• Enquiring stewards, Julia Dreblow• SRI investing - how to choose funds• Spotlight on SRI funds, Rathbones and Alliance Trust • Values as well as value, Nurjanon BegumA year of innovation‘It won’t be boring’ Mark PolsonInside...›› Synaptic’s Robo perspective, Eric Armstrong›› Market outlook from Multi Asset Team, M&G and Peter Westaway, Vanguard ›› The trials of Model Portfolio Research, Tahmina Mannan›› The importance of rebalancing, Justin Onuekwusi›› Active vs Passive - Don’t waste oxygen, Justin U-S›› Time Diversification vs Rebalancing In Retirement Portfolios, Abraham Okusanya ›› Email encryption, Paul Holland]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Enjoy an easy life with WeblineBuying financial products online has never been easier with the help of the Synaptic Webline portal, which can be accessed forNot only can you compare hundreds of online products against each other, you can also apply online directly into the chosen providers extranet, reducing time and effort usually spent re-keying data.By applying directly from Synaptic Webline firms may be entitled to an extra 10% of additional commission –For more information call us on0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.ukApplying Online - The Myths and Facts• The cost for applying via Webline is exactly the same astrading with the Provider on their site.• Webline portal will take a cut of the plan commission due to the adviser.• Applying via Webline means the data from the quote is populated, avoiding double data entry.• Application process cannot be re-started from within Webline service.• The Providers treat the application in exactly the same way as an application coming in via their extranet.• Advisers are often entitled up to an additional 10%commission when applying from Webline into provider extranet.• The client data is not kept by Webline, the application is input directly onto the provider’s system.• There is no cost to you or the client for sending the application in via Webline.Free to existing customersthis could result in huge gainsyou could even earn more commissionFact MythFactFact MythFact FactFact]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[CONTENTSIt won’t be boring 04 Mark Polson, the lang catM&G Multi Asset Team: Market Outlook 06Economic and market outlook: 10 muted growth and returns expectedPeter Westaway, VanguardThe trials of Model Portfolio Research 12 Tahmina Mannan, FEThe importance of rebalancing for 14 multi-asset investors Justin Onuekwusi, Legal &General Investment ManagementThe Real Value of Active Managers 16 Justin Urqhart-Stewart, Seven InvestmentManagementNew State Pension - winner or loser? 18 FionaTait, RoyalLondonTime Diversification Vs Rebalancing In 20 Retirement PortfoliosAbraham Okusanya, FinalytiQSynaptic’s Robo perspective 22 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedProof of suitability is easy with Synaptic 24 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedOwn suitability and risk before suitability and 26 risk own you Eric Armstrong, Synaptic SoftwareLimitedSynaptic Risk Table 29The New Synaptic 34 Contract Enquiry serviceMarie Aylward, Synaptic Software LimitedIt’sgoodtotalk!.....Orisit? 36 Paul Holland, Beyond EncryptionEnquiring stewards... researching the issues 38 others may fail to considerJulia Dreblow, Sri ServicesSRI Investing - how to choose funds 40 Stewart Smith, RSMRSustainable Future funds deliver strong 42 investment performance Mike Appleby, AllianceTrust InvestmentsRathbone Ethical Bond Fund 43 Bryn Jones, Head of Fixed IncomeEthical Investing value as well as values, 44 Nurjanon Begum, Synaptic Software LimitedCover Me Now Andrew Wibberley, Alea Risk 46If I die the business dies Marcus Primhak, LV= 48Introducing British Friendly Society John Willis, 50 Synaptic Software LimitedI don’t need protection, I’m young! Denise Wond, 52 Royal LondonGood health is good business Sally Hogbin, 54 VitalityLife3Something has changedContact DetailsSynaptic Software LimitedFusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AASales: 0800 783 4477 www.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Hardmannaomi.hardman@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969Resistance to technological change has often been explained by the role of regulation. It was never attractive for technologically orientated firms to try and innovate in our world because of regulation. This is no longer true, as the regulator throws the kitchen sink at initiatives to encourage FinTech and other technology based change.E&Y have helped the government identify the FinTech revenues they intend to increase for the general health of the economy, which includes £10bn revenue made up of Financial Data and Analytics, Financial Software and Platforms. E&Y describe the sweet spot for technological innovation as ‘Consumers are ready’; Industry conditions favour innovation’; the technology works’ and (crucially) ‘Regulations are changing quickly’.This all spells enormous opportunityas well as challenges for our adviser community. Advisers will provide the human element in what is going to be a more Robo (or Cyborg actually) orientated future. Greater sophistication will be required in the use of best advice tools,for example risk management tools such as Synaptic Risk to devise and explain strategies to clients experiencing increasing levels of market volatility or Product and Fund analysis required to support strategies for income in retirement.You may not realise, but Synaptic Webline is already way ahead in supporting large distributors for quotes and access to protection sales. Keep your eye out for more information about our Cover Me Now initiative.Most readers will have heard ofMoore’s Law or a version of it. Based on observations made by one of the founders of Intel, the law explains how quickly the pace of change moves. The time it takes for a technological measure to double decreases exponentially, whether it is the number of transistors in an integrated circuit, computing power or memory, the proliferation of the internet or evolution of artificial intelligence. Anyway, we intend to keep you informed from our perspective over the next few editions of Connection of the changes we think are relevant,and invite you to speak to us about any technological change you are interested in exploring with your software solutions.Eric ArmstrongEditorThe Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expresses throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all nights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4It won’t be boringMark Polson | Founder, the lang cat@theactualpolson assesses our prospects for 2016So far 2016 has been a real downer. As I write we’re waiting for a big ol’ storm to arrive from the East Coast of America, where it’s dumped up to 6 feet of snow in nothing flat. Half the UK is needing wrung out. We’ve lost David Bowie, and to top it off we’re talking about bringing back commission. I’m thinking of opting out.So it looks like 2016 is going to be a year of extremes. That’s OK – it won’t be boring – but while we watch lots of new things happening it’s important we don’t take our collective eyes off the ball, and by ball I do mean clients. As long as we’re clear on that.The truth is that most of the big development themes you’ll see bandied around in thepress this year will take some time to really impact your clients’ lives – if they do at all. As has always been the case, if you have a good relationship with your client (no, not like that, there wouldn’t be time) and are delivering financial planning that they understand and can put into practice, then the world of tech, platforms, products and componentry need be no more than a sideshow.But it will be an extremely noisy sideshow. Here are a few things that I think you’ll either enjoy reading about or be completely sick of, or both at different times, from the business we call show in 2016.First of all, roboadvice. Roboadvice – a word which is impossible to say quickly ten times in succession – is good because it makes people, mainly advisers, cross. That in turn makes them eager to defend the values of financial planning and to work out what it is they do over and above what the robos have to offer.At the lang cat we do some work with Paul Resnik of the risk profiling firm Finametrica, and Paul has a good take on all this stuff. He reckons the market for automated or algorithmic advice will split into two parts– weapons-grade enterprise roboadvice,and what he calls ‘cowbos’. Cowbos are the entrepreneurial ones who are out to disturb the market. They’re brash, fun, and hog the limelight. Sometimes they rope cattle. That’s not true, don’t know why I said it.To fast-forward through to the end – the big- scale robos win. The cowbos, if they’re lucky, come up with something good which means they’re of value to one of the big guys, and they get snaffled. Most often that’ll be when they’ve built something themselves, but it might be for special knowledge or skills. Funnily enough, earlier today I read about eVestor, the robo firm established by Duncan Cameron,the co-founder of Moneysupermarket, and Anthony Morrow, one of the founding shareholders of Paradigm, gulping Rohan]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[5Why do the big guys win? Because countercultural startuppery is great fun, and brilliant to write and read about. But trusting an unknown brand with your money on the basis of something new and cool is not something the great British public will do lightly.Sivajoti’s Postcard Planning firm for an undisclosed sum. PP is a new business which aims at a younger demographic, and which also has a robo arm called – and don’t shoot me, I’m just reporting it – Lemon Squeezy.Why do the big guys win? Because countercultural startuppery is great fun, and brilliant to write and read about. But trusting an unknown brand with your money onthe basis of something new and cool is not something the great British public will do lightly. It’s easy to forget the last time the nation did something like that. It was called Icesave and it didn’t work out too well.So by all means look at and think about automated or remote advice for earlier stage investors. But lots of other folks will be, and you’ll need to think how to stand out from brands with the punching power of Santander, Vanguard and others. Oh, and it won’t be any kind of get-rich-quick scheme – the composite charge for eVestor is going to be 0.44%.There is one element of robodom which I think might start to make a difference to adviser everyday lives this year, or maybe next, ornot at all (please bear in mind I spend a lot of time writing compliant copy), and that’s in the streamlining of gathering client details and identity verification. I think this will be the yearwhen – if you can offer the facility – you’ll find that many individuals start to be comfortable serving their own data.Indeed, there’s an interesting study from Linkedin in the USA which suggests that younger investors – what we call ‘affluent millenials’ in the look-at-me marketing game – would actually prefer to put their own data in rather than have it collected by a nice man in a suit. That way they know it’s right – and they don’t have to pay £150/hour to give frankly basic info which is part of every factfind. Keep a eye on developments on this front from platforms, vertically integrated providers and maybe even back office system providers. When allied to a good client portal there is lots to enjoy here.The other theme you’ll probably read alot about is something called ‘blockchain’.In effect this is what sits underneath the cryptocurrency called bitcoin, which is beloved of geeks and confusing to everyone else. What blockchain does is remove the need for a trusted party to keep a big database of Stuff. In our world that trusted party is probably a custodian or transfer agent. Instead of getting one of these guys to do the work, there is a decentralised register which is replicated across potentially millions of sites, all of which update dynamically all the time so that a) dependencyon a few big firms is removed and b) security could actually be increased. If that doesn’t make sense then don’t worry. Blockchain could rewire the house, and drop the electricity bill quite dramatically, but unless you’re highly motivated it’s not something for now.What else? The Financial Advice Market Review (FAMR) will be big news. Many providers are awaiting both its findings and any bombshells on pensions tax treatmentin Ozzy’s second budget of this Parliament before pulling the trigger on big proposition spend which could be interesting for advisers. A modest flutter on a carve-out for simplified advice delivered on non-toxic areas with a minimum of discretion for the adviser (who may be able to be QCF Level 3, and to take some form of commission) feels likely. Expect a flurry of new tech to look at in the months following FAMR’s publication. Assuming, of course, that the Osbot hasn’t completely filleted the pensions sector by this time.So no, it won’t be boring. There will be plenty to think about over and above the day-to-day of running an adviser business. The good news in all this is that everything that’s going on lowers the barriers to making big changes for the future and helps firms design and create service propositions that genuinely might be a break from the norm.]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[6M&G Multi Asset Team: Market Outlook 2016The dominant topic for investors today remains global policy activity.Markets have set themselves in ‘policy watch’ mode. From this point, even a small surprise from the central banks could trigger significant price action. In such an environment, we believe it is more important than ever to focus more on fundamentals, in terms of what trends in data are telling us about the health of the global economy. Nothing we have seen in recent data has prompted us to materially reassess our view that the aggregate global economy is growing at a moderate pace, while inflation remains low. So our global economic outlook remains broadly positive, although we expect the volatility that characterised the market environment of 2015 to continue to be a key feature during 2016.The folly of forecastingAt this time of year, we are often asked for our views on the outlook for markets in the coming year. We think it is important to acknowledge that, as uncomfortable as it may be to admit, no one can be sure about the future. Therefore, for us, spending too much time and energy on economic forecastingcan be an unhelpful distraction from what really matters – in-depth analysis of the facts underlying the environment in which we find ourselves today, coupled with observations of what current asset pricing, in the context of that environment, is telling us about where the greatest opportunities and risks are now. On that basis, although we cannot claim to know what lies ahead, we can make some key observations about the current investment landscape.Volatility to persistWhen we look back at 2015, the most striking feature was the return of market volatility, most notably in equities and emergingmarkets, but evident across most asset classes and regions. During certain phases, we experienced dramatic market swings, sometimes over intra-day periods. This seemed at odds with trends in data – in developed markets at least – indicating ongoing economic recovery.Our sense is that the clearest explanationfor this dislocation between price action and fundamentals is that investors, still traumatised by the shock of the Global Financial Crisis, are struggling to have faith in this growth and will require very strong evidence for a prolonged period to accept that a deep-seated recoveryis indeed under way. With sentiment so fragile and sensitive, we expect volatility to persistfor some time yet. However, it is importantto remember that short-term volatility does not always equal true risk, and often presents compelling opportunities for those with the emotional fortitude to take it on.Policymakers in the spotlightThe unprecedented levels of intervention bycentral bankers since 2008 means markets have become highly sensitive to their words and actions in recent years. We expect the likes of Yellen, Draghi and Kuroda to remain in the headlines into 2016 as, on the one hand, US policymakers try to nudge up interest rates without spooking markets, and on the other, the European Central Bank, Bank of Japanand People’s Bank of China look to additional measures for boosting growth. All of this means we find ourselves in an environment that appears unstable, with a great deal of focus on what policymakers will do next, particularly in terms of the historically low cash rates that have affected asset prices across the global investment universe.A divided worldWhen we look at the global economic landscape today, we see a major division between Asia and emerging markets, on one side, and the US and Europe, on the other. Asia and emerging markets are experiencing a clear slowdown. By contrast, the economic news]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[coming out of the US and Europe continues to indicate robust recovery. Although the situation in emerging markets represents genuine fundamental risk to certain regions, the extent to which it is likely to affect domestic demand in the developed world is, we believe, limited – certainly relative to the impact of a decline in the economy of a major developed country. This means we maintain a positive outlook at the global, aggregate level.However, this combination of a general lackof belief in global growth and attempts to untangle meaningful messages from every policy statement (no matter how seemingly meaningless) leaves investors with a lot of different factors to weigh up. We think thisis causing a great deal of confusion around how any asset ‘should’ be priced in the current environment.We anticipate this confusion will continue to drive periods of material mispricing – and hence investment opportunities – across asset classes.Oil slump may yet be feltOver the past 12 months or so, we have been among those believing the decline in the oil price to be a net positive economic factorat the global aggregate level, in terms of the effective tax cut it provides to businesses and consumers. However, we expected something of a lag before the effect was felt. Consumer indicators in the West appear to be showing that it has begun feeding through recently, which we think is likely to continue into 2016.This further bolsters our central view that the fundamental environment is supportive for growth and, therefore, for risk assets broadly. Lower commodity prices also contribute to our view that inflation is likely to remainlow, allowing policymakers to remain accommodative even in a growth environment, although we do believe inflation could start gradually picking up in certain areas over the months ahead.Equity risk premium the clearest signalOur positive outlook for global growth means equities remain our favoured asset class overall, from both a fundamental and valuation standpoint. Certainly, most equity markets are not as ‘cheap’ as they were two years ago, butthe significant equity risk premium remains the most compelling valuation signal today.We have to remember that this risk premium is because bonds are expensive, rather than because equities are cheap, and so we believe the prudent way to play this is to be neutralto slightly overweight equity, and underweight bonds. However, with the world so divided, it is vital to be selective within asset classes.In our view, European and Japanese equity is priced for stronger prospective returns than US equity – although certain areas of theUS market, such as banks, looked attractive, especially given the potential to perform well in a rising rate environment. Some emerging market equities are also very attractively priced, but the level of genuine fundamental risk means we are engaging with these assets more modestly.Bond yields should riseIn recent years, the consensus view thatthe global economy is struggling – despite evidence to the contrary – has driven mainstream bond yields to what are, in our view, unjustifiable lows. We believe mainstream government bonds, especially at the shortend, are generally overvalued, although wesee some value at the longer end of the US curve. The fact that the collapse in yields to generational lows has persisted for so much longer than could be expected highlights how difficult it is to predict when this situationwill change. Nonetheless, we do expectyields to rise in 2016 and we are watchful for opportunities in this space.For now, peripheral European and select emerging market debt offer compelling levels of yield. We cannot see the sense in such a significant spread between peripheral and core yields in the eurozone, between euro- denominated bonds supposedly backed by the same central bank. In terms of emerging market debt, we are mindful of genuine risks and potential sensitivity to US interest rate rises. However, our observation is that when something is so widely accepted as the assertion that “emerging market debt sells off when US rates rise”, much of the risk may already be in the price.Expect to be surprisedIt is interesting to look back at the topics that dominated headlines over 2015 and how these changed suddenly from week-to-week or day-to-day. The Ukraine crisis, Grexit, Brexit, Chinese slowdown, US rate rises, European political noise, and so on. This highlights how fickle investors can be in terms of what worries them most from one moment to the next, but also how the things that move markets are often the things that few predicted.Most of these issues are still unresolved, even if they have faded to the background for now. So any one of these topics could flare up again in 2016, or it may be something else entirely. The point is that we should not put too much emphasis on economic forecasting. We believe the most sensible thing to do is expect to be surprised, be mindful of what our fundamentals-based convictions are before volatility takes hold, and be ready to respond to the risks and opportunities presented once it does.M&G December 2015For Investment Professionals and Professional Investors only. Not for onward distribution. No other persons should rely on any information contained within. This information is not an offer or solicitation of an offer for the purchase of shares in any of M&G’s funds. For Switzerland: Distribution of this document in or from Switzerland is not permissible with the exception of the distribution to Qualified Investors according to the Swiss Collective Investment Schemes Act, the Swiss Collective Investment Schemes Ordinance and the respective Circular issuedby the Swiss supervisory authority (“Qualified Investors”). Suppliedfor the use by the initial recipient (provided it is a Qualified Investor) only. This financial promotion is issued by M&G Securities Limited (registered in England 90776) and M&G International Investments Ltd. Both are authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority in the UK and have their registered offices at Laurence Pountney Hill, London EC4R 0HH. M&G International Investments Ltd is registered in England, No. 4134655. It has a branch located in France, 6 rue Lamennais, Paris 75008, registered on the Trade Register of Paris, No. 499 832 400 and a branch in Spain, with corporate domicile at Plaza de Colón 2, Torre II Planta 14, 28046, Madrid, Spain, registered with the Commercial Registry of Madrid under Volume 32.573, sheet 30, page M-586297, inscription 1, CIF W8264591B and registered with the CNMV under the number 79.This financial promotion is further issued by M&G Investments (Hong Kong) Limited. Office: Suite 08, 20/F One International Finance Centre, 1 Harbour View Street, Central, Hong Kong. For Hong Kong only: If you have any questions about this financial promotion please contact M&G Investments (Hong Kong) Limited. For Switzerland, the financial promotion is published byM&G International Investments Switzerland AG, Talstrasse 66, 8001 Zurich, authorised and regulated by the Swiss Federal Financial Market Supervisory Authority. The Portuguese Securities Market Commission (Comissão do Mercado de Valores Mobiliários, the “CMVM”) has received a passporting notification under Directive 2009/65/EC ofthe European Parliament and of the Council and the Commission Regulation (EU) 584/2010 enabling the fund to be distributed to the public in Portugal. M&G International Limited is duly passported into Portugal to provide certain investment services in such jurisdiction on a cross-border basis and is registered for such purposes withthe CMVM and is therefore authorised to conduct the marketing (comercialização) of funds in Portugal. 84204_922087]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[10Economic and market outlook: muted growth and returns expectedPeterWestaway| ChiefEconomist|EuropeforVanguardAssetManagementThe first few months of the year are often filled with speculation about what the restof the year might hold for investors.While an economic and investment outlook is a useful tool, there’s no way to predict market returns with total accuracy. For that reason, Vanguard’s approach to forecasting is a little different: rather than projecting a figure for an asset class’s likely return in 2016, we estimate the probability of a range of return distributions over the next ten years, and our expectations for market returns over the next ten years are the most conservative they’ve been since 2006.When trying to predict the probability of a range of returns, economic context is key. Let’s take a look at each of the main regions.UKThe UK has seen encouraging growth in recent years, with real GDP growing 2.8%, above trend, in 2014 and looks likely to settle around 2.5% in 2015. We can thank strong private domestic demand for this, whichhas been supported by the fall in oil prices, rising employment, low borrowing costs and household disposable income growth. The historical low Bank of England rate of 0.5%, now unchanged for more than six years, has bolstered credit conditions for both firms and households, driving both business investment and the housing market.While we expect growth to stay reasonably strong in 2016, we also anticipate that it will slow down, something we already saw in thelast quarter of 2015, due to the following risk factors and unknowns:• Fiscal austerity is likely to have a negative impact on growth as the government works to turn public sector net borrowing into a surplus by 2019/20.• The impending referendum on Britain’s membership of the European Unionis another unknown: in our view, the economic consequences of Britain leaving the EU would likely be negative for the UK due to the adverse impact it would have on future trade with remaining members.• Although the UK has seen strong employment growth, with unemployment reaching 5.4% at the end of 2015, productivity has failed to rally in the way one would expect. When it recovers, wage growth should prompt the Bank of England to raise interest rates in 2016, but we expect this to be a very gradual process.Euro areaRenewed turmoil in the euro area had a negative effect on growth in 2015, but this was tempered by more quantitative easing from the ECB and falling commodity prices, meaning overall growth was 1.5%, around trend, in 2015. Lower bank lending rates caused bank lending to increase only slightly and struggled to effect any meaningful growth, a significant point given the euro-area’s dependence on bank-based financing. Further QE stimulus is likely to accelerate growth slightly in the next two years, but only towards its previous pre- crisis peak.Fiscal tightening has slowed down, or in the case of some countries, stopped completely, providing an impetus to growth in the last year, but we find the best prospect for growth in the medium to long term in the euro area is likely to be through structural reform. A number of periphery countries, notably Spain, have made]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11good progress in this area. However, progress in other countries, both core and periphery, has been slow.GlobalInvestment outlook: Still conservativeVanguard’s outlook for global equities and bonds remains the most guarded since 2006, given fairly compressed risk premiums and the low-interest-rate environment.We continue to view the global low-rate environment as secular, not cyclical.BondsThe return outlook for fixed income remains positive, yet muted. The expected long-run median return of the broad fixed income market is centred in the 1.5% to 2.5% range. It is important to note that we believe that in most scenarios, investment-grade fixed income provides important diversification benefits in a balanced portfolio. As we said in our 2015 outlook, even in a rising rate environment, duration tilts can be risky given global inflation dynamics and our expectations of monetary policy.Projected global eqity 10-year outlookProjected global eqity 10-year outlookAs we have seen, there are many factors that mean that the investment environment is likely to be challenging and volatile in the coming years. However, Vanguard firmly believes that the principles of portfolio construction should remain unchanged. Investors with appropriate levels of discipline, diversification and patience are likely to be rewarded over the next decade with fair inflation-adjusted returns.Peter Westaway, Chief Economist, Europe, Vanguard Asset ManagementImportant informationThis document is directed at professional investors and should not be distributed to or relied upon by retail investors.This document is designed for use by, and is directed only at persons resident in the UK.The material contained in this document is not to be regarded asan offer to buy or sell or the solicitation of any offer to buy or sell securities in any jurisdiction where such an offer or solicitation is against the law, or to anyone to whom it is unlawful to make such an offer or solicitation, or if the person making the offer or solicitation is not qualified to do so.The information on this document does not constitute legal, tax, or investmentadvice.Youmustnot,therefore,relyonthecontentofthis document when making any investment decisions.The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested.Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results.Any projections should be regarded as hypothetical in nature and do not reflect or guarantee future results.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management Limited.© 2016 Vanguard Asset Management Limited. All rights reserved.Global growth is set to remain frustratingly fragile in 2016 and global trade and manufacturing activities are likely to struggle. Vanguard’s view is that emerging markets are undergoing a persistent slowdown and so we believe that the weakness that has recently been seen in these markets will linger fora while. Indeed, we believe that the gap in GDP growth between emerging markets and developed economies should converge over time, towards a more balanced, unleveraged and healthier equilibrium.While we do not anticipate a Chinese recession in the near term, China’s investment slowdown represents the greatest downside risk, and we expect it to continue in 2016. Manufacturing, housing and financial conditions remain areas of concern and we estimate a high (71%) probability that China’s real GDP growth will fall below 7%.In the developed economies, we see policymakers continuing to struggle to achieve 2% inflation over the medium term. However, as of December 2015, some of the strongest deflationary forces (commodity prices, labour ‘slack’) are beginning to ease their hold, for the firsttimesince2006.Nevertheless,achieving more than 2% core inflation across developed markets could take several years.Our outlook for growth in developed economies, on the other hand, remains modest but steady. At full employment, the US is unlikely to accelerate in 2016, but is expected to reach its long term trend of about 2% a year.EquitiesOur medium-run outlook for global equities remains guarded in the 7% to 9% range. That said, our long-term outlook is not bearish and can even be viewed as constructive when adjusted for the low-rate environment.]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12The trials of Model Portfolio ResearchTahmina Mannan | Market & Industry Content Editor | FE2016 finds FE headquarters busy –with Crown ratings rebalances, FE Alpha ratings and upcoming FE Alpha Manager of the Year Awards. Tahmina Mannan reflects on the world of ratings and research and FE’s strides in the space over the past year.Last year’s FE DFM Survey found that while nearly 70 per cent of our adviser clients had invested client money in a Discretionary or Model Portfolio Service, more than 40 per cent of them admitted to finding it ‘extremely difficult’ or ‘very difficult’ to access quality research and analysis on the value of options available to them.We soon found that the results of the survey echoed an industry wide concern about the lack of transparency around performance, charging and risk mandates for model portfolios. This lack of research available to advisers also meant that they were unable to conduct objective analysis on the suitability of the solutions they were choosing, particularly on an ongoing basis.Concerns like these certainly continue to call for more solutions that will address this lack of transparency, solutions such as FE Transmission which allows advisers access to model portfolio data at a holdings level to conduct objective due-diligence, bespoke comparisons andproduce comprehensive client reporting – allowing for more structured research on their outsourced investment propositions.The rise and rise of multi-asset fundsMulti-asset funds have seen significant interest from advisers and investors alike due to their ‘ready-made’ portfolio like structure, leading to many new solutions being made available in the market place.With the growing popularity of these products in mind, FE saw the need for a Risk Targeted Multi Asset Universe which enables advisers to compare the burgeoning ranks of these types of funds and to assess their returns in relation to the risk taken and to each other..The universe is divided into five risk bands with funds assigned a band according to their FE Risk Scores. These scores measure the historic volatility of an investment instrument against the FTSE 100. The FTSE 100 maintains an FE Risk Score of 100; funds that are less volatilehave a lower score and vice versa, with cash scoring zero.While a fund’s position within a band is not static, to avoid excessive churn between bands, funds must fall outside the risk parametersof their current band for more than 16 weeks before being reassigned.The passives worldOne of last year’s top most bought funds was an index tracker from a well-known passives provider – underlining the increasing dominance of passive funds in the investment market.Although the latter part of 2015 failed to reward those who bought and held an index- tracker, there’s no denying that large numbers of investors sit firmly in the passives side when it comes to the active versus passive investment debate, if for no other reason than cost.Nonetheless, whichever side of the fence an adviser may sit on, they still need to be able to]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[do the correct research to be able to meet the needs of their clients.Thus, we launched the FE Passive fund ratings making it the most extensive rating system of index tracker funds in the retail industry, ranking exchange traded funds and passive funds alongside each other for first time.Unlike other more limited qualitative passive rating services, FE Passive Fund Ratings use quantitative methodology in the ratings process – and therefore removing any level of subjectivity that might pop up.This ensures that advisers can give impartial and independent advice.Guidance on going greenWhilst the asset management industry continues to be plagued by the active vs passive debate, not enough is being said of a small – but growing – part of the investment market, the ethical investment industry.This sector has grown-up a fair bit overthe past few years, its cause furthered bya change in consumer sentiment – fuelled by the financial crisis and a drive to attach responsibility to the way we use our money.This means that more people than ever want to use the power of their money to do good, but there still remains a significant gap in ratings and research firms offering proper guidance on the ethical investment sector.With this gap in mind, the FE Research team assessed more than 200 funds which fall under the ethical/SRI banner in the current market, to draw up a list of high-performing funds which are true to their socially responsible and ethical objectives.The debut list of approved ethical funds now sits within the FE Invest Approved list, in a bid to aid advisers when looking at this growing, yet still relatively niche, investment area.Bricks and mortarSpeaking of firsts, 2015’s investment landscape also highlighted the need to assess property funds (property was the second best-sellingwith net retail sales of £2.7 billion, according to stats from the Investment Association), prompting us to include physical property funds to our FE Approved List – picking the top funds for their ability to generate income.For those of you who remember, until last year we had excluded physical property funds due to the difficulties in rating these funds using a pure quantitative approach.This was also the reason behind our decision back in 2014 to not award crown ratings for physical property funds.However, we have now added funds from M&G, Columbia Threadneedle, F&C and Time Investments to the approved list, using a methodology that shies away from a focus on capital growth.The rationale behind our approach addresses the fact that appraised values of properties can greatly distort the performance and behaviour of property funds, and focussing on income- generation is a far more stable quality to asses these funds.Using FE Analytics to researchActive List Pro on FE AnalyticsModel Portfolio, Multi-Asset Fund, Unit Trust or Investment Trust – no matter what the instrument of choice is – it is added to an ‘Active List’ on Analytics for research and analysis. The Active List Pro now allows for funds from different universes to be added onto the same Active List; giving Advisers the freedom to compare, contrast and review suitability of selections within a single universe/mandate agnostic frame.The Active List Pro is particularly useful whilst balancing diversification and also in portfolio construction.Ability to Forecast Investment ReturnsFE’s Investment Forecaster, available on FE Analytics, helps advisers understand the likely return of proposed portfolios over a number of different time horizons. Based on the assetallocation of each portfolio, the forecaster provides a range of likelihoods of achieving certain targets in the future.The tool comes in particularly handyfor advisers who are providing pension accumulation advice. The chart belowshows likelihood of two portfolios providing consistent income over 26 years with a £2,000 annual withdrawal.Dynamic Portfolio ModellingThe Dynamic Portfolio Tool (DPT) has helped advisers to build, monitor and review self-built, Model and Discretionary portfolios. The historic nature of the tool tracks key switch points within the life of the portfolio – allowing advisers to demonstrate the value of their recommendations.FE Transmission users use the tool to track changes to their discretionary or Model portfolios, giving them the power to judge the active management their investors are paying for.Bespoke Report BuildingThe Custom Portfolio Report Builder (CBRP) tool on FE Analytics allows advisers to create fully customised reports, built specifically to suit the individual needs and objectives of their clients.The tool gives an adviser the freedom toeither create comprehensive reports including portfolio scans or to keep it simple in a standardised template format – which will go a long way to help produce engaging and easy- to-understand tools for communication.Contact detailsT / 020 7534 7661E / Tahmina.Mannan@financialexpress.netFE, 2nd Floor, Golden House,30 Great Pulteney Street, London, W1F 9NN United Kingdomwww.financialexpress.net13]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[14The importance of rebalancing for multi-asset investorsJustin Onuekwusi CFA | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementAfter a fairly quiet end to 2015, market volatility returned with a vengeance in 2016, led by crashing commodities and jitters over the Chinese economy. As with the correction seen over the summer, periods like this require attention from multi-asset investors who wish to maintain the risk profiles of their funds. In this article, I will outline how we manage the risk and opportunities presented by volatile markets...Rebalancing to correct the drift and maintain suitabilityAs expected, large falls in equity valuations as we’ve seen thus far this quarter, can potentially alter the risk profile of a multi-asset fund. Funds that ‘target’ risk, in contrast to those that are simply risk rated, respond very differently to these events.For example, a large fall in equity valuations will result in a fall in the overall percentage allocation of equities in the portfolio. A risk targeted fund considers the long-term risk profile of the underlying assets.When this happens, a risk targeted fund manager will look to correct the drift in portfolio risk. The point of this is to stay within a pre-set risk band and thus maintain client suitability.The diagram to the side illustrates the difference between risk-rated funds and risk- targeted funds. The five funds in our Multi- Index range are risk-targeted to DistributionTechnology and are designed to remain aligned to specific risk ratings. This is shown by the straight blue lines. The dark blue line represents a risk-rated fund, which begins at a risk rating of two and changes as time progresses, rapidly becoming unsuitable for a client whose risk tolerance has remained the same.Although we believe that our fund range can remain relatively stable within the Synaptic ratings, advisers will still need to regularly check that any fund remains suitable for their customers.This is fictional data to display how certain risk profiles can deviate from their risk rating.Combating volatility: the diversification/rebalancing bonusWe believe that asset allocation is thekey to multi-asset fund returns. Academic studies have confirmed that more than90% of an overall portfolio return is drivenby asset allocation. In addition to regular rebalancing to keep a portfolio in line withits target allocations and avoid portfolio drift, rebalancing in times of volatility can help to capture the ‘diversification’ bonus. Back inJune 2015, my colleague in the LGIM Asset Allocation team and I, published an in depth look at investment returns and the key role that diversification can play in offsetting the ‘drag’ of volatility on portfolios, while providing a boost to returns.Reducing volatility through portfolio diversification is well understood by the investment community, but the idea that a diversified portfolio that is regularly rebalanced]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[15Regularly rebalancing a diversified multi-asset portfolio leads to a boost in the expected return of the total portfolio, over and above the weighted average of the returns of the underlying assetsmight support returns is perhaps less known. We showed that regularly rebalancing a diversified multi-asset portfolio leads to a boost in the expected return of the total portfolio,overandabovetheweightedaverage of the returns of the underlying assets. This is what we mean by the ‘diversification bonus’.Consider a simple rebalancing strategy: 60% FTSE 100 Total Return Index and 40% Iboxx UK Corporate Index. In 1998-2013 the weighted average rate of return for the two indiceswas 5.5%, whereas the regularly rebalanced strategy would have delivered a return of 5.8%, resulting in the diversification bonus of 0.3% (Index returns source: Bloomberg. Based on full calendar years).Controlling the costs of rebalancingOne potential drawback of rebalancing, that might diminish or completely eliminate its benefits, is the trading cost involved. Effectively controlling those costs is crucial to successful multi-asset investing and something thatwe have built into every aspect of our funds’ design.We control rebalancing costs in three key ways:1. TakingadvantageofLGIM’sin-house capabilities. We use mainly in-house, index funds as building blocks to implement our asset allocation views. This allows us to rebalance and implement portfolio changes in a cost effective andefficient way by taking advantage of in-house crossing opportunities across the LGIM family of funds.2. Utilisefundflows.Asthefundsare growing we have been able to use fund flows to implement any portfolio change, rather than selling one asset to buy another.3. Allocation ranges.While rebalancing is important, automatically rebalancing every time we are slightly over our targeted allocations can be costly. Therefore our rebalancing process rests on a robustand sophisticated trade discipline to help avoid overtrading.We employ carefully constructed threshold tolerances and triggers to ensure we rebalance at the right time and at the right level to maintain the funds’ risk mandates.Conclusion: rebalancing and diversification are the answer to volatilityMarket volatility highlights the potential that diversification and rebalancing have for helping you help your clients meet their long-term investment goals. Market volatility presentsa number of opportunities – opportunities that don’t have to mean making a big ‘buy’ or ‘sell’ decision. Simply looking after portfolio rebalancing efficiently can help support long- term return.Please note that Synaptic’s ratings are a snapshot and we do not expressly seek to maintain the ratings. Although we believe that our fund range can remain relatively stablewithinthem,youwillstillneedto regularly check that any fund your client may be invested in remains aligned to Synaptic’s ratings over time.Contact detailsFor further information about our Multi Asset FundsT / 0345 070 8684E / enquiries@lgim.co.ukW: lgim.com/multi-indexThis is not a consumer advertisement. It’s intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons.The value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise, and investors may get back less than they invest. Legal& General and Distribution Technology are independent companies. Legal & General uses data and research from Distribution Technology to assist in managing the funds. Legal & General does not use or support Distribution Technology’s investor profiling technology.Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 1009418. Registered office: One Coleman Street, London EC2R 5AA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[16The Real Value of Active ManagersJustin Urqhart-Stewart | Seven Investment ManagementActive vs passive – don’t waste oxygenJust how many conferences have you been to over the years where they set up a ‘key debate’ between active and passive fund managers to see who is going to prove themselves as being better than the other?Frankly I find them really rather tiresome, and it normally ends up with an active manager being harangued for some poor stock choices and higher costs.Yes predictably the discussion ends up around cost which really doesn’t get to the heart of the matter. The truth is of course in the makeup of what is actually inside the funds themselves, be they passive or active, which makes the difference. Thus there are both good and bad active and passive funds.Now I have always been a fan of passivesas they are usually a very low cost and an efficient way to invest in certain markets and sectors, but you would be a fool just to follow the dogma of passives alone as there are also some very effective and successful, even after costs, active managers which we should take into account.In good portfolio construction it is theasset allocation that is usually the main differentiator between success and failure. Certainly having a discipline of both a longerterm strategic asset allocation, overlaid by a more detailed tactical asset allocation, has shown itself to be a very effective means of managing portfolios successfully.Thus it is the decision thereafter as to how best to execute, implement and populate these asset allocation decisions with either passive or active funds. Here certainly the passives have the advantage of being easy to trade and at again relatively low cost, but of course by using the passives they are by their nature just going to be close to replicating those indices and not beating them.However, the lower costs of the passives have been a real driver and you can see now how they have grown in volume (see chart 1) and will shortly probably account for 25% of the fund market. The vast majority though will still be active managers. Here is the nub of the issue – we have to look at the real portfolio structure of these active funds. Upon closer inspection you can start to subset the activemanagers according to their styles. Obviously this will vary over time and according to their own markets and chosen areas. Some will also mercurially disappear or merge quietly into another fund, which is more than likely a sign of fund failure or an inability to successfully market it.Active share of average mutual fundSource: Antti PetahjistoWhat we can do though is separate out those managers who seem to be almost ‘closet trackers’ in that although they are in theory actively managed, they seem to in effect ‘hug’ their index benchmark.Why would they do this? Well primarily to show that they haveShare of mutual fund assets]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[17In good portfolio construction it is the asset allocation that is usually the main differentiator between success and failure.not strayed far from their key measure and thus minimise the risk of failure. Thus if you look at chart 1 above we can divide theminto percentage bands and distinguish ‘closet trackers’ from the true active managers. In numbers it would seem that there are far more of these faux trackers, and relatively few true risk takers.The next question is then – does this make any difference? From the figures in the table below you can see that it is the highly active funds that seem to consistently beat not just the indices, and therefore the passives, but also the ‘closet trackers’ where you are paying higher costs for very marginal performance above the index. So from these figures we can see that active management of portfolios would appear to be worthwhile, but only some are trulyare they really focused on their goals and do they show a history of active management? Secondly you look at their ability for stock selection and timing and to this you add the experience of the manager and their team. Finally of course you would want to know the true costs, most of which should be within the ongoing charge figure (OCF), but here itis the net return that is important. If a truly successful manager has higher charges but has a history of higher returns after costs then so be it – but higher charges for a mere closet hugger is not acceptable to me.Of course active managers will change over time, or their market will. So what is applicable in a bull market may not be in a bear market, and for that you will have to use your own market judgement. However funds are notSource: Premier Asset Management/Morningstarfor fashionable trading on a whim from dayto day. Give the manager some time to prove their worth, but if in the meantime you need to take some shorter term tactical action, then here is the classic moment to use your more easily tradeable passive ETFs. That can give you the flexibility, thus leave the successful activemanagers to prove their out performance and earn for your clients some real returns properly in excess of the index benchmark.So active versus passive is a wasted argument. Both can be successful but equally both can be laggards. So don’t ignore the talents of the true active managers, even though they seem tobe more expensive, and equally cheap passives aren’t just the answer for all your portfolio needs. It’s actives with passives under asset allocation – there lies the answer.Justin Urquhart StewartDon’t ignore the talents of the true active managers, even though they seem to be more expensive, and equally cheap passives aren’t just the answer for all your portfolio needactive. Thus how do you find them?This is another area requiring some expertise and analysis. Merely judging by some ‘star’ guide of past performance is of little benefit or use here. Firstly you look for the style and conviction of the manager and their team -]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[18New State Pension - winner or loser?Fiona Tait | Pension Specialist | Royal LondonThe new State Pension (nSP) will be implemented at a maximum flat rate of £155.65 per week in 2016/7. This is good news for some, not so good for others.Women and the SNPI am a woman1 however this does not really affect my State Pension, largely because I have been continually employed since I left university and because I still have a few (we will gloss over exactly how many) years before I reach State Pension age (SPa).If I were 10 years older I might feel differently. Although the new state pension is probably better for me because the years when I was bringing up children are properly valued, Iwill also have to wait several years longer to get a pension at all than I expected when I started work. The SPa is rising for everyone but if I had been born between 1953 and 1955 the increase would have been the steepest, and I might not have realised in time to do something about it.Also, I might be relying on getting a widows pension when my husband, as is statistically likely, pre-deceases me. If he dies or reaches hisSPa before 6 April I will be covered; if however he is too young or too healthy I won’t. Thisis because from April my State Pension entitlement will depend on my own National Insurance (NI) record, not his. Women in this situation would be strongly advised to reassess their life cover in light of the changes.The one thing I would not have to worry about, if I were close to SPa, is having paid the married woman’s stamp. My right to a Basic State Pension (BSP) based on my husband’s NIrecord is protected until 6 April. I’m also not going to complain that I won’t get the nSP if my SPa is 63 instead of 65, I will after all be getting my pension for longer.On the plus side, previous credits would only have applied to the BSP element ofthe State Pension, not SERPS. As the nSP isa single tier system any credit will apply to the full amount, which should be particularly beneficial for women who are more likely to be in a caring role.On the plus side, previous credits would only have applied to the BSP element of the State Pension, not SERPS.]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[19Although the new state pension is probably better for me because the years when I was bringing up children are properly valued, I will also have to wait several years longer to get a pension at all than I expected when I started workContracted Out benefitsI have also been contracted out of SERPS and the S2P for most of my career which will reduce my entitlement to the nSP. However, far from losing out because of this I am likely to do well under the new system.It is true that I will not have accrued NI credits for those years and will therefore miss out on the nSP that I would have earned over this period. I do however have a number of years under the new system to make up some of these credits, and I will get my rebate pension and GMP on top of this, even if I eventually qualify for the maximum nSP.Deferring the nSPI could also benefit further by deferringmy State Pension at SPa. Assuming I’m in reasonable health, with at least average life expectancy it is a very good deal, even under the post April rates2. If I survive over 14 years my nSP will have paid out enough to offset a year’s delay in nSP and it will be indexed for the rest of my life.Higher EarnersIn the long run I would almost certainly get a higher State Pension under an earnings-relatedrather than flat rate scheme, but that ship has rightly sailed and there are compensations. The flat rate means it will be much easier for me to understand and to estimate the amount of pension I will eventually get.Granted, the transitional arrangements for contracted out years and pre April state benefits require a greater level of mathematical skill than I possess, but this is a function of the existing system, not the new one. From next year, the DWP tells us, everyone will be able to access an on-line statement of their projected nSP benefits, together with confirmation of their NI record to date.ConclusionThe nSP will be fairer and more transparent in the long run. The main losers are people who relied on the State Pension age remaining the same, rather than those receiving/not receivingthe nSP. Given current demographic changes this was always going to happen, but had action been taken much earlier the transitional period could have been less painful.The Royal London report ‘Pensions through the ages’ found that as many as 40% of 35 year olds did not believe the State Pension would even exist by the time they came to retire. I am not in this group, either by age or inclination, however I am equally not going to pin all my retirement hopes on the system remaining the same. People who can should save for themselves.Notes1. The more discerning readers will already have spotted this.2. The deferral rate for individual with a sPA before 5 April 2016 is 10.4% for each year of deferral. From 6 April the deferral rate will drop to 5.8%The main losers are people who relied on the State Pension age remaining the same, rather than those receiving/not receiving the nSP.]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[20Time Diversification Vs Rebalancing In Retirement PortfoliosAbraham Okusanya | Principal | FinalytiQMost of today’s portfolio management theories and practices are primarily designed to optimise return and manage risk during the accumulation stage of investing. However, there is an increasing acknowledgement of that investing for income in retirement is markedly different than investing in the accumulation stage.take withdrawal from a retirement portfolio, common sense suggests that the rebalancing ensures that much the withdrawal are taken from the best performing asset classes, giving the asset classes that have fallen some that to recover.Right?But what if we don’t rebalance the portfolio at all? What if we simply make withdrawal from the asset classes that have fallen the most and avoid rebalancing the portfolio? Or better still, what if we liquidate assets within the portfolio based on their relative expected return and again, avoid rebalancing altogether? In other words, since bonds have lower expected return than equities, what if we liquidate the bonds first to pay income, giving the equity allocation more time to grow? Put another way, what if you eat your bonds first, equities later?Time DiversificationIn a retirement portfolio, ‘eating bonds first and equity later‘ introduces the conceptof time-diversification; the idea that thelonger you hold equities for, the higher the chances outperforming bonds. According to Barclays Equity Gilt Study, since 1899, equity outperformed bonds 73% over any 5 years period, 79% of times over any 10 year period and 88% of times over any 18 years period. The point is, the longer you hold equities, the probability of experience bad outcome reduces.This is particularly due to how withdrawals amplify sequence risk in retirement portfolios. Client’s objective in retirement changes drastically from simply maximising long term return to supporting monthly/ annual income, for what is finite but precisely unknown period of time.Yet, in many cases, we continue to usethese portfolio management practices (e.g Efficient Frontier etc) to manage portfolios in retirement, when in actual fact they weren’t necessarily designed for that purpose since they don’t take account of impactof withdrawals and the need for portfolio longevity.The Received Wisdom of RebalancingRebalancing is one of such practices; whilethere remain some questions over whether ‘Rebalancing Bonus’ actually exists (sinceit depends on the correlation betweenthe expected return of asset classes in the portfolio), there is a general acknowledgement that rebalancing helps optimise risk-adjusted return and deliver a more consistent investment experience.And when it comes to managing a retirement portfolio, common sense suggests that rebalancing – selling assets that have performed well and buying more assets that underperformed – shouldn’t do much harm to the portfolio because it helps avoid or reduce unfavourable liquidation of asset that have fallen the most. Periodic rebalancing ensures that asset that are up the most are sold, while buying the ones that are down the most! When combined with the need to]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[21Accordingly, when thinking about spending retirement portfolio, does it makes any sense to diversify across time by spending bonds first (which is less risky in the short term but with lower long term expected return), giving the equity allocation more time to grow?And does rebalancing (which effectively trounce this benefit of time diversification) actually reduces portfolio longevity, thereby resulting in poorer outcome in a retirement portfolio?This a question that John Spitzer and Sandeep Singh tried to answer in their paper titled Is Rebalancing a Portfolio During Retirement Necessary? which was published in the Journal of Financial Planning. The modelled the following 5 liquidation strategies, across different asset allocation (30%, 40%, 50%, 60%, 70%, 80% equity) and inflation adjusted withdrawal rate (3%, 4%, 5%, 6% and 7%) assuming a retirement period of 30 years;1. Withdrawmoneyfromeitherstocksor bonds and then rebalance the portfolio annually to the initial stock/bond proportion. This harvesting rule will be referred to as “Rebalance.”2. Withdrawmoneyfromtheassetthathad the highest return during the year and do not rebalance. This will be referred to as “High First.”3. Withdrawmoneyfromtheassetthathad the lowest return during the year and do not rebalance. This will be referred to as “Low First.”To the extent that historical rates of return on bonds tend to be lower than historical rates of return on stocks,the following two additional methods of harvesting withdrawals will be referred to as “Bonds First” and “Stocks First.”4. Takewithdrawalsfrombondsfirstanddo not rebalance.5. Take withdrawals from stocks first and do not rebalance.Spitzer and Singh modelled these strategies using both historical market data between 1926 and 2003 (which included 49 overlapping 30-year retirement periods for example, 1926–1955, 1927, 1956...1974–2003 as well bootstrap simulations.The Result!The result of the of the historical simulations presented below, shows that time- diversification does have a remarkably positive effect on portfolio longevity (but only if you spend bond allocation first) compared toa rebalancing strategy. In virtually all the scenarios, it pays to eat your bonds first, equities later.Percentage of Times Under Temporal Order Portfolio Was Exhausted Befor 30 yearsThe CaveatOf course, this is not to say rebalancing a retirement portfolio in itself in bad; onlythat it’s likely to produce sub-optimal outcomes when compared to an effective time-diversification strategy. The caveat is that, adopting time-diversified withdrawal will invariable increase the equity allocation within the portfolio. As you spend down the bond allocation,you end up with more and more equity, as a percentage of the overall portfolio. This in turn increases the volatility within their portfolio, which the client may find uncomfortable. This also goes back to the conversation about how we measure risk, particularly in retirement; is volatility the real risk or is it running out of money?In addition to all this, we have to take account of the regulatory environment that we operate in, FOS is unlikely to look kindly on a 60% equity portolio that ended up being 90% equity portfolio 10 years later. I was horrified (yet again) few days ago when FOS uphelda complaint against an adviser in spite of the client suffering no financial loss whatsoever, because they had too much equity allocation!This constant battle between empirical evidence, client’s behavioural biases, established industry norms and incompetent/ overzealous regulatory bodies makes a planner’s job more difficult. Yet, I recently had a discussion with a planner who told me they view their job primarily as a behavioural coach to clients; and will specifically encourage, educate and seek informed consent from clients to take more equity risk than their ‘risktolerance’ might suggest, provided the client has the capacity and/or requirement to take such risk. This is no path for the fainthearted!For instance, using 60/40 equity/bond allocation and withdrawal rate of 5% (of the initial portfolio, adjusted for inflation) over30 years, time-diversification improved the failure rate from a whooping 35% to 18%! In other words, time diversification improved the probability of success from 65% to 82!]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[22Synaptic’s Robo perspectiveEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedAn update on the discussion around Robo...The government recognises the abyss that the UK consumer is facing in terms of the advice and savings gap. The fact that government raids on pension savings and failed regulatory initiatives are a large part of the problem offers further incentive for a fresh approach. In a nutshell the government feels that itcan address two key policy objectives at the same time – stimulate the economy with the development of ‘FinTech’, a sure fire future job creation and earnings success, whilst FinTech initiatives provide online solutions to help close the savings gap. Lots of commentary is being generated by consultants and thought leaders who are trying to establish their expertise in what is still very much a theoretical construct.A year old project called Project Innovatehas seen the FCA arrange special oversightfor over 150 tech based propositions to be cultivated, exploring areas of on-line financial services that do not fit the traditional regulatory mould. This is being extended to the creation of a ‘sand pit’ – actively promoting experimentation around new initiatives, where participants can expect a ‘regulation light touch’ to help explore the bleeding edge.In parallel to Project Innovate, the Treasury and the FCA are also conducting the FAMR, or ‘Financial Advice Market Review’. This will provide the framework for the development of policies, with a focus on reducing ‘financial exclusion’ and engaging with consumers.We think that the real significance of this initiative, in addition to the obvious growing encouragement for new technological solutions, is what it means for the distribution giants who are temporarily sitting in the sidelines. They are waiting to see the extent of any new freedoms that they will enjoy before re-entering the advice space. Having left with tails between legs following series of censures from the authorities and crowded out by RDR restrictions on commissions and other constraints to their profitability, Banks and Building Societies are licking their lips at the prospect of coming back into what they perceive may be a more profitable arenawith supportive regulation, and the ability to develop more automated processes for advice, which wouldn’t have been allowed previously.Inevitably, discussion returns to the pioneers in this space whether they be Americanor UK based. Betterment is an exampleof the former, Nutmeg is an example ofthe latter. On reflection it is clear that the only executions that exist are very narrow executions in terms of functionality. The ability to risk profile on line and divert fundsThe full Robo experience, driven by artificial intelligence and future generation net native technology will certainly take longer to come to fruition than driverless cars, or the ability to bond emotionally with Siri.]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[23About you Income Your Options Making a decisionYour retirement age: 68 Your projected pension pot:£80,000Your options for turning your pension into retirement incomeSearch the best providersYour life expectancy:89£20,000 £2,800A guaranteed income for life1 You can choose to buy a single life annuity which will pay you a guaranteed regular income until you die. (This is called a single life annuity)Your cash free lump sum could be:Your monthly income could be:(25%) per yearIs this right for you?until you dieExplore this option in more detailA guaranteed income for life for you 2 and your spouse or partner.You can choose to buy a joint life annuity which will pay a guaranteed regular income until both you and your partner die. (This is called a joint life annuity)Your cash free lump sum could be:Your monthly income could be:£20,000 (25%)£2,600 per yearuntil you die£1,500 per yearuntil your partner diesIs this right for me?xxxxxxxx Explore this option in more detailA guaranteed income for a fixed 3 number of years.You can choose to buy an annuity which will pay you a guaranteed regular income for a set number of years. (This is called a fixed term annuity)Your cash free lump sum could be:Your monthly income could be:(25%)£20,000 Is this right for me?£4,300 per yearuntil your 73Explore this option in more detailYou can choose to withdraw all your 4 pension as cash.You would receive 25% tax free but the rest would be taxed as income.(You could reduce the amount of tax you pay by withdrawing your money over a number of tax years.)Your cash free lump sum could be:Your taxable income would be:£20,000 (25%) £60,000Is this right for me?Explore this option in more detailDraw regular income from your5 pension pot as and when you want toYou can choose to leave your pension invested and withdrawal as much or a little cash as you like whenever it suits you. (This is called a Drawdown)Your cash free lump sum could be:Your monthly income could be*:£20,000 (25%) Is this right for me?£3,000 per year*however, for your pension pot to last your life expectancyyour average monthly withdraw should not exceed £300Explore this option in more detailAbout you Income Your options Making a decisionHow is your retirement shaping up?What other sources of income do you have?Let's look at how much this adds up to every year£11,550 per yearNow what about your pension income?ContinueSearch the best providersYour retirement age 68 Your estimated life expectancy 89 Add more detail Your current pension pot £60,000 Your projected pension pot £80,000Savings/Investments/ISAsOther monthly incomee.g property, employment, other pensions£20,000Howmuchofthisdoyou 0%       100% want to use as income?£300 per month Until I'm 89Add more detail£950 per year Other income   £3,600 per yearuntil your 89 *to ensure that your savings last you should not withdraw more than £80 every monthuntil your 89 until you dieSavings/Investments/ISAs*State pension£7,000 per yearinto a suitable portfolio are scratching the surface in terms of the where this is going. For the foreseeable future, no one really believes that Robos will be able to operate effectively in the UK without human element. Which means that what we are really talking about are online processes capable of improving services to the self-service brigade, and systems capable of guidance for the squeezed middle. The full Robo experience, driven by artificial intelligence and future generation net native technology will certainly take longer to come to fruition than driverless cars, or the ability to bond emotionally with Siri.However, our parent group happens to be one of the largest service and technology based groups in the UK, and within its many assets, has all of the key elements to draw on to push the development of digitally delivered financial services. Areas of expertise in house include automated decision tree software, artificially intelligent telephone service provision,gamification (important for engagement), user journey development, access to big data infrastructure, investment risk management, custody platforms, links to providers and a wide range of distribution partners eager to ensure they will continue to access clients, however they wish to serviced. Our hopeis that it will be traditional advisory firms that pick up the mantle of more automated processes within their advice propositions. Synaptic have a leadership role in the group’s plans, and look forward to helping shape any software based solutions.One advantage that Synaptic has is ownership of the ‘Robo Protector’ Webline, the portal whose infrastructure supports the quotes and on-line applications for a large proportionof the Protection sales in the UK, including leading lights such as Reassured, Money Supermarket and Cavendish Online. Because Protection does not require the regulatory rigour of investment, Protection sales aretherefore not technically ‘Robo’ by the Treasury / FCA definition. By any other measure Webline’s market leadership and commercial presence makes it an outstanding Fintech success story.A further step into the greater automationof advice functionality has been taken by Synaptic, and we now have a ‘wire frame’ prototype for an online at retirement Robo solution, equivalent to one or two notable incumbents. We intend to use this as first base towards our vision of a more holistic approach to automated advice, where website or advisers can broaden out their exposure in this area.The Synaptic ‘at Retirement’ Prototype(see screenshot above) will model a customer’s retirement income, taking into account the various options that exist in the mix, including guaranteed (annuity purchase), investment and other income.]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24Proof of suitability is easy with SynapticEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedThe depth of suitability reporting within the Synaptic Research suiteOne of the interesting perspectives gained at Synaptic comes from insights into different firms’ compliance approaches. Given the reliance on Synaptic by over six thousand firms, we have a significant observation pool. We seek to understand how firms are working by looking at some of the M.I. that is generated by our online tools, for example the patterns of due diligence around platform selectionor portfolio investment strategy, but also by working closely with firms who sensibly seek to get the best out of the software that they have invested in and request assistance from us on how to achieve their objectives and build their processes.We were delighted last month to hear that one of our main customer groups with over 500 advisers had been congratulated by the regulator following a recent assessment.This was done in the context of the recent thematic review around suitability in wealth management – where up to a third of the firms assessed will require enforcement, and the majority could not demonstrate a reasonable level of knowledge of customer and suitability of recommendations made.The congratulations in question was for robust compliance processes impacting favourably on client outcomes, and a key factor inthe achievement alongside the skill and intelligence of this organisation’s practitioners was the entrenched and consistent use of thetools in the Synaptic Compliance suite.Adviser software breaks into two broad areas; firstly back office and secondly research. Having good back office functionality, particularly in the client management, commissions and management info areasis essential, but a back office should not determine the research capabilities of your business. Good research tools such as Synaptic can easily be integrated with back offices, and regularly are. Similarly, many firms are being lured by siren call of platforms purportingto be back offices, and further negating the need for independent assessment of their recommendations. If a firm becomes entirely dependent on their platform provider, there is a risk that they are compromising their independence.Our industry’s concept of independencewas forged out of the need to pry control away from the hands of Providers whose tied sales were seen as detrimental to consumer outcomes. In spite of everything that has gone under the bridge since that time, the concept of searching the whole of market in order to compare products and ensure ‘suitability’ has been upheld, and more than anything defines the independent practitioner. The ability to establish and prove suitability is the hallmark of professionalism and the core skill of an independent, protecting them from teams of salespersons, robos or other lunch grabbers.So what have we learnt? A lot of firms could make their lives much easier by rethinking their basic compliance processes, and useof research tools. It seems that some of the most vocal critics of the perceived excess in compliance requirements, those who feel that they need to fire off 150 page suitability reports to clients, are falling short of:- knowing their client- establishing suitability through appropriateresearch taking in whole of market view,cost and risk- evidencing recommendation audit trail.In the words of Rory Percival: ‘Let the adviser fill in a personalised report based on the client. My suggestion is - don’t have any template objectives in suitability reports. That is thebest defence against us (i.e. the FCA), the Financial Ombudsman Service and complaints. Where you’ve shown it’s more suitable forthat individual client you’re going to have a better defence.’ This has been a developing theme for some time now. Interestingly Rory Percival added that he doesn’t recognise the complaints of advisers who claim inconsistency between the FCA and FOS, dismissing it asa myth. ‘If you’ve got a reference number ofa case that goes against what we are saying, or against our approach, let me know. I keep saying this and I still haven’t seen a single one yet. No one has sent me any evidence.’]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[25If a firm becomes entirely dependent on their platform provider, there is a risk that they are compromising their independenceThe suitability tick list(Thanks to Rory Percival, Mel Holman (Compliance and Training Solutions) and IFP). 1. Thewholefilea. Remove information contained in the file from the Suitability report – so it shorter and more client-friendly. The story does not need to be replicated from the file into the report.2. Knowyourclienta. Must be up to dateb. Doesn’t need to be in fact find format(eg could be a mind map) 3. Quantifyclientobjectives4. AttitudetoRiskversusCapacityforLossa. In simple terms ATR is emotional and CFLis factual – linked to client’s knowledge and experience5. SuitabilityReports–thethreemusthaves:a. The client’s demands (needs andobjectives)b. Why the recommendation is suitablefor that clientc. Any disadvantages and risks to theclient that are associated with the recommended solutionFinal advice – ‘Don’t include anything irrelevant to the client’.The following table offers an overview of Suitability reporting from the Synaptic suiteProductSynaptic Product and FundSynaptic ComparatorSynaptic ModellerArea of suitability:Proof of product suitability based on client requirementsProof of suitability of cost and chargesSuitability around Risk• Filters and ranks selections• Identifies suitable productrecommendation• Full audit trial• Company, fund and product factsheets available• Calculate s ‘Total Solution Cost’ / R.I.Y.• Switching suitability proof with editable assumed growth rates• Allows alignment with Providerillustrations• Regularly performs millions ofcalculations in a single piece of research, identifying appropriate share class• Built in ATRQ and investment strategy from Moody’s, but fully configurable• Provides a stochastically derived, probability based view of investment outcomes• Identifies likelihood and extent of portfolio losses to enable informed discussion around riskFor more information regarding the Synaptic Suite call us on 0800 783 4477 or visit www.synaptic.co.uk.]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26Own suitability and risk before suitability and risk own youEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedThere is a surge of new information detailing the shortcomings of firms’ approaches to establishing suitability of recommended investments around risk. There cannot be a more important issue to resolve, as failure is more likely than ever to attract censure from the regulator, but more importantly without credible control of risk, client detriment will derive from too little or too much.In some ways consideration of risk is the most exciting part of the jigsaw when putting together an investment strategy. Every other element in the mix depends on getting that approach right.Research around risk must operate on a client by client basis beyond the examination of historical draw down and volatility measures. The fact is that many advisory firms are still reliant on ‘qualitative’ overlays of opinion to statistics based on past experience.Without an all-encompassing risk framework that defines both clients and investment recommendations, firms will not be able to evidence suitability. The FCA recently detailed some of its findings in the most damning thematic review to date. The review examined DFM business, highlighting the dangers ofineffective outsourcing by advisers. In TR 15/12 of December 2015, the key issues identified were‘an inability to demonstrate suitability, for example.. inadequate risk profiling , or failure to record customers’ financial position and.. a risk of unsuitability due to inconsistencies between portfolios and the customer’s attitude to risk, investment objectives and/or investment horizon.’Unless an adviser has handed off the client entirely (which evidence suggests is only the minority of cases) any liability will remain squarely with the adviser. According to Harrison Spence (FT Adviser Jan 15), a survey of 150 firms showed that as much as 43%use a discretionary adviser to meet some of their clients’ needs. Mr Spence also pointedto the FCA’s research from 2011 which found that 79% of wealth managers files were not appropriate, largely in respect of risk. We know from previous reviews that adviser firms struggle to the same extent with the effective use of tools and research.The recent thematic review will require enforcement measures in a third of the firms examined. There is little room for complacency with this issue.What to do?Because we cannot know the future, the only realistic approach is to mathematically model all the possible outcomes of an investmentThe only realistic approach is to mathematically model all the possible outcomes of an investment strategy, including the full range of interest rate and inflation possibilities]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[27In some ways consideration of risk is the most exciting part of the jigsaw when putting together an investment strategy. Every other element in the mix depends on getting that approach right.Royal London Governed Portfolio 2KeyTactical (OUTER) %Cash 1.5 UK Corporate Bonds 11.3 UK Govt Bonds 16.5 UK Equities 28.1 Global Equities (ex UK) 23.0 Emerging Markets Equities 0.0 Global Property 13.5 Global Private Equity 0.0 Hedge Funds 0.0 Commodities 0.0 European Fixed Income 0.0 US Fixed Income 0.0 Global Bonds (ex UK) 6.3Max gain Ave gain Min gain23.46% 5.16% -13.02%Balancedstrategy, including the full range of interest rate and inflation possibilities. This is the only way that the required conversation aroundrisk dynamics can take place as the two key quotients can be addressed: how likely are losses, and equally importantly, what extent are these likely losses to be. If the adviser can assess the likelihood of losing 10 or 20% of a portfolio in any one year of a ten year term, the client can quickly start to understand their own prospects. How else do we address the thorny topics of impact of a bad sequence of returns or how volatility drag can affect savings / decumulation plans?To build this functionality in the Synaptic research suite, we needed to partner with a firm who addressed all of the complexitiesof the risk and suitability challenge. We felt the only solution available, which happens to be the industry leader and most widely used by insurance companies and other financial institutions is the Moody’s Analytics (formerly Barrie + Hibbert) stochastic model, which builds a probability based distribution of outcomes, facilitating the risk conversation with clients and providing the necessary documentation for compliance purposes. Qualitative objectivity is gained by the factthat the results are mathematically derived using Monte Carlo simulation and a level of reliability can be ascribed to the model by examining the accuracy of previous projections.The key to escaping the compliance quagmire and providing best advice is having an investment strategy fully aligned and constantly reviewed, including ATRQ, risk categories and rated investment recommendations. That almost certainly cannot be you if you need time to take care of your clients. The qualitative overlay then becomes the icing on the cake rather than evidence of an objective suitability gap.Article first appeared in the Financial Planner Magazine, 2016.The key to escaping the compliance quagmire and providing best advice is having an investment strategy fully aligned and constantly reviewed]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[After 21 years we still hold the key to complianceSYNAPTIC PRODUCT & FUND SOFTWARE• Providing independent and objective whole of market research. • Helping advisers navigate the challenges of compliance.• The cornerstone of compliance advice in the UK.• Integrates fully with the entire Synaptic Research Suite.For more information call us on 0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Cautious MPS 1 2 CF Canlife Portfolio III 1 2Income MPS 1 2 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 1 2Balanced MPS 1 2 CF Canlife Portfolio V 1 2Growth MPS 1 2 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 1 2Global Equity MPS 1 2 CF Canlife Portfolio VII 1 2Canlife Portfolio 3 1 2Canlife Portfolio 4 1 2Canlife Portfolio 5 1 2CF Canlife Portfolio III 1 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 1 CF Canlife Portfolio V 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VII 1 Canlife Portfolio 34C a u t i o5 u s M P S 4Incom5e MPS4B a l a n 5c e d M P S 4Grow5th MPS 4Globa5l Equity MPS 4 54 54 54 54 5Close Managed Diversified Income F Close Managed Conservative FundCanlife Portfolio 6 1 2 Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund 1 2Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund Close Diversified Income Portfolio F Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Balanced Portfolio Fund Close Growth Portfolio FundCanlife Portfolio 7 1 2 Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund 1 2Close Conservative Portfolio Fund 1 2Close Balanced Portfolio Fund 1 2Close Growth Portfolio Fund 1 2Close Managed Diversified Income Fund 1 2Close Managed Conservative Fund 1 2 F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation 1 2Foundation Defensive Fund Cautious Fund Balanced Fund Growth FundClose Managed Balanced Fund 1 2 F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund 1 2Close Managed Balanced FundClose Managed Growth Fund 1 2 F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund 1 2Close Managed Growth FundClose Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund 1 2 F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund 1 2Close Tactical Select Passive ConservaClose Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund 1 2 F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund 1 2Close Tactical Select Passive BalancClose Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund 1 2 F&C MM Navigator Distribution 1 2Close Tactical Select Passive GrowthClose DMS Diversified Income 1 2 F&C MM Navigator Moderate 1 2Close DMS Diversified IncomeClose DMS Conservative 1 2 F&C MM Navigator Progressive 1 2Close DMS ConservativeClose DMS Balanced 1 2Close DMS BalancedF&C MM Navigator Select 1 Close DMS Growth 1F&C MM Navigator Boutiques 1 Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) 123 43 43 4F&C MM Navigator Boutiques Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling)Close DMS GrowthCautious Moderately Cautious Balanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurous Cautious3 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 43 42 3 4555555555555555555555555555555555555555555Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 72 32 32 32 32 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 32212345Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis: Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation Synaptic Risk Rating based o trategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset AllocationF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM LifestyleF&C MM Navigator Distribution F&C MM Navigator Moderate F&C MM Navigator Progressive F&C MM Navigator Select12345123451234512345123451234512345123451234512345]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 51 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5R4isk Le5vel 1 Short R4isk Le5vel 2 Short R4isk Le5vel 3 Short R4isk Le5vel 4 Short R4isk Le5vel 5 ShortR 4 i s k L e 5v e l 1 M e d i u m R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 2 M e d i u m R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 3 M e d i u m R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 4 M e d i u m R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 5 M e d i u m R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 1 L o n gR 4 i s k L e 5v e l 2 L o n g R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 3 L o n g R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 4 L o n g R 4 i s k L e 5v e l 5 L o n g I n4 c o m e5Multi Asset AdventurousMulti Asset Allocator AdventurousMulti Asset Allocator DefensiveMulti Asset Allocator GrowthMulti Asset Allocator StrategicMulti Asset Allocator WorldMulti Asset Balanced IncomeMulti Asset DefensiveMulti Asset GrowthMulti Asset IncomeMulti Asset Income & GrowthMulti Asset Open AdventurousMulti Asset Open DefensiveMulti Asset Open GrowthMulti Asset Open StrategicMulti Asset StrategicOpen World 12345 Wealth Builder12345Diversified Income Fund12345Diversified Growth Fund12345MAP 12345 12345Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7Managed Growth Fund12345Investec Cautious Managed Fund12345123451234512345123451234512345123451 2 31 2 34 54 5Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk1234512345Questionnaire by visiting risk.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[M&G Episode Allocation FundCF Canlife Portfolio III M&G Episode Income FundCF Canlife Portfolio IV M&G Episode Growth FundCF Canlife Portfolio V M&G Optimal Income FundCF Canlife Portfolio VI M&G Global Dividend FundCF Canlife Portfolio VIIM&G Global Emerging Markets FundCanlife Portfolio 3 M&G Recovery FundCanlife Portfolio 4M&G Strategic Corporate Bond FundCanlife Portfolio 5 M&G Property PortfolioCanlife Portfolio 6M&G Global Macro Bond FundCanlife Portfolio 7M&G Corporate Bond FundPremier Cash PortfolioF&C MM Lifestyle FoundationPremier Cash Plus PortfolioF&C MM Lifestyle Defensive FundPremier Capital Builder Portfolio F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious FundPremier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced FundPremier Income and Growth Portfolio F&C MM Lifestyle Growth FundPremier Income PortfolioF&C MM Navigator DistributionPremier Conservative Portfolio F&C MM Navigator ModeratePremier High Income Portfolio F&C MM Navigator ProgressivePremier Balanced Portfolio F&C MM Navigator SelectPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio F&C MM Navigator BoutiquesPremier Growth PortfolioPyrford Global Total Return (Sterling)Premier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio1111111111111111111111111111111111111111111112222222222222222222222222222222222222222222223333333333333333333333333333333333333333333334444444444444444444444444444444444444444444445 MP3 1 52 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 34 C a u t i 5o u s M P S4I n c o m5 e M P S 4Balan5ced MPS 4Grow5th MPS 4Globa5l Equity MPS 45Close Bond Income Portfolio FundCautiousBalanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousBalancedModerately AdventurousAdventurousCautiousModerately Cautious5 MP50 1 55 MP4 1 55 MP5 1 55 MP6 1 55 MP7 1 5555555555FundsPortfoliosPremier UK Money Market Fund 1 Premier Defensive Growth Fund 1 Premier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund 1Close Diversified Income Portfolio F45Close Conservative Portfolio Fund45Close Balanced Portfolio Fund45Close Growth Portfolio Fund45Close Managed Diversified Income F45Close Managed Conservative Fund45Close Managed Balanced Fund45Close Managed Growth Fund45Close Tactical Select Passive Conserva45Close Tactical Select Passive Balanc45Close Tactical Select Passive Growth45Close DMS Diversified Income45Close DMS Conservative45Close DMS Balanced45Close DMS Growth5 Premier Liberation IV Fund 1 55 Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund 1 55 Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund 1 55 Premier Liberation V Fund 1 55 Premier Diversified Fund 1 55 Premier Liberation VI Fund 1 55 Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund 1 55 Premier Liberation VII Fund 1 55 Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund 1 5555555Synaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis: Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation Synaptic Risk Rating based o trategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 3P4ruFun5d CautiousP4ruFun5d Protected Cautious P4ruFun5d GrowthP4ruFun5d Protected Growth P4ruFun5d 0-30P4ruFun5d 10-40P4ruFun5d 20-55P4ruFun5d 40-80D4ynam5ic 0-30D4ynam5ic 10-40D4ynam5ic 20-55D4ynam5ic 40-80D4ynam5ic 60-100W4 P Op5timum ReturnF 4o c u s e 5d 0 - 3 0F 4o c u s e 5d 1 0 - 4 0F 4o c u s e 5d 2 0 - 5 5Focused 40-80Focused 60-1004545RMAP Total Return45RMAP Strategic Growth45RMAP Enhanced Growth45RMAP Strategic Income45Strategy 145Strategy 245Strategy 345Strategy 41111111111111111111111111111122222222222222222222222222222333333333333333333333333333334444444444444444455555555555555555MPS Global Growth MPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global Income MPS IncomeMPS ConservativeMPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 512345Strategy 512345Strategy 61234512345123454 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5RL Governed Portfolio 1 (l)RL Governed Portfolio 2RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s)RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l)RL Governed Portfolio 5RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s)RL Governed Portfolio 7 (l)RL Governed Portfolio 8RL Governed Portfolio 9 (s)RL GRIP 1 12345 RL GRIP 2 12345 RL GRIP 3 12345 RL GRIP 4 12345 RL GRIP 5 123451 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Conservative Portfolio 1 2 3 4 CF Canlife Portfolio III 1 2 3 4Defensive Portfolio 1 2 3 4 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 1 2 3 4Moderate Portfolio 1 2 3 4 CF Canlife Portfolio V 1 2 3 4Progressive Portfolio 1 2 3 4 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 1 2 3 4Positive Portfolio 1 2 3 4 CF Canlife Portfolio VII 1 2 3 4Positive Plus Portfolio 1 2 3 4 Canlife Portfolio 3 1 2 3 4Adventurous Portfolio 1 2 3 4 Canlife Portfolio 4 1 2 3 4Adventurous Plus Portfolio 1 2 3 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 1 2 3 4Canlife Portfolio 6 1 2 3 4 Canlife Portfolio 7 1 2 3 4Vanguard LifeStrategy 20% 1 2 3 4Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% 1 2 3 4Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% 1 2 3 4Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation 1 2 3 4Vanguard LifeStrategy 100% 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund 1 2 3 4F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Navigator Distribution 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Navigator Moderate 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Navigator Progressive 1 2 3 4 F&C MM Navigator Select 1 2 3 455555555555555555555555555SantanderSantander Atlas 3 Santander Atlas 4 Santander Atlas 5 Santander Atlas 6 Santander Atlas 7 Santander Atlas IncomeSchroder MM DiversitySchroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK GrowthSchroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 C a u t i 5o u s M P S4I n c o m5 e M P S 4Balan5ced MPS 4Grow5th MPS 4Globa5l Equity MPS 45Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund 4Close5Diversified Income Portfolio F 4Close5Conservative Portfolio Fund 4Close5Balanced Portfolio Fund 4Close5Growth Portfolio Fund 4Close5Managed Diversified Income F 4Close5Managed Conservative Fund 4Close5Managed Balanced Fund 4Close5Managed Growth Fund4 C l o s e 5T a c t i c a l S e l e c t P a s s i v e C o n s e r v a 4Close5Tactical Select Passive BalancClose Tactical Select Passive Growth Close DMS Diversified IncomeClose DMS ConservativeClose DMS BalancedClose DMS Growth555555F&C MM Navigator Boutiques 1 2 3 4(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Scottish Life directly for further information before recommending.5Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) 1 2 3 4 5About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to therisk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.Cautious Moderately Cautious Balanced Moderately Adventurous Adventurous Cautious Balanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis: Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation Synaptic Risk Rating based o trategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[34The New Synaptic Contract Enquiry serviceMarie Aylward | Customer Services | Synaptic Software LimitedMarie Alward looks at the service designed as an industry utility to power any proposition including back offices and research toolsThe state of the art Synaptic contract enquiry is an inexpensive utility that allows youto acquire up-to-date valuations from 13 Providers and platforms. Synaptic research suite customers can use the service to update holdings valuations automatically, allowing them to perform reviews easily.A major criticism that has emerged in the recent thematic review regarding suitability of investments by wealth managers has been shortcomings relating to ‘know your client’. One of the three pillars of establishing suitability is having an up to date view of the client, including their holdings.Avoiding the need to contact the provider direct, the user can save a significant amount of time and resource by exchanging data electronically.Contract Enquiry enables electronic updates of funds and units from the product provider’s database directly into your back office system or into Synaptic. A request message is sentvia the Enterprise Messaging Platform which contains the contract details you wish to enquire about. A response message is sent back from the provider supplying the valuation details. For most providers these are the current assets that the contract is investing in and the number of units held (allocation) as well as the current price of those units. Some providers are also able to deliver additional details, such as transfer and surrender value, and where available these are used to update the holding record under the ‘client’ tab within Synaptic or passed back to the Back Office.Additionally the service is offered outside of normal business hours, seven days a week, allowing client servicing at times convenient to them. Servicing hours vary dependant on the provider.The information requested and the message received have been defined by the Origo Standards committee to insure both quality and consistency of data. Where a provider does not use the Origo Standards then proprietary secure messaging has been implementedthat meets statutory compliance and data protection requirements.Marie Alward looks at the service designed as an industry utility to power any proposition including back offices and research toolsThe state of the art Synaptic contract enquiry is an inexpensive utility that allows youto acquire up-to-date valuations from 13 Providers and platforms. Synaptic research suite customers can use the service to update holdings valuations automatically, allowing them to perform reviews easily.A major criticism that has emerged in the recent thematic review regarding suitability of investments by wealth managers has been shortcomings relating to ‘know your client’. One of the three pillars of establishing suitability is having an up to date view of the client, including their holdings.Avoiding the need to contact the provider direct, the user can save a significant amount of time and resource by exchanging data electronically.Contract Enquiry enables electronic updates of funds and units from the product provider’s database directly into your back office system or into Synaptic. A request message is sentvia the Enterprise Messaging Platform which contains the contract details you wish to enquire about. A response message is sent back from the provider supplying the valuation details. For most providers these are the current assets that the contract is investing in and the number of units held (allocation) as well as the current price of those units. Some providers are also able to deliver additional details, such as transfer and surrender value, and where available these are used to update the holding record under the ‘client’ tab within Synaptic or passed back to the Back Office.Additionally the service is offered outside of normal business hours, seven days a week, allowing client servicing at times convenient to them. Servicing hours vary dependant on the provider.The information requested and the message received have been defined by the Origo Standards committee to insure both quality and consistency of data. Where a provider does not use the Origo Standards then proprietary secure messaging has been implementedthat meets statutory compliance and data protection requirements.]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[What is the Enterprise Messaging Platform?The Enterprise Messaging Platform (EMP) provides Origo and Non-Origo electronic messaging between Synaptic and the product providers (includes platforms, wrapper providers, traditional life and pensions providers). Synaptic is the trusted third party and the services framework known as Synaptic is the platform host. The Platform supports UNIPASS© Identity Management and X.509 Certificate based Identity Management using Global Certificate Authorities.Screenshot 1 shows the ‘Provider screen’.insert provider list 2 graphicScreenshot 2. Shows how to set up regular valuations to take place automatically.Screenshot 3. Shows detail of holdings including up to date valuations.• • • • •You can use the Provider screen to:•Confirmthatyouareregisteredforonlineserviceswithyour selected providersRequest Authorisation of New ProvidersSet Provider Specific Connection CredentialsObtain Provider Server StatusEnable and Disable Services for ‘Your’ OrganisationLook up provider support information and service capabilitiesPlease contact us on 0800 783 4477 to learn more about the Synaptic Contract Enquiry service.35]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[36It’s good to talk!. . . Or is it?Paul Holland | CEO | Beyond EncryptionHow many times have you said something and regretted it? Retracting the spoken word isn’t easy!!With email it’s even easier to send the wrong content to the wrong person – sadly if you make that mistake, as we all have, the recipient holds documentary proof of the error; a mistake that could cost you dearly!Unless one wishes to risk the wrath ofthe Information Commissioners Office, secure electronic communication is a legal requirement and not just a ‘nice to have’; under the 1998 Data Protection Act (DPA) the regulator can levy penalties against such breaches of up to £500,000 per incident!The underlying technology that drives the internet, packet switching, will soon be 50 years old having originally been introduced when computers at Stanford and UCLA connected for the first time. A little under two years later email arrived, its invention credited to Ray Tomlinson in 1971. Ray picked the‘@’ symbol from the computer keyboard to denote sending messages from one computerto another . . . The rest, as they say, is history.The sheer volume of electronic communication today is mind blowing; 2011 saw the peakof text messaging with 150 billion SMS sent worldwide but this pales into insignificance compared with current daily worldwide email traffic volumes . . .The traditional postal service has suffered with the rise of alternative electronic communication (or ‘e-substitution’ as it is known in the industry) and has beenin decline since 2004; particularly in thetransactional / business sector. Interestingly,much of this ‘e-substitution’ is being causedinsecure and expensive; even recorded delivery only confirms delivery to a specified address rather than an identified individual. It won’t be a surprise that today, the Royal Mail service survives largely upon increased parcel delivery, ironically fuelled by online retail activity!Whilst the instant nature of email can be a key benefit for businesses, the simplicity of its operation has also lead to the infringement of data security.Normal email simply confirms delivery to a particular email address in much the same way as recorded delivery post can only prove delivery to a particular address, and not necessarily the intended recipient themselves.However, the email content itself may haveby technologies which have existed forSection 2 – Historical trends and contextseveral years rather than by very recentMost e-substitution is being caused by technologies which hinnovations as might be expected.been intercepted ‘en-route’ or someone elseexisted for several years rather than very recent innovationPhone Fax TVWorld wide weblaunched19901st online bankAmazon E-bayGoogleFirst graphical web browserHMRC launches online Self AssessmentYou Tube60% of UK has internet access75% of UK has home internet access50% of UK using the internet dailyGoogle Adwords2000FacebookiPhoneiPad2010 2013Many of theEmail, PDF and electronic invoicing systems enable B2B electronic invoicingThetrechanroelomgieasjor inefficiencies, risks and the currentlymay have had access to the device on which Rich ematihlsealelomwanielwasdledttreersvsolwumaesshtomstoevde !onlineMajor banks launch online portals enabling paperless statementsPay-Per-Click enables growth in internet advertisingThe effects innovatio printing is n be felt until tof the pl earlcosts (monetary and ecological) associateddriving themajor mailwith the traditional postal service. Slow,reductions have existed for a number of yearsRecent technological enablers such as Social networks, smartphones and tablets are expected to drive furtherdeclines, e.g. impact on Direct Mail and magazinesa sna i]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[37Nearly 200 billion emails are sent each and every day, that’s around 250 times as many words as you and I might speak in our entire lifetimes!During 2015, the Mortgage market saw a number of incidents where content was intercepted by unscrupulous thieves seeking to gain by misuse of the data.‘Home Deposit Fraud’, as its now been dubbed, became a hot topic in the tabloids with reports of hundreds of thousands of pounds of purchaser’s deposit money being re- directed to fraudsters bank accounts; no doubt 2016 will see its own fair share of personal and business data corruption.Communication®A number of solutions seeking to address these various issues have failed to gain widespread consumer adoption, most likely because they have failed to dovetail with existing desktop, online and mobile systems.From a corporate perspective, adopting existing identification parameters is similarly critical.Senders need to be able to choose the method by which they verify the recipient’s identity; this may take the form of a simple client specific ‘Question & Answer’ or extend to more sophisticated methods such as ‘physical tokens’ – many of us already use keypads or card readers that our banks issue alongside online internet banking.We have all used telephony banking systems that utilise simple pre agreed ‘Questionand Answer swaps’ to validate our identityto a degree of certainty that the bank is comfortable with, thereby enabling us to view statements, send money, pay bills etc.Naturally these variables cannot be shared with any other third party; so how can these ‘pre agreed’ parameters be utilised within a secure online communication system?BE have created adapters to seamlessly integrate secure email with the consumers chosen technology, whether they’re a user of Apple or Microsoft desktop and / or Apple or Android mobile devices. The recipient need not install anything in order to receive secure, Identity Assured Communication®.However, if they do choose to use the available ‘plug ins’, they too can simply and securely send and receive secure communicationsfrom within their chosen systems ANDreceive a ‘Verified Identity’ notification once the intended recipient has opened a secure communication.Learn more, register, and use for FREE at www.BeyondEncryption.comThe average British resident consumes nearly 4 1⁄2 twelve metre (40 foot) trees in paper consumption every year.Using BE a sender may employ existing ID parameters to identify their intended recipient, without exposing them externally.The ability to secure email communication simply and to ensure that the intended recipient, and only the intended recipient, opens that communication is crucial – going ‘Beyond Encryption’ - Identity Assured]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[38Enquiring stewards... researching the issues others may fail to considerJulia Dreblow | Director of sriServices and Founder of FundEcoMarketThe last time I contributed to Connections, in late 2014, I talked about fears of a ‘carbon bubble’ and the Governor of the Bank of England’s first pubic reference to the risk of ‘stranded assets’.Much has changed since then. In particular; COP21, the Paris climate change conference where195 countriessignedanagreementto limit temperature rises to below 2°C - and the divest campaign. Both look set to shape the way people think about energy and climate over the coming years.The fact that that coal, oil and gas reserves cannot all be burned - if we are to avoid catastrophic climate change - poses significant questions for investors large and small, ‘ethical’ or ‘otherwise’.However fossil fuels are not the only high profile issues that investors may wish to consider.Military action in Syria, heartbreaking images of refugees, tempers fraying over gay marriage within the Anglican Church, loss of biodiversity and a diesel fuelled corporate disaster – all are high profile issues people may want to reflect in their investment decision making.Investment managers label such issues with rather unwelcoming terminology like ‘avoidanceofstrategicarmaments’,‘human rights’, ‘equal opportunities’, ‘resource management’ and ‘corporate governance’ ... but they are none the less relevant.The industry is however moving towards better management of such issues. The FRC Stewardship Code, for example, encourages longer term thinking and greater engagement.‘Mainstream’ fund management responses can be broadly split into two, albeit overlapping, groups; research intended to inform buy/sell decisions - and ongoing ‘activity’ with investee companies.The former, ‘ESG integration’ (Environmental, Social and Governance), is increasingly used to improve risk management. It typically involves researching areas that would otherwise be overlooked – and voting shares accordingly. Activity with existing investee companiesmeanwhile can take many forms take many forms - variously referred to as ‘responsible ownership,stewardshipand/orengagement’. This involves investors thinking of themselves as ‘stewards’ or ‘part owners’ - and typically involves encouraging better management of material ESG issues through dialogue, voting and sometimes shareholder resolutions.Alliance Trust, Jupiter, Pictet, Sarasin & Partners, BMO (F&C) and Aviva are good examples of investors who are active in these ways. The Sarasin ‘House Report’ , for example, weaves easily between ESG and financial issues. Their work in this year’s ‘Aiming for A’ shareholder coalition is likely to be high profile as they and others are asking Anglo American, Glencore and Rio Tinto to show that they are workingto lessen the impact of climate change on their businesses - ahead of this year’s AGM. This follows last year’s program, led by CCLA, which resulted in 98% of shareholders backing a similar resolution at Shell and BP. So this will be one to watch.]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[39In these changing times there can be no downside to understanding clients’ aims better. Indeed you are likely to find that as stewards of your clients’ financial plans this is an increasingly essential skill set.This train of thought is taken even further by some funds of course.Many chose to put ‘sustainability’ and other ‘ethical’ issues front of house. Approaches vary greatly with some focusing more on ‘finding companies with winning longer term strategies - given the way the world is changing - while others focus more on finding attractive ‘ethically appropriate’ holdings.To help advisers make sense of this diversity and match it to clients’ aims we have come up with the ‘SRI Styles’ segmentation system – as used in Fund EcoMarket and by RSMR in their ‘Rated SRI fund’ service.In brief - the recently reviewed segments are:• ESG Integration - conventional funds that also research material ‘Environmental, Social and Governance’ risks.• Responsible Ownership & Engagement - conventional funds that actively encourage better ESG management through ‘responsible ownership’ - for the benefit of investors.• Sustainability Themed funds focus on companies’ responses to sustainability issues to help identify investment opportunities. These regularly include ethical criteria also. See options from Alliance Trust SF range, QuilterCheviot,Triodos,Impax andWHEB.• Environmental Themed funds focuson environmental issues to help identify opportunities. These may include ethical criteria also. See options from Jupiter, Pictet and Scottish Widows.• Social Themed funds focus on social (people) issues when selecting investments. May include ethical criteria. eg Columbia Threadneedle Social Bond.• Ethically Balanced funds combine positive and negative ethical screening criteria. May use ‘best in sector’ strategies and allow diverse investment. See options from Rathbones, EdenTree, Henderson, Standard Life, BMO/F&C, Friends Life.• Negative Ethical funds employ strict ‘negative’ values based ‘ethical’ criteria – which may mean they exclude a number of sectors. See options from Kames, Alliance Trust Ethical (ex NU) and OMW Ethical.• Faith Based funds avoid companies in line with religious principles (eg Shariah Law). (Note: many ethical funds also have ‘faith friendly’ policies).(The ‘triangle’ image shown illustrates a rough ‘allowable universe’ for investment).This system is intended as a guidethat helps highlight core strategies.Within each style strategies vary -and there are areas of crossover. Many ‘Themed’ options, for instance, list ethical avoidance criteria although these may have little impact on stock selection (as themes drive where they will invest).In addition, things change. Only a short time ago the term ‘fossil free’ was almost unknown to investors, diesel was in favour and there was no Social Investment sector.For advisers, the winning formula canonly be to focus on what clients’ want - by asking them.Identifying priorities with the help of a supplementary fact find is an easy way to do this. Our online ‘SRI StyleFinder’ fact find is free to use and as a Synaptic user you will also have access to their updated ‘issues based’ questionnaire.These methods are quite different, but both are supported by tools, links and reporting functions. In these changing times there can be no downside to understanding clients’ aims better. Indeed you are likely to find that as stewards of your clients’ financial plans this is an increasingly essential skill set.Notesi http://newsroom.unfccc.int/unfccc-newsroom/finale-cop21/ii https://www.frc.org.uk/Our-Work/Codes-Standards/Corporate- governance/UK-Stewardship-Code.aspxiii See Sarasin entry on www.FundEcoMarket.co.uk for report linkESG IntegrationEthically Balanced Negative Ethical Environmental Theme Social ThemeFaith BasedResponsible Ownership & Engagement]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[40SRI Investing how to choose fundsStewart Smith | Investment Manager | RSMRThe market for SRI funds is clearly diverse, both in terms of client requirements and in terms of the funds available. It is also dynamic with new ideas and themes emerging on an ongoing basis. Mostadvisers now accept that consideration of SRI investmentsshould form part of their normal advice process, regardlessof whether or not they specialise in this area, but many arenot clear on how to approach their fund selection.We work closely with sriServices, who categorise these funds into SRI styles. This is a very useful starting point, enabling you to find funds which fit with your clients’ requirements. Once this is done, you then need to narrow down your choice to a specific fund, which is where our SRI fund rating comes in.Our SRI fund rating is our ‘badge of quality’ for SRI funds, and uses a similar and equally robust methodology to that used for mainstream funds, modified slightly to take account ofthe range of SRI funds and their specific characteristics.We currently rate 27 SRI funds, and the process for determining whether or not the fund deserves a rating can be summarised as follows:The first part of the process is to determine the initial investment fund list on which to conduct further research. Our starting point for this is funds listed within the InvestmentAssociation (IA) sectors, to which we apply a filter to highlight just those with a specific SRI / ethical focus. In order to ensure we compare like with like, we then group thefunds according to their SRI style (determined by sriServices) before moving on to look more closely at the funds themselves.]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[41Our methodology for assessing SRI funds (and any other type of fund) allows us the flexibility to include funds that have not met the risk or performance criteria we set.Having identified a workable universe of funds, we then look closely at the funds with our research being split into two key areas – quantitative research and qualitative research.The quantitative research consists of a number of filters which are applied to the fund universe. Our fund ratings are aimed at retail investors and so we exclude funds which don’t focus on this market – for example charity funds. We then apply a series of statistical screens, looking at a range of performance and risk measures. Here we are looking to exclude the funds that have performed badly and also to better understand the risks being taken and how this affects the performance of the funds. Given the range of funds considered, each is looked at in the context of its IA sector and its SRI style, thereby ensuring that we comparea fund with its appropriate peer group. More detail on the actual measures used can be found by registering on our Research Hub and accessing our SRI Guide (http://members. rsmgroup.co.uk).The qualitative research is where we focus much of our time and resource as this is arguably the more important aspect – particularly for SRI funds. Here we look at the fund as a whole within the context of its aims and objectives with the purpose of understanding how it works in detail,and how its objectives and fund processrelate to the performance and risk wehave seen in our quantitative research.The qualitative assessment is based on a thorough understanding of the fund. Muchof the information is obtained through a detailed questionnaire completed by thefund management group, but we also obtain information from a variety of other sources. In this part of the process we consider how the fund is run, the resources in place to manage the fund and the expertise of key individuals. We also look at how the fund management team make stock decisions and what risk measures and controls are in place. Again, more detail on this can be found on our website.Our methodology for assessing SRI funds (and any other type of fund) allows us the flexibility to include funds that have not met the risk or performance criteria we set. This is important in many areas, but particularly SRI as a fund may be run in such a way that means it will have periods of underperformance or it may be in a sector to which it is not really comparable. Our process is to understand the fund and understand why it has performed in the wayit has. Where we can see clear reasons for any underperformance, and still see reasons for using the fund, then it may still be rated. This flexibility is particularly important in the areaof SRI as the funds will, by their nature, have a more limited universe of stocks to select from and may also be subject to other constraints that could affect their performance. A strong fund process and well defined stock selection criteria together with a commitment to the SRI market can override some of the other criteria.Our SRI rated fund list comprises thosefunds that we feel are well run and have a robust, repeatable process that has resulted in performance in line with expectation and with the risks taken thereby providing advisers with a usable list of funds, all of which have meta minimum standard. It is important to note that there will be other funds outside this list that may be suitable depending on the risk profile of the client and their specific needs and preferences - we have taken into account a number quantitative and qualitative factors but a different set of factors may have resulted in a different set of funds.From the list of rated SRI funds, you then need to select the most appropriate fund for your client, the sriServices SRI styles can help to narrow down your choice, and the factsheets that we provide for each of our rated funds can be used to provide the additional information you need to finalise your choice.Join our Research Hub at http://members.rsmgroup.co.uk]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[42Sustainable Future funds deliver strong investment performanceMike Appleby | Investment Manager | Alliance Trust InvestmentsThe Sustainable Future funds have delivered very strong investment performance. Seven out of eight (over 87%) of these funds are either 1st or 2nd quartile versus their conventional mainstream peers over the three year and five year period to the end of December 2015.Quartile Rankings to 31/12/2015Peer Groups1 year3 years5 yearsSustainable Future UK GrowthIA UK All Cos112UK EthicalIA UK All Cos111Luxcellence - Alliance Trust Sustainable Future Pan-EuropeanPan European Equity Funds111Sustainable Future Cautious ManagedIA Mixed 40% - 85% Equities1--Sustainable Future Defensive ManagedIA Mixed 20% - 60% Equities1--Sustainable Future ManagedIA Mixed 40% - 85% Equities111Sustainable Future Global GrowthIA Global211Sustainable Future Absolute GrowthIA Flexible111Sustainable Future Corporate BondIA £ Corporate Bond222Sustainable Future European ex UKIA Europe ex UK233Source: Financial Express, as at 31/12/2015. Past performance is not a guide to future performance.There is increasing demand for sustainable and ethical funds; and there are advisors who have chosen to differentiate themselves and grow, by specialising in offering these types of funds. Yet, some advisors still feel reluctant to recommend these funds, due to long-held misconceptions about poor investment performance, as well as being confused about this style of investment. It is time to get up to date and get rid of these misconceptions.The objective of the Sustainable Future funds, which are run by Alliance Trust Investments, is to generate investment returns thatare competitive to conventional funds, by looking for good businesses set to benefit from long-term trends we see happening in the economy. Many of these trends relateto improving quality of life by reducing the negative externalities and promoting positive consequences of business – this is essentially what we mean by sustainability.We are interested in understanding this because it can have a meaningful effect on the value of companies. We look for well run businesses which benefit from these trends and invest where we believe they are undervalued.We are stewards of our client’s capital and encourage proactive management of the business for the benefit of long-term shareholder returns.As for what these funds mean by sustainability or ethics: we clearly state our position on issues of concern to clients, disclose all fund holdings and are happy to respond to client queries on them. In addition, we publish information about trends we see happeningin the market and what stocks to watch; which gives investors plenty of information to understand where their money is invested.These funds could make a lot of sense for many of your clients.Important informationFor investment professionals only.The value of investments and the income from them may go down as well as up and is not guaranteed. Investors may not get back the amount invested.References[1] Analysis on the Sustainable Future Equity Funds by MSCI Research (12-Aug-2015) http://www.alliancetrustinvestments.com/sri-hub/ posts/2015/September/investments-to-be-fossil-fuel-freeAlliance Trust Investments Limited is a subsidiary of Alliance Trust PLC and is registered in Scotland No. SC330862, registered office, 8 West Marketgait, Dundee DD1 1QN; is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority, firm reference number 479764. Alliance Trust Investments gives no financial or investment advice.Focus on the managerAt Alliance Trust Investments (ATI) we have some of the top talent in the industry to manage our investment portfolio. Our team of 17 specialists are led by Peter Michaelis and have over225 years industry experience between them. They have significant experience in managing the Sustainable Future funds and deep expertise in integrating sustainability into investment selection. We offer a diverse range of funds from corporate bond, through mixed asset funds and a selection of equity funds. We believe that our investment philosophy is robust and has been used in the running of our Sustainable Future funds for over ten years.]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[43Rathbone Ethical Bond FundBryn Jones | Fund Manager | Head of Fixed IncomeThe fundOur objective is to provide a regular, above average income through investing in a range of bonds and bond market instruments that meet strict criteria ethically and financially.We run this benchmark-agnostic fundwith a strongly defined view that accounts for economic and political trends,company analysis, and thematic ideas.The investment grade fund targets a high yield with a strong ethical overlay. Once investment themes have been developed, the team carry out credit analysis tofind the assets that work best within the thematic framework. Cash flow and strong balance sheets are key in determiningbond selection, with the team applying the ‘Four Cs Plus’ principles: character, capacity, collateral and covenants. The ‘Plus’ is conviction – that to achieve above-average long-term performance, the team feelthey must think differently to the market. After that, an ethical overlay is applied - a negative screening to exclude any corporate bond issuers in breach of any of the exclusion criteria.The fund shall exclude bonds issued by companies wholly or predominately involved in the manufacture ofalcoholic beverages; animal testing; the manufacture or sale of strategic weapon systems, ordnance or combat vehicles; environmentally unsustainable or high- impact activities; gambling; nuclear power; pornography or the manufacture of tobacco or tobacco products.We then ensure that that issuers satisfyat least one of the fund’s positive criteria requirements - progressive or well- developed practice or policies in one ofthe following key areas including corporate community investment; commitment to workplace diversity and equal opportunities;employee work/life balance; human rights; management of environmental impacts and the provision of products or services that offer social or environmental benefits.The ethical research for the fund is done by specialist ethical investment unit Rathbone Greenbank Investments. The team has been at the forefront of developments in the ethical investment industry since 1992, launching one of the first bespoke ethical portfolio services.The managerBryn Jones, Fund Manager, Head of Fixed Income Bryn.jones@rathbones.comBryn is the Head of Fixed Income for Rathbones, and is lead manager on the Rathbone Ethical Bond Fund and the Rathbone Strategic Bond Fund. He joined Rathbones in November 2004 from Merrill Lynch, where he managed $2 billion of fixed income assets.Peformance to 31.1.16. I-Class unitsSector asset allocation (iBoxx sector classifcations) at 31.1.16Bryn is a member of the Rathbone Strategic Asset Allocation Committee, Non-Executive Chairman of Rathbones’ Fixed Income Committee, and an adviser to the Rathbone Banking Committee. Bryn appears regularly on CNBC and Bloomberg TV, and is also a co-opted Trustee for the Trust for London. He also sits on the IA Fixed Income Committee.Bryn’s Rathbone Ethical Bond Fund was awarded Best Sterling Corporate Bond Fund at the Morningstar UK Fund Awards 2014; Best SRI Bond Fund at the Money Observer 2015 Fund Awards and a ‘Highly Commended’ at the 2015 Moneywise Awards. His Rathbone Strategic Bond Fund was voted best Multi-Asset Fixed Income Strategy at the Investment Week Specialist Investment Awards 2015.1 year3 years5 yearsRathbone Ethical Bond Fund-1.5617.8342.95IA Sterling Corporate Bond sector-3.3711.5231.05Quartile111The information contained in this note is for use by investment advisers and journalists and must not be circulated to private clients or to the general public. Source performance data, Financial Express, bid to bid, net income re-invested.]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[44Ethical Investing value as well as values.Nurjanon Begum | Research Analyst | Synaptic SoftwareEthical investing is driven by the growing recognition of the need for companies and investors to take a long term approach to issues ranging from climate change to resource scarcity, therefore more people are seeking out sustainable investments.One of the key drivers for the growth in the market is that people want to actually see their money doing well, and many more would like to be offered sustainable and ethical options.Many savers are increasingly recognisinga market opportunity in building a more sustainable economy and the dangers of failing to do so. Recent incidents such as the fatal fires at textile factories in Bangladesh andthe ongoing scandals in the banking sectorare all blatant illustrations of serious impacts that failing to consider Environmental, Social and Governance (ESG) - factors can haveon companies’ profits, their share prices and therefore investor returns.In the past, the views of investors were that they had to sacrifice financial returns inorder to invest according to their beliefs. This viewpoint is slowly changing; it can be about value as much as it is about values. Now many funds focus on negative screening and reflecton sectors such as ethical and faith based investments that focus on excluding industries perceived as immoral such as tobacco, weapons, alcohol, gambling and pornography. It should no longer be just a moral issue; it should become a logical decision and a method of managing savings and planning for the future in a changing world.Once advisers have identified clients who have social goals, they need to know what to do next. Our ethical fund data on Synaptic helps investors and advisors make those choices. We have our ethical fact find which allows investors to screen the negative and positivecriteria in order to identify SRI aims- finding out what company activities their clients want to actively support with their investment or indeed to avoid.Our software also aids ethical fund selection when carrying out product and fund research which make it easy for advisers to includethese ethical policy questions into their fact find with their clients.The Synaptic Product and Fund tool helps users find appropriate funds for their clients. The tool includes an ‘ethical’ area which enables advisers to filter according to dozens of criteria – including ethical screens and other responsible investment fund and fund manager attributes. The data is independent, verified continually and the quantity available is forever expanding. The aim is to give advisers the ease to include it into their fact find with their clients.We currently maintain ethical policy data for over 730 funds and are finding on occasion that our customers are encouraging more fund managers to push this data to us as they are using our system to screen ethical funds and want specific promoters on there. It’s a promising sign that investing in ethical funds is increasing.]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[During 2015, in excess of 5% of fund recommendations through Synaptic included some element of ethical screening. The five most commonly selected ethical policy fields (all of which represent negative fund exclusions) were avoidance of investing in: Tobacco, Military, Environmental Abuse, Human Rights Abuse and Pornography.Source: Synaptic correct as at January 2016The consensus is that tools such as Julia Dreblow (a Synaptic collaborator’s) EcoMarket Database Tool and Synaptic software help simplify the advice process. We just hope that it’s used more frequently to change the current trend and advice process to include SRI and ethical investing in their fact finds.The screenshot below as shows how Synaptic presents view of ethical funds in aggregate or by sector, enabling analysis by specific feature. Advisers can filter and rank options in order to present to clients.If you would like a trial of our software, please phone us on 0800 783 4477 and quote ‘Research Team’.45]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[46Page needs logo and brand colCover Me NowAndrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskThe insurance principle of grouping people together should not bean excuse to shove very different people through the same customer journey. At present there is very little distinction between different people’s needs and expectations when they come to buy life insurance.Aged 65 and applying for £3m? – Great – here’s a long application form and a slightly insufficient number of financial questions that mean that we’ll have to come back and ask you more questions later.Aged 30 and applying for £150,000 toprotect your mortgage? Great – here’s a long application form with questions about medical things you’ve never heard of to worry you that we may find a way not to pay your claim.There are many different approaches that help companies focus on what their customer wants. Whether using customer segmentation models or focus groups in insurance these are all too often focused exclusively on product design rather than improving the customer experience to actually find or buy the product.It may not come as a surprise that underwriters don’t really think like many others. We tendto talk about cases rather than about people (or even applicants or potential customers). In our minds we categorise these cases in the following three headline ways:- people who say no to everything- people who say yes to some minor things but can be underwritten without getting more evidence- people who say yes to some more serious things and so we would prefer to get some more evidenceIn simple terms this is why I get excited whenI think about Cover Me Now – because it absolutely focuses on one huge group of people and makes their experience much better.Cover Me Now gets the most possible customers covered as quickly as possible. It understands that some customers will requirea more detailed assessment, and that there may be differences between how insurers want to treat these situations.In these instances the questions the insurers ask and the decisions they make may differ. There should be improvements here too, but we shouldn’t focus all the industry’s energy on solving that significant but smaller problem.We know that whilst the numbers of people being rated has crept up over the last decade there are still more “clean” applications where every answer is “No”. These people still have to go through all the questions we ask. They then face the uncertainty of not knowing if there might be an individual company tweak to their pricing when they go through the insurer’s website if different questions are asked or different factors taken into account.o]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours47There are many things that we need to do to get more people who need it buying life insurance. To start by making the process easy and ensuring that people who think about buying it can do so in a fair and straightforward way would be a big step forward.I believe that these people are potentiallymore likely to be put off the process altogetherthan less healthy people. You can explain to someone that has high blood pressure thatyou need to ask a few more questions, or to - someone who has had cancer that you wouldlike to see some medical reports to ensure theyget the best possible terms for them.Explaining to someone who has absolutelynothing wrong with them that you need to - force them through the same cumbersomeprocess is more difficult. This is particularlytrue when there is suspicion about insurance companies claims approaches and every extra question and process can be seen as another - trap to be used against the customer later on.People are more likely to give more accurate answers if the questions are short, well written and only asked once in the process – so there should be less issues around misrepresentation at claims stageIf you answer no to all questions asked you are on average a better risk than someone who answers yes but currently gets standard rates – which should reduce any increase to risk cost by asking less questionsThese people are low cost to underwrite and insure – and so getting more of them brings a lower administration cost to the business overall. The insurer can then chooses whether to spread that saving across all customers or target it at these peopleThere is real potential to grow the market by improving the process for this silent majority of lives. These people do not currently cause insurance companies administrative painand costs with pre-sales enquiries, multiple applications to different insurers and medical evidence requests and underwriting. Instead these customers see a cumbersome process that assumes people are unhealthy – and shirk away from the process altogether.- If the customer sees final prices for more than one provider they are more likely to continue and complete the process and less likely to look around for alternatives in the near futureThere are several other detailed attributes to the Cover Me Now approach that compliment the overall theme:- Webline allows you to see all quotes on the same page, so that you can still see the results of any insurers who are not signed up to Cover Me Now. Therefore you still have an understanding of these offerings without additional searching to see what terms may be available from othersThere are many things that we need to doto get more people who need it buying life insurance. To start by making the process easy and ensuring that people who think about buying it can do so in a fair and straightforward way would be a big step forward. By making these improvements Cover Me Now can help more people get the protection they and their families need.For further information on Cover Me Now call 0800 783 4477.COVER ME NOW]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[48‘If I die the business dies’Why Business Protection is essential for sole tradersMarcus Primhak | Business Protection Manager | LV=Sole traders are a vital part of the economy, with 3.3 million operating in the UK. Put into context, there are more sole traders comparedto partnerships, limited liability partnerships and limited companies combined - presenting advisers with a big business opportunity.One in seven of the workforce is self- employed, and the number of people working for themselves has increased by 30% since 2000. But how can advisers successfully pitch Business Protection to the solo entrepreneur? Especially when so many sole traders (wrongly) assume, ‘if I die, the business dies with me’.Why sole traders need a succession planWhen a sole trader dies a number of financial and contractual obligations still need to be fulfilled – regardless of whether the business carries on trading or is wound down. Without succession planning, these will usually fall to a spouse or the next-of-kin, and can include:• Finance – outstanding overdrafts and finance will need to be transferred (or paid off) and the new owner will be expected to brief investors on the ability to meet existing commitments.• Clients – ongoing contracts will need tobe assessed; the family or estate may need to recruit a sub-contractor to fulfil existing commitments, or employ additional staff. Alternatively, penalties could be imposed for the non-delivery of goods or services.• Leased premises –the landlord will need to be informed of the sole trader’s death and a new lease may be required. If the business is wound down, significant penalties might need to be paid if the premises are no longer needed.• Employees – 9% of sole traders employ staff using the PAYE system. Even though the name of the business mayhave changed, Transfer of Undertakings (Protection of Employment or TUPE) regulations mean employees still have a right to continued employment. If the new owner intends to cease trading then staff will be entitled to redundancy pay. Any outstanding litigation and tribunal claims will continue, so the estate or family will be expected to deal with these as well.• Health and safety – whoever takes over responsibility for the business will beheld accountable for all health and safety matters? They will need to make sure all regulations are being met, are risk assessed and properly documented. This may need to be outsourced.• Insurance – any insurance policies will need to be transferred into the name of the new owner and might require specialist advice.• Updating the trading name – all relevant paper work (invoices, letterheads etc.)When a sole trader dies a numberof financial and contractual obligations still need to be fulfilled]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[49Sole traders now make up such a significant part of UK business – so having products and advice standards specifically catered for them should be an important consideration for both advisers and providers.need updating e.g. Steve Jones t/a Jones Construction will now trade as Jane Jones t/a Jones Construction.Key Person cover (written in trust, on the life of the sole trader) can provide the deceased’s family with the money needed to meet these obligations. However, many sole tradershave given little or no thought about their responsibilities if they die - let alone their family’s legal commitments, even though the costs to meet these can be high.Buying the family timeA lump sum payment will help ease muchof the pressure felt by the family, who will already be dealing with the devastating loss of a loved one. They can use the money to decidethe money paid from Key Person cover will ensure any employees are appropriately compensated, outstanding debts are cleared and all other commitments are dealt with. If the family decide to continue trading, they will be able to cover existing obligations and ensure running costs are met during the recovery period.These ongoing business liabilities should give sole traders a big wake-up call. And advisers should be ready to recommend Key Person cover that includes the appropriate features for sole traders:• Advisers will want to make sure that the guaranteed insurability options can be exercised by sole traders, and if possible,family, it’s worth checking children’s cover is included (as some Business Protection policies exclude it). During a period of intense family stress and worry, having the funds available to support the sole trader so they can spend more time at home could be immeasurably valuable. Likewise, if the sole trader has key employees who have children.• Some Business Protection policies now include a number of value-added benefits, including free access to services suchas legal helplines, HR support, funding guidance and regulatory advice. These resources can be invaluable to sole traders (and their loved ones during a claim), who would have to pay for comparable services separately. Research by LV= reveals 38% of businesses who have access to equivalent services have used them, and 68% of all business that have them rate the support as invaluable.Sole traders now make up such a significant part of UK business – so having products and advice standards specifically catered for them should be an important consideration for both advisers and providers.You can find out more about LV= Business Protection (including Key Person cover for sole traders) at www.LV.com/businessprotectionOne in seven of the workforce is self-employed, and the number of people working for themselves has increased by 30% since 2000what to do with the business - a specialist can be recruited who is able to make sensible decisions regarding its future. If the family chooses to wind down the trading activities,include the option to increase cover based on a rise in net taxable earnings.• If recommending life insurance and critical illness cover and the sole trader has a young]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50Introducing British Friendly SocietyJohn Willis | Director | Synaptic Software LimitedThe British Friendly Society (BFS) was founded initially in 1902 to provide sickness benefits for Commercial Travellers.While the Society hasgrown and diversified since then, it remains a mutual which is a strong, resourceful and a trusted partner to thousands of people.Based in Bedford, British Friendly is one of the larger UK Friendly Societies with over £90min assets, operating solely for the benefit of its more than 17,000 members. Since 2002 it has also managed the British Airways Benefit Fund, in March 2011 it launched Protect and thenin July 2013 the Breathing Space product was announced.Mindful of its mutual status, BFS began looking during 2015 for a very cost-effective solution to expanding its market coverage, and extending its reach in to a wider audience of financial advisers. At the same time it needed a solution that allowed it to grow ina controlled way, and maintain the servicing levels that its members expected.The Synaptic Webline approachAt this stage BFS began working with Synaptic Webline to jointly devise a solution that allowed BFS to rapidly offer three of its key income protection products through the portal.Webline was already delivering quotes and new business for eleven IP providers, and BFS planned to be the twelfth. There’s a healthy user base on Synaptic Webline, and good mixture of both advisers (B2B users) and online offerings (B2B2C / D2C). Between them these users are regularly receiving well over a million comparative quotation responses from the participating providers each month. Once the BFS service was up and running, it was an easy matter to make their products available to Webline’s existing user base.In order to reduce the project delivery times and keep costs under control for the firstphase, it was decided that Synaptic would build and run a local “quote engine” for BFS’s IP products. Working closely with BFS the new quote module was built and thoroughly tested, and approved by BFS for release. In parallel Synaptic also wrote the software for creating and delivering PDF documents of the personalised illustrations to advisers. The whole development and testing process took a few weeks, and allowed BFS to offer their IP products to a large new user base on Webline for a modest cost.In 2015, BFS launched their new online application which now allows them to acceptIn 2015, BFS launched their new online application which now allows them to accept a percentage of their cases automatically online]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[51Mindful of its mutual status, BFS began looking during 2015 for a very cost-effective solution to expanding its market coverage, and extending its reach in to a wider audience of financial advisers.a percentage of their cases automatically online. Several of the other IP providers already have online new business facilities into their extranets – and Webline links seamlessly to them for users to submit their new cases online. Typically over 5,000 cases are begun this way each month.British Friendly Society Income ProtectionSynaptic Webline now enables hundreds of additional firms to access the major BFS income protection products –• The Protect (Long Term) Policy. The Protect (Long Term) Policy provides regular benefit payments for the duration of the insured’s incapacity until their chosen retirement date under the Policy, or until a defined event occurs.• The Protect (Short Term) Policy provides regular benefit payments for a period of up to 1, 2 or 5 years depending on which payment period the insured has selected.• Breathing Space is an income protection policy suitable for the self-employed, casual or part time workers or those with irregular incomes. It provides flexible options and doesn’t require any proof of income atany stage, just proof that the insured wasworking before suffering a loss of income. It pays a regular benefit following sickness or injury leading to a loss of earnings. Cover is provided on an own occupation basis, meaning that the Policy will pay benefitsif, in the opinion of a Doctor, the insuredis unable to do the main tasks of their occupation.For more information call us on0800 783 4477 or visit www.synaptic.co.ukSynaptic Webline now enables hundreds of additional firms to access the major BFS income protection products]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52I don’t need protection, I’m young!Denise Wond | Marketing Manager | Royal LondonThe world was rocked by the death of Jonah Lomu, one of Rugby’s greatest stars, he was just 40 years old. His death was mourned across the world and highlighted that our time on earth comes with no guaranteeof longevity.Despite his fame and success Jonah died relatively broke. The mansion he shared with his family was rented, the cars bought on finance and very little in the way of savings. His lackof assets and savings has been blamed on maintaining a lifestyle that 20 years of illness made unaffordable1. The chances are that he’d have been off work for much of the twenty years of illness, dialysis and surgery he endured. Jonah’s story is clear evidence, if any were needed, that you’re never too young to take out the cover you need.As bad as the situation is, there is a worldwide community of loyal fans who have set up a trust fund to provide an income for his sons. That would not be the case had he been just another working man from across the street. And if he’d lived in the UK, where only 9%of working households have any incomeprotection in place, it’s highly unlikely that he’d have had protection in place2. As sad as they are, such high profile cases present a perfect opportunity for advisers to introduce protection to their client conversations. Most clients will need at least some protection, they just don’t buy it, and those who do, don’t buy enough of the right cover. Income protection which covers the highest risk your clients face, remains the protection underdog.In fact, we live in a topsy turvy world where the most bought cover is life cover and the leastis income protection. Why? Perhaps because life cover is easy to sell – we all die and it’s cheap. On closer inspection however, the reason why it’s so cheap is quite clear – we rarely die prematurely. Conversely, income protectionis relatively more expensive because the risks are so much higher, which would surely be an indication that clients need it.We live in a topsy turvy world where the most bought cover is life cover and the least is income protection.]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[53Most clients will need at least some protection, they just don’t buy it, and those who do, don’t buy enough of the right cover. Income protection which covers the highest risk your clients face, remains the protection underdog.Each year 650,000 people make a claim for Employment Support Allowance (ESA) but only around 300,000 end up with any health related benefit.Within our industry, the 7families campaign has done a lot of good work in terms of raising awareness of the need for income protection. Much more has to be done to raise awareness with consumers. And that probably needs to start with advisers.There’s plenty of convincing material out there and loads of reliable statistics that could help you open the income protection conversation. Most providers also have a stacked toolbox that you can dip into. It helps if you have a solid understanding of the limits of state support, because it is limited. And unfortunately most of your clients will only be vaguely aware of what kind of support they could expect to receive. Highlighting the reality may be enough to open their eyes to the need for more than just some life cover. You can easily do this using entitledto.co.ukIf there’s any doubt, you only need to look at the depth and breadth of welfare reform to understand that state support is likely to be limited. Benefit caps, the bedroom tax, means- testing, the move to universal credit are just some of the changes the government has made to reduce the welfare bill. Significantly, support for mortgage interest will become a loan from April 2018 upon which interest will be charged and admin charges will be levied. Additionally, from April 2016 those in need of that support will need to wait 39 weeks before it kicks in.Our benefits system is complex as is the application process. Figures from the 2011 health and work report tell us that each year 650,000 people make a claim for Employment Support Allowance (ESA) but only around 300,000 end up with any health related benefit. Those odds aren’t that great. Add to that thelimited support most employers offer and the gap becomes quite evident.If you don’t have these conversations withyour clients who else will? Who else has your expertise? And importantly, how would you feel if, having secured the mortgage for your clients, they subsequently ended up with a financial nightmare that enough of the right cover could have protected?Source: 1 The Guardian 2Mintel Income Protection – UK February 2015]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[54Good health is good businessSally Hogbin | Head of Legal & Business Support | VitalityLifeWith absenteeism costing UK businesses more than £15 billion every year*, businesses of all sizes are beginning to appreciate that improving employee health and wellbeing can have a significant impact on their finances, as well as increasing productivity and engagement in the workplace. At VitalityLife, we understand how strong the link is between good health and bottom-line results.This is one of the reasons why we’ve recently enhanced our offering so our healthy rewards and discounts are now available across our entire range of business protection products. We believe a healthy business is a prosperous business and that if business owners put wellbeing on the agenda and improve their own health, they can set the standard for the rest of their workforce. Simply put, good health is good business.Vitality Optimiser for Business ProtectionOur new product enhancements now allow business owners to choose to optimise their Business Protection Plan with Vitality Optimiser and receive an upfront discount on premiums. For longer terms the discount can be as much as 25%, meaning cash flowis improved and more money is retained inthe business for other purposes. Figures from Companies House show that the averageage of a company coming off the Company Register is 13.6 years, so this saving in the early years could be vital.Premiums are adjusted each year depending on the “Vitality Status” of the person covered. The more they do to keep healthy, the less money the business has to pay in premiums. We’re also one of the only insurers to offer up to £100 cashback each year based on the Vitality Status of the person covered, so our plans can also help the business itself save money directly.This new integrated approach to wellness and protection enables small businesses to offer their people an employee benefits packageusually reserved only for large businesses. With our plans, business owners and employeescan have access to discounts and rewardslike money off travel with British Airways and Eurostar, as well as being rewarded with aBusinesses can builda culture of health improvement to lower costs and promote overall business success]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[55Our new product enhancements now allow business owners to choose to optimise their Business Protection Plan with Vitality Optimiser and receive an upfront discount on premiumscinema ticket and a drink at Starbucks every week for being active. Discounted health screenings are also available so each year the business owner can be sure he or she is fit for his or her business year ahead.Our plans therefore provide benefits during the individual’s working life, as well as peace of mind and the necessary funds should an unexpected death or severe illness occur.Shareholder protection: under the spotlightIf a business owner dies, their share of the business will usually pass to the chosen beneficiaries under their Will. To regain full control of the business, the surviving business owners will need to buy the deceased’s share of the business from the beneficiaries to retain control. Many businesses will not have the available capital to do this.With VitalityLife’s Shareholder Protection, a lump sum is paid if a business owner dies. This lump sum provides the capital to enable the surviving business owners to purchase the deceased’s or incapacitated individual’s share of the business – allowing them to keep control of their business. Additional cover can be included to protect the owners should a shareholder suffer a severe illness. Each planis set up under a business trust and a cross option agreement for all participating owners should be put in place to facilitate a potential future sale or purchase of the shares.Although the long term benefits and peace of mind provided by shareholder protection are clear to see, cost is often raised as an issue. However, shareholder protection can often be established at an annual cost of under 1% of the company turnover. Premium equalisation should also be carried out meaning that each shareholder pays a proportionate amount towards the benefit he or she is likely to receive. This will often have the added benefit of sharing some of the oldest person’s premium between the younger lives removing an objection from the oldest individual.In recent months we’ve seen an increasing number of business owners taking out shareholder protection and choosing to include the VitalityLife healthy rewards and discounts for a small extra cost. This suggests business owners know that their own good health is crucial for their business’s long-term success.Disability Cover for BusinessFor many businesses, the long term illness or disablement of a key individual can have a similar impact to a death within the business.To protect against this risk Disability Cover for Business can be included on the Business Protection Plan. It covers 48 specified conditions that will always pay valid claims at 100% of the chosen sum assured. This type of cover is therefore ideal for shareholder protection. Our Business Protection Plan can also be used for Loan Protection and Key Person Cover.Changing Business CultureWith a Business Protection Plan from VitalityLife, businesses have the opportunity to build a culture of health improvement which can result in lower costs, improved performance and overall business success. The workplace offers the ideal environment where business owners and employees are a naturally captive audience with unique resources and built-in infrastructure necessary to encourage healthy behaviour changes.Find out more by speaking to your VitalityLife Business Consultant or visiting vitalitylife.co.uk/ adviserbp*Source: VitalityHealth’s ‘Britain’s Healthiest Company’, 2015]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Objective risk managementUnlike any other best advice tool, Synaptic Modeller offers full access to the Moody’s Analytics risk management tool. Now is the time to strengthen your due diligence around risk and suitability using Synaptic’s metrics for risk, Capacity and Tolerance for Loss.Synaptic Modeller is part of the Synaptic Research suite that includes Synaptic Product and Fund, Synaptic Comparator and Synaptic Webline. All can be accessed through single log on, payment and agreement. *Offer includes option for Synaptic Contract Enquiry service, allowing you to maintain holdings information from Providers, including up-to-date valuations. (Subject to £75 setting up fee).Synaptic Modeller Special Deal• Knowyourclient,understandtheirappetiteand tolerance for risk• Storeclients’detailsincludingtheirriskprofile• Modelinvestmentoutcomeswithactualholdings*using Moody’s Analytics stochastic engine• Create,manageandriskassessportfoliosandfunds• IncludesindustryleadingATRQ• Fullrangeofreports• Workefficientlyandaccurately• UsedbyawiderangeofnetworksandIFA'sTo watch our Risk Profiling and Fund selection video, visit the quick links section of our website www.synaptic.co.ukFor more information and to claim your discount on Synaptic Modeller call 0800 783 4477 now.Deal informationOffer ends 31st May 2016, Synaptic Software Limited reserve the right to withdraw this offer at any time, depending on availability and demand. Minimum contract term 18 months. Additional discounts may be available for bulk requirements, or additional software modules. Existing Modeller contracts, including any existing obligations will not be affected by this offer.month £15 per(reduced from £50 per month) for full portfolio andrisk management]]></page></pages></Search>