<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q3 2017Selection of industry features for the professional adviserSynaptic Risk Ratings Table published. New Providers include Aviva Investors, LV=, Old Mutual Global Investors, Scottish Widows• Update: Synaptic Analyser - Getting ready for ‘Appropriate Pension Transfer Analysis’• Feature: Conquering Risk: Do you know your Attitude to Risk from your Capacity for Loss?• Feature: GDPR (Data Protection) - What’s in IT for me?• Update: Intelliflo’s Intelligent Office now integrates with Synaptic research software• Update: Synaptic Cover Me Now Protection Portal now combines ‘Buy it Now’ Protection with full range of provider optionsOnce in a lifetime opportunity?Pension transfers and investment matters with David Norman (TCF Investments / MAPS)Inside...›› Busting the myth of ‘U-Shaped’ Retirement Spending. Abraham Okusanya, FinalytiQ›› Fact or myth? Active vs Passive. Justin Onuekwusi, LGIM›› Invest for retirement income and avoid the pitfalls. Iain McGowan, Scottish Widows›› Not all income is created equal. David Palmer, Sarasin & Partners›› Volatility targeting: a cautionary tale. Thomas Wells, Aviva Investors ›› Steering a smooth course in retirement. Steve Lewis, LV=]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[The Suitability SuiteRisk . Costs . Due diligence . Best adviceProof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research• The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costsSynaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reportingSynaptic ComparatorDetailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculationsRISKSynaptic RiskA.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfoliosSynaptic ModellerModels investment outcomes for new existing holdings. Manage and assess investment riskSYNAPTICWEBLINEProtection and Annuity quotes and on-line applications Synaptic Webline (including enhanced annuities)Synaptic Suitability offer £140 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp is £226Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.SAVE OVER£125 PER LICENCE]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Once in a lifetime opportunity? 04 Maybe for some.David Norman, TCF Investment & MAPSGetting ready for ‘Appropriate Pension 06 Transfer Analysis’ (APTA)Synaptic Software LimitedBusting the myth of ‘U-shaped’ retirement 08 spendingAbraham Okusanya, FinalytiQPlatform market update: Regulatory and 10 Due Diligence SmackdownSteve Nelson, the lang catFact or Myth? 12 Justin Onuekwusi CFA, Legal & GeneralInvestment ManagementConquering Risk: Do you know your Attitude 14 to Risk from your Capacity for Loss?Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Risk Table 16Invest for retirement income and avoid 24 the pitfallsIain McGowan, Scottish WidowsNot all income is created equal 26 Verbatim introducing David Palmer, Sarasin &Partners LLPThe time has come for an “all-in” fee 28 Ben Raven, Tavistock WealthVolatility targeting: a cautionary tale 30 Thomas Wells CFA, Aviva InvestorsSix questions on the market outlook 32 Paul Craig, Old Mutual Cirilium PortfoliosIn search of rewards 34 John Redwood, Charles StanleyCorrelation fixation 36 John Stopford, Investec Asset ManagementSteering a smooth course in retirement 38 Steve Lewis, LV=Business Protection and poor health 40 Richard Jessup, JustCommercial interests 42 Nigel Ashfield, TIME InvestmentsWhat to look for in a financial adviser 44 Neil Cowell, Vanguard Asset ManagementPortfolio construction - is Modern Portfolio 46 Theory still relevant?Geoff Mills, RSMRGeneral Data Protection Regulation – What’s 48 in IT for me?Tiina Stephens, Synaptic Software LimitedIntelliflo’s Intelligent Office now integrates 50 with Synaptic research softwareSynaptic Software LimitedCurrent issues and future opportunities 52 for Critical IllnessAndrew Wibberley, Alea RiskSynaptic Cover Me Now Protection Portal 54 Synaptic Software LimitedFor some clients, the opportunity to move from DB may be too good to miss, and Dan Norman explains why this may be the case. More widely, pensions work has always represented a significant proportion (often the majority) of income for advisers, and that is clearly not going to change anytime soon.Having the right research tools is becoming more important than ever, a point that is coming up repeatedly in FCA guidance as well as expert commentary in regards to forthcoming MiFID II (January 2018). Never has the role of Synaptic been more relevant. Whilst the quality of outcomes exists in most advice areas, the FCA is demanding better due diligence and evidence of research in files across the board.In this edition, we focus on our brand new research tool, Synaptic Analyser, combining all the elements of retirement planning including accurate enhanced annuity quotes, with accurate provider illustrations. Youcan complete drawdown planning using additional sources of income, including multiple scenarios from one screen.We highlight the success that the new Synaptic Risk service has enjoyed, as more and more advisers, fund groups, providers and discretionary managers recognise the advantages that aligning fully with Synaptic and Moody’s offers.In the protection realm, we are delighted to have brought the UK’s leading buy-it-now proposition, Cover Me Now to market - and encourage any protection writers to consider this option for inclusion in their operations. Cover me now is available fully integrated with Synaptic Webline, which itself has several enhancements including ‘Provider Features’ which can be viewed with a roll- over when looking at ‘multi-benefit’.There is a lot of change to assimilate at the moment, but we are confident that Synaptic will assist the thousands of subscribers that we have to stay ahead of the pack when it comes to accurate research.Eric ArmstrongEditorContact DetailsSynaptic Software LimitedFusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AASales: 0800 783 4477To sign up for Connection magazine visitwww.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Byfordnaomi.byford@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969The Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expresses throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.CONTENTSOnce in a lifetime opportunity?3]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4Once in a lifetime opportunity?Maybe for some.Pension transfers and investment mattersDavid Norman | CEO | TCF Investment and MAPSPension planning has two clear stages: saving up and drawing down. Advisers, and possibly clients, will have many years’ experience of the saving up phase – but very little of the drawing down stage, especially over extended periods.The need to access a sustainable inflation linked withdrawal rate while maintainingan appropriate level of capital is key. Rather than simply trying to maximise returns, investors are trying to maximise “durability” of income.This durability is one of the fundamental risks associated with taking a DB transfer.Pensions freedoms and home equityRecent changes in pensions legislationand the very high CETVs (Cash Equivalent Transfer Values) mean that for many people, their pension will become their largest asset – possibly of much higher value than even their home. It is therefore natural when faced with this large and important asset that people will want to preserve it. Unfortunately for many this will mean not taking any risk (risk of loss), and invest in cash. When in fact one of the most pernicious long-term risks is inflation – and cash is a poor asset to protect against inflation.The rapid rise in equity release products, and the improvement in the product over recent years, may also be a factor to consider in wider pension (long term income) provision.With sensible planning, it is now possible to pass pension wealth to future generations very tax effectively. This is assisted by the new Residence Nil Rate Band for IHT.The interaction between the pension and IHT tax regimes, the need for long-term income, the potential need for long-term care, the need for a diversified asset mix of real assets inside your pension fund (not just owninga residential property outside your pension fund), the tax-effectiveness of investing inside a pension wrapper, the triple lock (or double lock) on state pension benefits, the enhanced death benefits and IHT planning available under pension freedoms all serve to highlight the critical need for professional impartial advice when considering a full or partial transfer of DB scheme benefits.What is clear is that a simple critical yield assessment is flawed.The state of DB schemesOne important factor to consider when planning to transfer from a DB scheme is the health of the scheme and the risk of it failing to meet some, or all, of its future liability.This takes on greater significance for those with higher benefits that are yet to retire (as the Pension Protection Fund (PPF) only covers pensions to a cap). The cap at age 65 is, from 1 April 2017 this equates to £34,655.05 (when the 90 per cent level is applied), set byDWP.Note: The PPF has approximately £3.5bn of assets and receives c £540m a year in levies. Level of UK DB scheme deficits is c£300bn. So, there is more than a little gap if there is series of large calls.Not so many years ago, a DB pension was deemed to be “guaranteed” but as we have seen with BHS/Tata and a myriad of smaller schemes which fail, often un-noticed, this concept is no longer absolute.It may be a better outcome for an investor with a full state pension entitlement, to spend their pension pot faster than a typical annuity / DB pension would allow while they are in good health. Knowing that they have significant home equity in their main residence to draw from in later life. So long as they understand the impacts and risks of this strategy the improved “quality of life” that they can enjoy for say 10 years with a higher income, could be a compelling reason for a DB transfer to access more flexible benefits.]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[5Not so many years ago, a DB pension was deemed to be “guaranteed” but as we have seen with BHS/Tata and a myriad of smaller schemes which fail, often un-noticed, this concept is no longer absolute.State of the pension nationHymans Robertson research shows that:• DB liabilities are now greater than UK GDP• For many schemes benefits being paid outare greater than contributions being paid in.• An estimated £10bn a year will flow out ofDB schemesPrevious requirements for schemes to match their liabilities to bonds means that schemes have been holding the “wrong” long term assets (bonds) to meet long-term inflation linked liabilities. Indeed, any rise in inflation could lead to a rapid fall in bond prices further exacerbating the funding gap for DB schemes.High CETVsThe very low bond yields have driven CETVs from DB schemes to very high levels. Some investors have seen the CETVs more than double in a very short period, and critical yields even being driven negative – CETVs more than 100 times the pension are not uncommon. It is exactly these long and sustained falls in bond yields that has driven transfer values from DB schemes up. As the discount rate has fallen, the cash required today to buy out a given liability has risen.Many commentators are concerned about the significant risk in bond markets that ultra-low yields have created – while thereis currently no sign of a liquidity crunch, the prospect of rising inflation may trigger a rapid reversal of yields and sharp fall in bond prices. And as we have seen in credit markets historically this can be a rapid and violent change in direction.Note: CETVs are driven by the discount rate (usually long dated bond yields adjusted for the scheme asset allocation mix), inflation rates and the scheme demographics. Rising inflation expectations as well as falling long dated bond yields will typically increase transfer values.From a long-term return perspective, itis easy to see why a transfer value, based on bond yields of less than 1%, invested in a broad equity portfolio, with a 3-4% dividend yield could make a move from DB to DC worthy of consideration at least from an investment perspective.Particularly when you consider thesteady rate at which dividends have been maintained by FTSE ALL Share companies see Figure 1.In the weedsWithout seeking specialist advice, many clients will think there is a binary choice between DB “guarantees” or DC “non- guaranteed”. This does not have to betrue: A strategy of utilising a short term (guaranteed) annuity to bridge the income gap to state pension age, or secure guaranteeof nil rate income tax band for non-earners could be appropriate. Indeed, a single person with grown up children may be able to secure a guaranteed income equal to their DB scheme benefits and still have remaining cash. I would expect to see a rising demand for, and development in, the annuity market (long term guarantees up to 30 years) which offer valuable long-term certainty.One important factor to consider when planning to transfer from a DB scheme is the health of the scheme and the risk of it failing to meet some, or all, of its future liability.Figure 1. FTSE All-Share Index Dividend Yields (blue) and Annual Total Returns (red). Source: Siblis ResearchArmed with a professional financial adviser (coach), a low-cost well-diversified portfolio and a sensible approach to investment and income provision, the opportunity presented by all-time high CETVs make a transfer a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity.With thanks to Janice Russell, Specialist Pension Adviser at Russell Retirement Solutions, for her valuable input. This is an abridged version of a longer article – please contact Dan (David) directly if you wish to see the original.To review this article in full please request via email: david.norman@tcfinvestment.com]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[6Getting ready for ‘Appropriate Pension Transfer Analysis’ (APTA) – the future of pensions adviceEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedOlder software including TVAS and pension switching tools may soon be passed their sell-by-date.The Consultation Process for ‘Advising on Pension Transfers’ is now underway – and a lot of issues are coming to a head reflecting that annuity is no longer the default option and guaranteed income is not necessarily the end game:• There is a need for clear strategies (including risk) tied to investment and income objectives;• Advising in this area ‘impossible without some kind of cashflow modelling’ (Rory Percival ‘17).The good news is that Synaptic are now launching a single tool that facilitates the financial planning requirements in the new world, where a ‘personal recommendation’is part of any compliant pension (or other) investment transfer. Synaptic Analyser provides:1. State of the art cashflow modelling; 2. Research that provides calculations tohelp produce the new ‘Transfer ValueComparator’;3. Accurate quotes for retirement, includingdrawdown products.Most advisers will have noticed the upheavals in the pensions advice areas, and wondered what opportunities exist for them. Part of the disruption has come from the cessation of trading of various transfer specialists, the typethat would review a case to allow an adviser recommendation to proceed. The regulator recognised that the process had been too compartmentalised, distorted by ‘contingent charging’ (incentivising the recommendation to switch, on which the fee was ‘contingent’).This is a significant transition period for our industry. The regulator is shifting the goal posts in a constructive way that requires firms to re-purpose their processes to re-centreon the client. By focussing on a ‘critical yield’ calculation, too little consideration was given to the client, either in terms of their objectives and wider circumstances, or in the subsequent execution of pension switching advice. This is a big upheaval as the current ‘value analysis requirement’ (TVA) is on the way OUT.The new Synaptic Analyser tool has been designed to cover several requirements, with the possibility of reducing the number of tools an adviser needs to purchase, or work with, combining retirement income modelling and drawdown analysis – designed to fulfil the financial planning requirements and due diligence for all kinds of pension advice in the new world. Synaptic Analyser will:1. Replace some of the tools that have previously provided TVA calculations This is good news as use of ‘defaults’ and ‘box ticking’ culture is baked into theshortcomings of these tools. Synaptic Analyser will provide a more up-to-date template for advice, including accurate ‘enhanced’ annuity quotes.2. ThecentralpropositionoftheCP17/16 paper is that consumer protection requires pensions advice to be ‘apersonal recommendation’. Due in partto the relatively recent advent of high transfer valuations and the increasing precariousness of many schemes, a transfer is no longer deemed unsuitable by default, however removal of specific benefits are deemed to be unsuitable by default. So (3.10) ‘We propose to require all advice on the transfer and conversion of safeguarded benefits to include a personal recommendation’.There is further clarification in use of software:‘Adviser firms will be responsible for ensuring the APTA, including the TVC, is undertaken to a sufficient degree to support a suitable recommendation. Advice firms are liablefor the advice even where it is checked by a third party pension transfer specialist. Consequently, advisory firms must make sure that any software used meets their advice needs’.]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[7This is a significant transition period for our industry. The regulator is shifting the goal posts in a constructive way that requires firms to re-purpose their processes to re-centre on the client.Synaptic Analyser has the following attributes:1. Uses a a state-of-the-art cashflowmodelling tool to frame all advice in termsof objectives and strategies2. Illustratefundlongevity,mortalityandimpact of inflation3. Demonstrate sustainable withdrawal rates4. Layerincomefrommultiplepensionsand other sources of income, whether state benefit, property, investments or DB scheme – no need to buy multiple tools5. ‘Redroute’whichcreatesamodelfrom minimum inputs – simply set the slider6. Explorealternativescenarios‘onthefly’from a single web-based view7. Getaccuratequotes,includingReductionin Yield calculations drawing on charges information that is up-to-date and verified by the providersThe 3 principal valuations presented in the Synaptic Analyser dashboard format opposite are:1. Calculationof‘Investmentrequiredfordesired income’2. Maximumachievableincome(fromthepensions in drawdown)3. Maximumannuityincome,takenfromlive provider quotes (as per the APTA requirements, including ability to produce enhanced quotes – essential given that 65% of retirees qualify for enhanced rates).The new look ‘Transfer Value Comparator’ from CP17-16.Example of transfer value comparisonThe transfer value offered instead of your pension income is £120,000.How does this compare with the amount you need to buy the same income on the open market?The notional annuity purchase is being used as a proxy to determine the value that might be gained or lost by giving up the safeguarded benefits.Example given: it could cost you £140,000 to obtain a comparable level of guaranteed income on the open market. This means the same retirement income could cost you £20,000 more by transferring.For further information or to request a trial of the NEW Synaptic Analyser tool please call 0800 783 4477 or email sales@synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[8Busting the mythof ‘U-shaped’ retirement spendingAbraham Okusanya | Principal | FinalytiQIt’s a rather commonly held view that most people spend more earlyin retirement, when they’re active and keen to enjoy their new-found freedom. Then they go into a less active stage where spending declines, only for it to pick up dramatically in later life due to care costs.Sounds logical, right?The trouble is, for the majority of people, this idea of ‘U-shaped’ spending in retirement is but a myth.For some time, researchers have identified an important phenomenon known as the ‘saving puzzle’ – older people keep accumulating assets in retirement and the amount of money they save increases with age!Dr Brancati and her colleagues at theInternational Longevity Center – UKrecently conducted a detailed analysis of two large datasets; the Living Costs and Food Survey, and the English Longitudinal Study of Ageing, to gain insight into income and expenditure patterns of the older population. Their findings are set out in a recent paper titled Understanding Retirement Journeys: Expectations vs reality. The researchers note the absence of the U-shaped spending in retirement...Our findings suggest that typical consumption in retirement does not follow a U-shaped path – consumption does not dramatically rise at the start of retirement or pick up towards the end of life to meetlong-term care related expenditures.At this point it should be noted that our data is restricted to households only and therefore excludes those actively living in care homes who may be paying for it from their remaining assets. Yet we can explore the extent to which care expenditures eat into household budgets across different ages. Analysis of the data suggests that even for the 80+ age group, only a minority (6.4% of households) are putting money towards meeting long-term care needs. This doesn’t mean that U shaped consumptionin retirement is a misnomer, but perhaps implies that it is atypical.As it turns out, spending in retirement actually declines progressively in real terms. As people get older, they spend progressively less!A household headed by someone aged 80 and over spends, on average, 43% (or £131) less than a household headed by a 50-year- old. If we include the amount of money people pay for their mortgage as household expenditure, then the decline becomes even steeper with households headed by someone aged 80+ spending 56.4% less(or £173) than households headed by a 50 year old. Indeed, we calculate that by age 80+, individuals are saving, on average, around £5,870 per year. Figure 3 opposite shows that, from age 65, spending typically declines progressively and is about 35% lower at age 80.Even when researchers split people aged 50+ between top and bottom earners(i.e. people whose income is eitherabove or below the median), the trend remains broadly consistent. People spend progressively less as they get older. However, high earners experience a much faster and steeper decline in spending after age 60 than bottom earners. Indeed, bottom earners have more stable spending patterns throughout their lifetime, and their total expenditure starts to decline only after age 70.The authors concluded that older people spend consistently less than their younger counterparts regardless of their income. This trend is persistent and it’s not a periodic effect.‘Consumption in retirement starts relatively]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[9Researchers have identified an important phenomenon known as the ‘saving puzzle’ – older people keep accumulating assets in retirement and the amount of money they save increases with age!Figure 1. Income and consumption expenditure at different ageshigh and ends low. This pattern is common to both high and low income groups, is robust to the inclusion of factors other than age and is not simply the result of the time period in which the data was collected.’Amazingly, this trend is broadly consistent even whenyou look at segments of people with different lifestyles.The authors note that even the “Extravagant Couples” – those who spend nearly 40% of their total expenditure on recreational goods and services – spend more than their income in the first decade or so of retirement, as do those who are “Just Getting By”, while the “Prudent Families” and “Frugal Foodies” consistently spend below their income over the duration of retirement All of the groups save in later life. From age 75 onwards, even the “Just Getting By” group, which is the lowest income group, starts to save. The savings are the consequence of falling consumption towards the end of life on non-essential items.These findings are consistent with findings in the US, where researchers found that retirement spending tends to decrease by at least 1% a year in real terms throughout retirement!Of course, many people will need care in later life, but this is not typical. Consider the following data from Age UK (2016). • only 16% of people aged 85+ in the UK live in care homes• the median period from admission to the care home todeath is 462 days. (15 months)While it’s important to factor in possible care costs into a retirement income plan, the chances that someone actually ends up having to pay for care are relatively low. In any case, it’s entirely practical for people to rely on their property wealth to meet care costs in later life.So what?The assumption that income withdrawal needs to keepup with inflation throughout the entire retirement periodis not supported by empirical data on spending pattern in retirement. This has a major implication for how we calculate sustainable withdrawal from retirement portfolios. An ideal sustainable withdrawal strategy should follow the typical spending pattern in retirement. This allows higher withdrawal at the early part of retirement and should progressively fall (at least in real terms) over their retirement period.Figure 2. Income and consumption expenditure at different ages - top and bottom earnersFigure 3. Consumption by consumer segmentwww.finalytiq.co.uk | www.twitter.com/AbrahamOnMoney | abraham@finalytiq.co.uk]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[10Platform market update: Regulatory and Due Diligence SmackdownSteve Nelson | Head of research | the lang catThis is my first column for Synaptic Connection so it’s only polite if I say hello and introduce myself. “Hello!” I’ve been a lang cat for over 4 years (which, in human years, must be a lifetime by now?) and while we look at lots of aspects of the finance industry in our team, it’s fair to say we spend the biggest chunk of our time digging around the platform sector in particular.The lang cat is founded on the principleof making the complex simple, punching industry jargon square in the face in the process, and there’s a few phrases that are twisting my undergarments at the moment. I’ll be having a moan about these as we go.Back to platforms. We speak to the platform providers regularly to find out what they’re up to, collecting loads of data in the process on a regular basis. In parallel to this, we also chat to lots advisers about how they’re feeling about this part of the industry, often helping them with their due diligence.(Moan #1, platform selection rather than due diligence please.) More on that later.What’s been happening recently then?So, I’m writing this at what feels like a strangejuncture. In my 15 years in the industry there’s never been both so much and yet so little to talk about in the industry. On the one hand,if regulation is your boat, then there’s beenno shortage of bedtime reading to keep you going in recent months.But let’s spare a thought for proposition developers inside platforms just now. Imagine you’ve got to contend with GDPR, the sequel to MIFID, the implications of the FCA asset management market study and the potential scope of the upcoming platform review. It’s overwhelming enough to make time to read all this legislation, let alone lead and develop a business through this.Looking specifically at the FCA studies, we think a few old friends are about to come into sharp focus once more. Value for money is one but is torturous to define, especially asvalue is something that is experienced by the user, not defined by a regulator, manufacturer or market commentator for that matter. Answers on a postcard.Superclean share classes and the increasing trend towards vertical integration (7 of the top 10 platforms by AUA have a fund manager in the wider group) are others and we’re going to be all over both in the coming months.Little wonder then that when we meet with platforms, we’re hearing a consistent message across the board that development spend is being swallowed up by de minimus changes to meet regulatory obligations. This is a market where innovation is being compromised at the hands of standing still. Leaving shmucks like me without shiny new toys to review.]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11There’s never been both so much and yet so little to talk about in the industry. On the one hand, if regulation is your boat, then there’s been no shortage of bedtime reading to keep you going in recent months.And that’s before you talk about re- platforming, where we estimate that there’s around £800m being spent on in-flight projects with various providers upgrading or moving their kit.(Moan #2. Re-platforming is a horrible phrase. When I buy a new TV I’m not re-tellying. “Yeah love, I’m just off down to the shop to re- mobile,” said no-one ever. Give me ‘Technology upgrade’ or ‘moving to a new tech supplier/ version’ any day thank you very much.)This is all very interesting Steve, but what does this mean to me as an adviser? How do I go about my due dil...sorry...platform selection?Thanks. It’s not all bad news. We hear lots of criticism that platforms are becoming more vanilla – especially with the homogenisation of underlying tech. And in truth, while you can run a decent model portfolio CIP on most platforms, we think that criticism is generally a wee bit unfair. If you go digging then there’s a wider and more interesting variety of choice than initially meets the eye. Off the top of my head (there’s lots that didn’t make the cut here) you have:• Platforms like Nucleus, James Hay and Transact, who adhere closely to the original idea of what a platform was meant to be. Independent and investment agnostic – arguably leaving you more in control of your client proposition• Taking that one step further we’re seeing increased demand for the black-box enabling model from the likes of SEI, IFDS and Pershing• Towards the other end of the spectrum you have the likes of Standard Life and Zurich who are up there in terms of having the fullest propositions in terms of end to end functionality, tooling and support.• If your investment proposition favours a significant ETI component than platforms like Ascentric, Alliance Trust Savings, AJ Bell who have in-house dealing desks and as a result, fuller integrated trading capability.• And from an end-customer perspective, you have platforms like Seven IM andTrue Potential who do great work from a reporting perspective that sticks out a mile from their peers.But that’s all very high level, I want some practical help?Fair enough. We’ll end on some tips that we’ve picked up along the way when helping advisers with platform selection exercises:• The extremely patronising (sorry) but important one. Understand your own business model and what you need from a platform. For example, if you want to own your own tooling (i.e. risk profiling, CGT) proposition, then consider whether you need all the bells and whistles of some platforms - especially if those platforms are more expensive.• The exercise should be repeated for each of your client segments. One platform might be suitable across multiple segments but there’s a decent chance it wont.• Price isn’t everything. Something cheap and rubbish is still rubbish. You should see the first car I bought.• It’s a complex decision and it deservesto be treated as such. Be very, very waryof narrow metrics and flawed ratings. Profitability is a good example here. It can be a good proxy for business performance but only if understood correctly. For many platforms there simply isn’t a set of report and accounts that can be attributed solely to platform revenue and expenditure.• Make use of the information that’s already out there. *Advertising Klaxon* The lang cat has a free platform directory on our website. There’s lots of other tools and resources out there too.• You don’t need to ask every platform a matrix of several hundred questions (we’ve seen this). Consider the practicalities of what you’re going to do with all that data. Especially with all the regulation you’ve got to read!• If you go down an RFI question set then think very, very carefully about what you ask. If you ask 20 providers, “Are you committedto the UK market?” don’t be surprised if you get 20 answers that say “Yes”. Ask about the stuff that really matters to you as a business and be really specific in line with your business objectives.If you have any more, we’d love to hear your thoughts. Been nice meeting you.Visit www.langcatfinancial.co.uk for more from Steve and the rest of the lang cats.]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12Fact or myth?Justin Onuekwusi CFA | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementIt is clear that both active and passive investments both have a role to play in portfolios. However, as the active versus passive debate rolls on, there are many myths on both sides about the advantages of one over the other. We look to dismiss some of these myths so investors can focus on the facts.Figure 1: United Kingdom2017 marks the ten-year anniversary of the beginning of the global financial crisis; a time when all investors could see was the ‘goldilocks economy’ and very few were concerned about the bears coming home. Fast forward to now and we are becoming more concerned that this exuberance is creeping back into markets. High equity valuations, structurally low bond yields and the continued spectre of political risk all present investors with real dilemmas. This has coincided with the growing popularity of index funds. Much of this popularity has been driven by the average active manager underperforming their respective benchmark. Many investors fear that recent index fund outperformance of actively managed fundsis a function of upward trending markets and that if we see a correction or downturn in markets, active managers will come to the fore by boosting cash levels or allocating more to defensive stocks. Fact or Myth? We took a look back at every negative year for the IA equity sectors since the year 2000 and then reviewed how the average manager performed versus a comparative index.Active managers underperform in two out of three observationsFirstly, looking at the UK market, the average UK equity fund has actually outperformed the FTSE All Share index since the year 2000. Many point to the mid-cap bias of the majority of active managers in the sector as the reason for this extended period of strong returns.However, what about when the average manager delivered a negative return? The results are close but the median fund manager underperformed in two out of three downturns, only beating the index when the dot-com bubble burst.]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[13Figure 2: United StatesFigure 3: Emerging MarketActive managers underperform is four out of four observationsThe US market is seen as a poster child for index investing; thought to be one of the most efficient markets available to investors and therefore one of the hardest to beat. Unlike the UK market, there is clearly no contest here between the performance of active fundsand the S&P 500. In every single instance ofa negative return from the average manager in the IA North America sector, the index outperforms the median fund manager, often by a clear margin as shown in the global financial crisis and during the euro crisis.Finally, emerging markets equities – an asset class where it is often claimed that active managers should be able to add value. In contrast to the US, this is understood to be an extremely inefficient market, one which provides plenty of opportunities for nimble active managers with an informational advantage or the ability to identify mispriced stocks. However, this intuitive understanding misses a crucial aspect. The greater an opportunity for an accomplished activefund manager to outperform, there is an equally large chance that an unskilled, or perhaps just plain unlucky, fund managerwill underperform. With this in mind, Figure3 showing the average active manager inthe IA Global EM sector underperforms the index across each period is less surprising than previously thought.Active managers underperform is five out of five observations. The active/passive debate rumbles on.There you have it! The average active manager underperforms 11 out of our 12 annual observations. So, when it comesto the myth that active managers deliver superior performance than their benchmarks on the downside, that can well and trulybe debunked- at least looking at the three markets above. The active/passive debate will undoubtedly continue with each side often taking pot shots at the other. Here it should be noted we have specifically looked at active managers versus a comparative index (the benchmark), and not versus index funds, which of course will bear their own charges. Ultimately, there are managers who can outperform their index but the investors needs to decide whether it is worth paying the extra fees for the potential alpha a fund manager may or may not bring.Multi-index investing: Keep active with index-like costsWithin the LGIM Multi-Index funds, we believe in having the best of both worlds. Our active management of the asset allocation allows us to dynamically adjust the portfolio to respond to the ever-changing market environment. During anticipated periods of market weakness, we would look to de-risk the funds at opportune times, thanks to our assessment of the economic cycle, valuations and a range of systemic risks.Using predominantly index funds as portfolio building blocks means that we can pass on those cost savings to investors as well as benefit from the advantages of diversification. Yet, even Multi- Index does choose to invest in actively managed building blocks in some cases if it is the only way to get access to an asset class, or if that asset class lends itself more to active management.Offering a range of risk-targeted funds to suit the needs of any investor, we look to use every tool available to protect investors’ capital during the next potential downturn in markets.For further information about our Multi-Index fund range:0345 070 8684* fundsales@lgim.com lgim.comImportant NoticeThis is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income from them can fall as well as rise, is not guaranteed and your clients may get back less than they invest. *Call charges will vary and calls will be monitored and recorded. Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 1009418. Registered office: One Coleman Street, London EC2R 5AA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[14RISKConquering Risk: Do you know your Attitude to Risk from your Capacity for Loss?Eric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedWe look at this most important point of due diligence when considering suitability and risk, and why so many advisers struggle to perform the necessary due diligence. Experts are warning that January 2018 will be the deadline for getting your house in order in regards to risk profiling and the ‘use of tools’, as this is the date that the MiFID II legislation comes into effect.The Finalised Guidance document of 2011: ‘Assessing suitability: Establishing the riska customer is willing and able to take and making a suitable investment selection’ set out the rules. Here the primacy of a client’s investment objectives was established, and the importance of linking objectivesto appropriate risk-based strategies. It isa complex area, but these are essential concepts, and luckily they really work when put into practice.It is the responsibility of the adviser to ensure that ‘the client is able financially to bear any related investment risks consistent with their investment objectives’. Moreover, the adviser must ensure that the client has the ‘necessary experience and knowledge to understand the risks involved’.Here’s the punch line: the ‘route by which this key assessment is made is through the ability to assess a client’s ‘Capacity for Loss’.Many, if not most, complaints are upheld on the basis of whether a client’s risk exposure was suitable or not, based on their ‘Capacity for Loss’ (perversely in some cases, even when a client has done well).If this assessment is so important, where is it falling down for so many advisers?Thematic work has highlighted the poor use of tools, the lack of proof of suitability and failure to gain ‘informed consent’ around the risk inherent in the investment strategy recommended.Many advisers are conflating the outputs from their Attitude to Risk Questionnaire with their fuller consideration of the client’scircumstances. Capacity for Loss is different to the assessment provided by the questionnaire. It is an objective evaluation of the extent of losses that can be sustained before there is a ‘material impact on standard of living’.Simply asking a client to confirm their Capacity for Loss will not work, as it not a subjective response that is required. It requires the skill and objectivity of an adviser, whowill balance what he or she knows about the client and their objectives, to recommend an investment strategy within their capacity to sustain possible losses.It also underlines why research and recommendations must be ‘personalised’. The wrong approach is to say: ‘The questionnaire says you’re balanced and you get portfolio5.’ Evidence of this truncated approach being used appears regularly in the trade press,]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[RISK15If this assessment is so important, where is it falling down for so many advisers?either in the many laments from the regulator following their review of files, but equally from practitioners who struggle to accept the limitations of these techniques, and in doing so fail to gasp their benefits.As providers of best advice tools, we get the equivalent challenge: ‘The questionnaire says 3, and the investment I want to propose isa 4. How do I get around this?’ The correct answer of course is ‘Let’s look first at the client’s objectives for this investment, assess their Capacity for Loss and see which strategy is appropriate’.A further pointer to success in our quest is in the nuanced wisdom that has always been present in the Finalised Guidance, that you cannot successfully match an investment recommendation with a client without credible research that quantifies potential loss. This shows us the real reason why so many advisers fail the proof of suitabilitytest – they can’t actually provide a consistent projection that quantifies possible loss = leaving them hanging. They could say ‘In the great depression of 2008, representing the maximum drawdown for this strategy, we saw a loss of 15%’. This is going to prove difficult with investments that will have evolvedin terms of construction and themes, and contain funds whose track records may not even extend further than a year or two. You need a much more circumspect approach.We at Synaptic believe that Moody’s Analytics are the greatest experts in meeting this mathematical challenge, which is why we have built our risk ratings on their model, rather than the ‘qualitative’ assessment offered by our competitors. In our toolsand when we publish our risk ratings, we include the regularly updated, stochastically forecasted loss that is expected in a bad year for that investment or portfolio. That gives the adviser a consistent research-based measure to back up their consideration of Capacityfor Loss, and the means of setting the client’s expectations. In doing so, the adviser will have avoided many of the pitfalls that improper use of tools presents.Capacity for Loss quotient highlighted: illustration shows graph from Synaptic Modeller with the likely portfolio loss in a (5% or 1 in 20) ‘bad year’. This calculation identifies this investment as an ‘adventurous’ strategy.Easy access to the Synaptic Risk RatingsSynaptic Product and Fund users can now access the full table of Synaptic Risk Ratings within the Investments tab of the research tool. This means that up to 8,000 Synaptic subscribers can use the risk ratings and risk factsheets as part of their due diligence.If you do not already have access to the Attitude to Risk Questionnaire (ATRQ) that maps to these risk ratings, then call us on 0800 783 4477 and we’ll arrange it straight away at no cost.]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[MAF I MAF II MAF III MAF IV MAF VCautious MPSIncome MPSBalanced MPSGrowth MPSGlobal Equity MPS Cautious Passive+ Income Passive+ Balanced Passive+ Growth Passive+ Global Equity Passive+Carmignac Portfolio SécuritéCarmignac Portfolio Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Capital Plus Carmignac Portfolio Commodities Carmignac Portfolio Emergents Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Entrepreneurs Carmignac Portfolio Capital Cube Carmignac Portfolio Investissement Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Discovery Carmignac Portfolio Emerging Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Grande Europe Carmignac Portfolio Euro-Patrimoine Carmignac Portfolio Global BondF&C MM Lifestyle FoundationF&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) F&C MM Navigator Distribution F&C MM Navigator ModerateF&C MM Navigator ProgressiveF&C MM Navigator SelectF&C MM Navigator BoutiquesCF Canlife Portfolio III CF Canlife Portfolio IV CF Canlife Portfolio V CF Canlife Portfolio VI CF Canlife Portfolio VII Canlife Portfolio 3 Canlife Portfolio 4 Canlife Portfolio 5 Canlife Portfolio 6 Canlife Portfolio 7CF Canlife Managed 0%-35% Canlife Managed 0%-35%]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Dynamic Passive 1 Dynamic Passive 2 Dynamic Passive 3 Dynamic Passive 4 Dynamic Passive 5Close Bond Income Portfolio FundClose Managed Income FundClose Managed Conservative FundClose Managed Balanced FundClose Managed Growth FundClose Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund Close DMS Income PlusClose DMS ConservativeClose DMS BalancedClose DMS GrowthClose Diversified Income Portfolio Fund Close Conservative Portfolio Fund Close Balanced Portfolio FundClose Growth Portfolio FundMulti Manager Income 1 Multi Manager Income 2 Multi Manager Income 3 Multi Manager Income 4 Multi Manager Income 5 Multi Manager Total Return 1 Multi Manager Total Return 2 Multi Manager Total Return 3 Multi Manager Total Return 4 Multi Manager Total Return 5Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios Hawksmoor Model Portfolios MI Hawksmoor VanbrughMI Hawksmoor DistributionDefensive Cautious Balanced Growth Aggressive DistributionDynamic PassiveMulti ManagerAccess the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-riskDiversified Income FundDiversified Growth FundMAPInvestec Global Multi-Asset Total Return Fund Investec Cautious Managed Fund]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Multi-Index Income 6OM Generation 3OM Generation 4OM Generation 5OM Cirilium Conservative Fund OM Cirilium Balanced Fund OM Cirilium Moderate Fund OM Cirilium Dynamic Fund OM Cirilium Adventurous Fund Creation Conservative Creation BalancedCreation Moderate Creation Dynamic Creation AdventurousFlexible Guaranteed Funds Balanced Flexible Guaranteed Funds Cautious Flexible Guaranteed Managed GrowthMP3 MP50 MP4 MP5 MP6 MP7Adventurous Portfolio Income Seeker Portfolio Growth Seeker Portfolio Income Focus Portfolio Temperate Portfolio Growth Focus Portfolio Lower Risk Income Portfolio Lower Risk Growth Portfolio Protective PortfolioBalanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousCautiousModerately CautiousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Premier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income PortfolioPremier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced PortfolioPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth PortfolioPremier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth PortfolioPruFund CautiousPruFund Protected Cautious PruFund GrowthPruFund Protected Growth PruFund 0-30PruFund 10-40PruFund 20-55PruFund 40-80Dynamic 0-30Dynamic 10-40Dynamic 20-55Dynamic 40-80Dynamic 60-100WP Optimum Return Focused 0-30Focused 10-40Focused 20-55Focused 40-80Focused 60-100Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market FundPremier Defensive Growth FundPremier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund Premier Diversified FundPremier Liberation IV FundPremier Liberation V FundPremier Liberation VI FundPremier Liberation VII FundMPS Global Growth MPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global Income MPS IncomeMPS ConservativeMPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)PortfoliosFunds]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[BespokeStrategy 1 Strategy 2 Strategy 3 Strategy 4 Strategy 5 Strategy 6Managed PortfoliosCautious Balanced Income Balanced Plus EquityEquity PlusRMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic IncomeMulti AssetRL Governed Portfolio 1 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 7 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 (s) RL GRIP 1RL GRIP 2 RL GRIP 3 RL GRIP 4 RL GRIP 5Russell Secure PortfolioRussell Cautious PortfolioRussell Conservative PortfolioRussell Moderate PortfolioRussell Balanced PortfolioRussell Progressive PortfolioRussell Adventurous PortfolioRussell Growth PortfolioRussell Aggressive PortfolioRussell Aggressive PlusRussell Defensive Assets FundRussell Investments Real Assets Fund Russell Investments UK GrowthRussell Investments International Growth Russell Investments MA Growth 1 Russell Investments MA Growth 2 Russell Investments MA Growth 3 Russell Investments MA Growth 4 Russell Investments MA Growth 5 Russell Investments MA Income]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive PortfolioPositive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus PortfolioPension Portfolio 1 Pension Portfolio 2 Pension Portfolio 3 Pension Portfolio A Pension Portfolio B Pension Portfolio 4 Pension Portfolio C Pension Portfolio 5 Premier Pension Portfolio 1 Premier Pension Portfolio 2 Premier Pension Portfolio 3 Premier Pension Portfolio A Premier Pension Portfolio B Premier Pension Portfolio 4 Premier Pension Portfolio C Premier Pension Portfolio 5Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder Schroder SchroderMM DiversityMM Diversity Balanced MM Diversity IncomeMM Diversity Tactical MM InternationalMM UK GrowthMixed Distribution Fund Global Multi Asset Income Dynamic Multi Asset Managed BalancedCautiousModerately CautiousBalancedModerately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset AllocationCautiousIncomeModerately Cautious BalancedModerately Adventurous AdventurousPersonal Injury]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ACUMEN Bond Portfolio ACUMEN Conservative Portfolio ACUMEN Income Portfolio ACUMEN Progressive Portfolio ACUMEN Adventurous Portfolio ACUMEN Equity Portfolio ACUMEN Strategic Portfolio Tavistock PB PROFILE 3 Tavistock PB PROFILE 4 Tavistock PB PROFILE 5 Tavistock PB PROFILE 6 Tavistock PB PROFILE 7 Tavistock PB PROFILE 8 Tavistock PB IncomeTavistock PROFILE 3Tavistock PROFILE 4Tavistock PROFILE 5Tavistock PROFILE 6Tavistock PROFILE 7Tavistock PROFILE 8Thesis Optima Income Thesis Optima Balanced Thesis Optima Growth Thesis Collectives 1 of 7 Thesis Collectives 2 of 7 Thesis Securities 3 of 7 Thesis Securities 4 of 7 Thesis Securities 5 of 7 Thesis Securities 6 of 7 Thesis Securities 7 of 7Commercial Freehold FundVanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[FP Verbatim Portfolio 3FP Verbatim Portfolio 4FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth FP Verbatim Portfolio 6FP Verbatim Portfolio 7FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 IncomeRSM Model Portfolio 2 RSM Model Portfolio 3 RSM Model Portfolio 4 RSM Model Portfolio 5 RSM Model Portfolio 6 RSM Model Portfolio 7 RSM Model Portfolio 8 RSM Model Portfolio 9 RSM Model Portfolio 10Total Clarity Portfolio 3 Total Clarity Portfolio 4 Total Clarity Portfolio 5 Total Clarity Portfolio 6VDSJH3 VDSJH4 VDSJH5 VDSJH6 VDSJH7 VDSJH8 VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS RSMR VDS TCF 3 VDS TCF 4 VDS TCF 5 VDS TCF 6 VDS TCF 7 VDS TCF 8 VDS S&W 3 VDS S&W 4 VDS S&W 5 VDS S&W 6 VDS S&W 7 VDS S&W 8 VDSHR3 VDSHR4 VDSHR5 VDSHR6 VDSHR7 VDSHR8PortfoliosVDSRSMR2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10Total Clarity(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further information before recommending.About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24Invest for retirement income and avoid the pitfallsIain McGowan | Head of Fund Proposition | Scottish WidowsInvesting for growth or income?The basic retirement decision for most people was relatively straightforward in the pre-pension freedoms era. Buy an annuity with your pension pot or receive a defined benefit pension and look forward to a regular income until you die. Pension freedoms changed all this. Clients now have more flexibility and choice, but there’s a potential downside too – complexity.Taking income – the client conundrumWhile greater flexibility and access is nowon offer, security of income remains high on the list of priorities. The risk of running out of money has increased for many people since the Government removed safeguards like compulsory withdrawal (known as GAD) limits.Annuities may be unpopular, but the only way to have income certainty for life is to buy one – or another type of guaranteed product.For those who want flexibility and continue to remain invested, there isn’t a magic solution that delivers security of income.What this means for advisersAdvisers have started to consider implementing Centralised Retirement Propositions (CRPs) that are distinct from the Centralised Investment Propositions (CIPs) used for accumulating clients. A one-size- fits-all approach is unlikely to be suitable, so a range of CRP investment solutions for different clients is appropriate.A CRP should be clearly aligned to different client segments, with appropriate investment choices and strategies depending on their wealth and needs. Retirement income planning and advice is complex and arguably the stakes are higher than for clients in accumulation.A CRP is not just about choosing a suitable range of investments. The framework alsoincludes the factfind process and clearly understanding the client’s objectives. This will help identify the key risks personal to the client, and will shape a suitable retirement income strategy.Threats to retirement incomeThe main risk is your client running out of money accounting for longevity, investment choice, their withdrawal strategy and any plans to leave a legacy.But making sure this doesn’t happen isn’t simple.As a financial adviser, you will understand the potentially devastating impact that might arise from the sequence of returns on a client’s investments. This risk arises when losses are]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[25For those who want flexibility and continue to remain invested, there isn’t a magic solution that delivers security of income.locked in due to the same level of income being taken from a portfolio even as it declines in value as a result of market volatility or weak investment returns. This is particularly acute in theearlystagesofretirement.Yourchallenge is to help your client understand this risk and enable them to mitigate it.Reduce retirement income riskDecide on the investment philosophy – total return vs natural incomeConsider whether a client’s income should come from:• natural income (the client doesn’t touch their capital); or• the total return of their investments (their income comes from their capital and any investment return).For clients with enough income from other sources, investing for and spending natural income is a viable option for discretionary spend.But natural income may not be sufficient for clients with more modestly sized pots. The unpredictable income level delivered and the investment risk they may need to take to generate enough income may make this strategy unrealistic.For these clients a total return approach, where the income is derived from a combination of income and capital, is likely to be required.Get the withdrawal strategy rightThere are several withdrawal approaches you can take – or combine – to reduce income risk. Suitability depends on individual client circumstances.• Come up with a sustainable withdrawal rate combined with a complementary investment strategy.• Be flexible with the amount of income the clienttakes,dependingonreturns.Youcould agree a cap on the amount they’ll take and, achieve this by not adjusting for inflation, limiting lump sum withdrawals or reducing the amount of regular withdrawals.• Consider a multi-pot strategy to manage income withdrawals across the short, medium and long term.1. Keep enough in cash to take income for an agreed time period (perhapsup to two years) so the client doesn’t have to draw down from their portfolio if markets drop. The downside is that lower returns can bring down the overall portfolio return.2. Ring fence the next three to five years’ income in a low risk stable asset.3. For longer term income needs that may demand longer term growth, invest in a well-diversified risk-rated investment solution such as a multi- asset fund.Perhaps the most important element is the client review. You’ll be well used to doing this with clients building their pots. But when they retire, it becomes essential in managing risk.Choose your investment structure – diversify through multi-asset investingA well-diversified portfolio is an effective way to shield clients from the effects of stock market volatility. You can achieve diversification in a number of ways – suchas single multi-asset funds, selecting a fund panel to choose from, model portfolios and discretionary managed solutions. It all depends on the client and your advice proposition.Diversificationdoesn’tremovetheissueof sequence risk, but it can help to reduce the effect on the portfolio when there’s a market downturn by reducing downside volatility as a withdrawal is made.For many advisers, using straightforward risk-rated multi-asset funds can offer clientsan easy, relatively low cost way to achieve diversification and improve the risk: return ratio. Diversification could go beyond the traditional bonds and equities split and offer exposure to different asset classes, geographies, liquidity, value and other criteria.High demand for multi-asset solutions continues to drive innovation and reduce costs in this space.In the Scottish Widows multi-asset Premier Range for example, strategies such as smart beta equity management and absolute return strategies increase diversification and potentially reduce volatility as a result.In summaryThe reality for clients and advisers is that investing in retirement can be a risky business.There’s no magic solution; but if you offer clients quality financial planning that considers the risks and solutions highlighted in this article, you can help clients achieve a comfortable retirement, and potentially leave a legacy too.For further information please visit:www.scottishwidows.co.uk/extranet/index]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26Not all income is created equalDavid Palmer | Fund Manager | Sarasin & Partners LLPDavid Palmer is the appointed Fund Manager for the Verbatim’s Portfolio 5 Income Fund, where he is tasked with finding quarterly income, whilst pursuing capital growth in the medium to long term.In the diverse, bewildering world of equities, dividends are popularly seen as a reassuring mark of resilience and stability. Dividends indicate healthy free cash flow; the keyinput into a company’s discounted cashflow valuation, and the ultimate financial purpose of any equity investment. Regular cash payments are easy to understand compared to the esoteric world of share prices themselves, which can meander in response to an enormous array of considerations, some of which are logical, some not.The market equates dividends with financial strength, and dividend paying stocks provide an income stream capable of meeting the owners’ liabilities. In a world of abnormally low interest rates, where yield is so hardto come by, this is an ever more useful financial trait.It is also true that, over the long term, dividends are a key determinant of equity returns. In the UK market, for example,over four fifths of the equity market’s real return since 1900 has come from reinvested dividends. In the US since 1927, higher yielding stocks have outperformed zero yielding stocksby 2.8% per annum; an enormous quantum when compounded over a long period.By focusing on yield, one is therefore fishing in the right pond. Not only do dividends compound at a healthy rate over the long term, but by omitting stocks without them we also avoid the worst speculative excesses of the markets. Very few dotcom stocks, for example, paid any dividends.Bigger is not always betterThere is need for caution, however: while a high dividend yield can be the sign of a solid company throwing off more cash than it can use, a figure that is too high should give pause for thought. The maxim that ‘if something appears too good to be true, it probably is’ has enormous validity in the world of investment. Caveat emptor. Investors are justifiably suspicious of high-yield bonds (which are often labelled ‘junk’ for a reason) but are attracted to the supposed safety of high income equities. This is an inconsistent and illogical reaction. After all, dividends are only paid to shareholders after bondholders have received their interest.A very high yield can be a sign that the company is under financial stress, and may be forced to cut its dividend – generallyan atrocious outcome for the owner. Furthermore, when we dissect the equity market, some of the highest yielding sectors are those normally associated with the highest risk, or the lowest quality.Telecoms, financials, oils and utilities are some of the most verdant areas of the market for yield, yet each of these sectors faces some profound issues. Telecoms are capital hungry, heavily regulated businesses, with a poor record of value creation. Banks are highly levered and have an unfortunate habit of periodically flirting with bankruptcy. Oil companies not only depend for their prosperity on a volatile and unpredictable commodity price, they also face huge operational risks (think about BP’s Macondo disaster, the bill for which is $47billion and counting) and, longer term, the riskof decarbonisation. Ditto utilities, whose coal and gas powered assets may be of little relevance in a world pivoting to renewable energy.]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[27In the UK market, for example, over four fifths of the equity market’s real return since 1900 has come from reinvested dividends.At the front of our mind is the truism that equities are long term assets, and thatthe bulk of their value is typically derived from cash flows expected to be generated well into the future. We therefore look for businesses and management teams that share our principles, and determinedly seek to build resilience. Are they prudent and sufficiently long-term in their outlook? Are they appropriately incentivised to ensure the perennial success of the business? Are the issues they face manageable at all, or is the business a structural short?Ask the right questionsIt is therefore critical that we individually assess the resilience of each company in which we invest to ensure that the dividend can continue to be paid, and preferably grow, ideally into perpetuity. There is a lengthy quantitative and qualitative financial checklist to ensure that any higher income stock has a sustainable yield. Is the dividend well covered by free cash flow? Is the balance sheet strong, with any leverage appropriate to the risks of the business? Does the underlying leverage differ markedly from that which the company reports? Are there other claims on cash flows from bond holders, pension funds etc., that come before equity owners in the capital structure? Are capital expenditures sufficient to ensure the business is nourished for future prosperity? Is the competitive environment manageable?At the front of our mind is the truism that equities are long term assets, and thatthe bulk of their value is typically derived from cash flows expected to be generated well into the future. We therefore look for businesses and management teams that share our principles, and determinedly seek to build resilience. Are they prudent andsufficiently long-term in their outlook? Are they appropriately incentivised to ensure the perennial success of the business? Are the issues they face manageable at all, or is the business a structural short?A quality companyAn example of a sound dividend payeris National Grid, playing a vital role in connecting millions of people to the energy they use, safely, reliably and efficiently. It aims to be a low risk business focused on generating shareholder value though both dividends and asset growth by investing in essential infrastructure under predominantly regulated market conditions with a balance of activities both in the UK and the USA.The Company presents the UK government with the ability to offer a flexible solutionto increasing renewable sources of energy generation, whilst keeping its element of household bills as low as possible. Growthof about 5% per annum in its UK RAB [Regulated Asset Base] is secure through to 2021, whilst dependent upon the level of energy decarbonisation the country achieves. In the USA, where National Grid negotiates returns with individual state regulators, there is a fresh focus on increasing investment in infrastructure and this is positive.The company has a regular dividend yield of 4.0%, and the dividend growth policy is linked to the UK Retail Price Index (RPI). In 2017 the dividend increased by 2.1% in line with UK RPI, and with inflation beginning to raise its head, this has the potential to grow further over the coming years.National Grid is committed to returning £4 billion to shareholders from the proceeds resulting from the sale of a 61% stake in its UK Gas Distribution business. Of this £3.2 billion has been paid as a special dividend andthe remainder will be delivered through share ‘buybacks.’This is the kind of company that we favour: one that doesn’t simply pay a high dividend yield, but offers a sustainable yield that can grow and deliver reliable returns over the long-term.This document is for investment professionals only and should not be relied upon by private investors.This document has been issued by Sarasin & Partners LLPwhich is a limited liability partnership registered in England and Wales with registered number OC329859 and is authorised and regulated by the UK Financial Conduct Authority and passported under MiFID to provide investment services in the Republic of Ireland. It has been prepared solely for information purposes and is not a solicitation, or an offer to buy or sell any security. The information on which the document is based has been obtained from sources that we believe to be reliable, and in good faith, but we have not independently verified such information and we make no representation or warranty, express or implied, as to their accuracy. All expressions of opinion are subject to change without notice.Please note that the prices of shares and the income from them can fall as well as rise and you may not get back the amount originally invested. This can be as a result of market movements and also of variations in the exchange rates between currencies. Past performance is not a guide to future returns and may not be repeated.Neither Sarasin & Partners LLP nor any other member of theBank J. Safra Sarasin group accepts any liability or responsibility whatsoever for any consequential loss of any kind arising outof the use of this document or any part of its contents. The useof this document should not be regarded as a substitute for the exercise by the recipient of his or her own judgment. Sarasin & Partners LLP and/or any person connected with it may act upon or make use of the material referred to herein and/or any of the information upon which it is based, prior to publication of this document. If you are a private investor you should not rely on this document but should contact your professional adviser.© 2017 Sarasin & Partners LLP – all rights reserved. This document can only be distributed or reproduced with permission from Sarasin & Partners LLP.]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[28The time has come for an “all-in” feeBenRaven | Director | TavistockWealthThe FCA confirmed in July it will introduce an all-in fee for the fund management industry.What the regulator wantsThe FCA wants to improve transparency and address “weak” price competition within the industry. A “standardised template of costs and charges” will be introduced and significantly, this template will include an estimate of transaction charges. Transaction charges do NOT currently have to be included in the Ongoing Charges Figure (OCF) published by fund managers, and this leads to an incredibly misleading representation of the true costof owning a fund for a 12-month period.For more information about how much these additional transaction charges can amount to, you can read our blog “Active Funds; why does nobody mention trading charges?” (blog.tavistockwealth.com):The issue is that an OCF represents the tipof the proverbial ice-berg. An active fund manager, in their quest to outperforma benchmark, must place a number of successful trades over time. Identifying these trades and recognising the right time to place them, are only two parts of the puzzle. Once an active manager decidesto place a trade they must incur a cost for doing so. This cost may come in the form ofa bid/offer spread, a brokerage fee or paying duties if purchasing an equity. Whatever the guise, an active manager must pay a cost when entering into every trade. To make matters worse, they must incur a further cost when exiting every trade. Therefore, if we make the (big) assumption that the average trade is successful, it must be successful enough to absorb two rounds of tradingcosts before it breaks-even for the fund. This is the best case scenario and by no means guarantees a significant contribution to fund performance.One study, which aims to shine light on the “invisible costs” of active fund management, looks at 1,758 equity funds around the globe. The study concludes that trading costs have a negative impact on performance and are, on average, larger than the expense ratios quoted by the active fund managers. Across the sample of funds, the average OCF was in the region of 1% with the average trading costs stated as an additional 1.44% per annum. For small-cap funds it was as high as 3.17% per annum. To be clear, these trading costs come in addition to the OCF published by active fund managers.The FCA has concluded that neither active nor passive funds outperform their benchmarks after their (all-in) costs and has found examples of “poor value for money products” in both active and passive strategies.]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[29The FCA wants to improve transparency and address “weak” price competition within the industry. A “standardised template of costs and charges” will be introduced and significantly, this template will include an estimate of transaction charges.Why they want itThe FCA has concluded that neitheractive nor passive funds outperform their benchmarks after their (all-in) costs and has found examples of “poor value for money products” in both active and passive strategies. Going hand in hand with this is the FCA’s reiterated concern that investor “awareness and focus on charges is mixed and often poor” and that there are a “significant number of retail investors who are not aware” of all the charges they pay for their asset management service.What will happen to fund managersFund managers who have historically included the bare minimum within their OCFs will now need to include an estimate for transaction charges. This will result in drastic increases in the average manager’s OCF. Our research shows us that an average OCF for a traditional active managerwill be in the region of 1% however the average trading charges on top of this can be as high as an additional 1.5% (see our aforementioned blog on trading charges). Therefore, some managers will be forced to publish a new OCF that is more than twice as high as their previous one (2.5% vs 1%).Tavistock’s Approachwould typically associate with a traditional active manager. Even when trades are placed, within an OEIC these trades are carried out in a fund structure which does not expose clients to significant additional transaction charges.We have always quoted our OCF inclusive of the underlying ETFs, the cost of currency hedging those ETFs, our Annual Management Charge, all necessary operating expenses and the running costs of the OEIC structure. Consequently, we believe our ACUMEN range to be amongst the most reliable methods of providing the “all-in” fee that the regulator is looking for.For more information about Tavistock Wealth:blog.tavistockwealth.com tavistockwealth.com linkedin.com/company/tavistock-wealthSource of data: Shedding light on ‘invisible’ costs: trading costs and mutual fund performance. Roger Edelen, Richard Evans, Gregory Kadlec.OCF Trading ChargesOCF (Fixed Costs Only) 1%OCF + Variable Costs (e.g. Trading) 1.00%1.44%3%2%1%0%What are clients actually paying?OCF (Fixed Costs Only) OCF + Variable Costs (e.g. Trading)Since inception Tavistock Wealth have constructed our flagship ACUMEN Portfolio range in the most cost and tax efficient manner possible. Our strategy is to actively trade a basket of ETFs and this is done via a UCITS compliant Open-Ended Investment Company (OEIC) fund structure. From an ETF perspective, the OEIC structure means investors are exempt from CGT upon rebalancing the portfolio, exempt from stamp duty within the portfolio and are also immune to any dealing costs involved with purchasing ETFs directly through a platform (which can vary enormously dependingon the platform). Our asset allocation is based on decades worth of backward and forward-looking data, and as such is not subject to the level of trading that one]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[30Page needs logo and brand colVolatility targeting: a cautionary taleThomas Wells CFA® | Fund Manager | Aviva InvestorsMulti-asset solutions should avoid blindly targeting volatility and instead deploy a robust process for portfolio construction. Thomas Wells, Fund Manager of the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund Range, explains the dangers of using volatility as your only measure of risk.Have any of your clients expressed concerns that their portfolio is too volatile? It would seem improbable. This is because from a client’s perspective, risk is losing money and not the volatility of returns. Despite this, the finance industry is fixated with using volatility as a measure of risk to the extent that the terms volatility and risk are used interchangeably.What are the pitfalls of volatility?• Volatility fluctuates over timeThis can be particularly problematic for portfolio managers who target a certain level of volatility. For example, a fund targeting20% volatility in 2011 would translate to a portfolio consisting of 100% global equity. Fast forward to 2017 and to achieve the same level of volatility, the portfolio manager would have to either leverage the portfolio or increase exposure to more volatile and risky assets.• Arbitrary volatility targets can lead investors down a dangerous roadDuring low volatile periods, such as now, portfolio managers would have to add extrarisks in order to achieve an arbitrary volatility target. When a period of market distress materialises, investors could lose more money than anticipated as portfolio managers are forced to sell risky assets in a declining market.Are we in a high risk or low risk environment?The majority of our investors perceive current market risk to be above average. This is hardly surprising given the busy political calendar in Europe and the uncertainties that surround thecurrent US presidency. Yet when you look at volatility, it tells a very different story.What does this mean for volatility measurements?The graph below shows volatility across global equities is currently at unusually low levels, in fact one of the lowest points in the last ten years.Source: Bloomberg as at 28 February 2017. Rolling 3yr monthly volatility of MSCI AC Wold Index (GBP).o]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours31The finance industry is fixated with using volatility as a measure of risk to the extent that the terms volatility and risk are used interchangeably.Key TakeawaysSource: Bloomberg as at 28 February 2017. Rolling 3yr monthly volatility of MSCI AC Wold Index (GBP).• ••Volatility is not necessarily a very good measure of risk, especially in isolation.There are pitfalls to blindly targeting an absolute level of volatility as a means of managing risk.Portfolio construction is important for delivering consistent client outcomes.The only way to reconcile this difference between investors’ perception of ‘above average’ risk and the unusually low levels of volatility we are currently experiencing is by recognising that volatility is not a very good measure of risk.If we look at 2007, this was another period where volatility was at an unusually low level. This was prior to the global financial crisis. While we do not believe this is an indication that we are at the point of the next financial crisis, it does teach us a useful lesson: volatility is not a very good forward indicator of risk.As you can see in the above graph, volatility increased at the same time as equity markets sold-off during the crisis. By blindly targeting volatility as a means of managing risk in your portfolio you would not have had time to de- risk your portfolio before the equity markets sold-off.The importance of portfolio constructionRather than narrowly focus on volatility, we believe at the heart of any successful multi- asset solution is a robust portfolio construction process. For the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund Range, we focus on three key elements: Strategic, Tactical and Implementation.• Strategic asset allocationThis is where we create our long-term portfolios that are aligned to client risk profiles. We use longer term volatility and correlation measures which are more stable.We also believe in the merits of investing ona global basis to enhance risk-adjusted returns and help diversify the portfolio. Our multi-asset funds are fully unconstrained which means we do not follow a benchmark or peer-group. This gives us the freedom to invest where the best risk-adjusted returns are.• Tactical asset allocationTo generate additional returns or to protect the portfolios, we make deviations from our strategic asset allocation in line with our House View.To select asset classes and regions, we use a combination of three factors – economic fundamentals, valuations and market sentiment.This helps us make well informed and reasoned adjustments to the portfolio.• ImplementationWe believe implementation is as important as idea generation. When we build portfolios, we take each asset’s contribution to risk into account and stress test the portfolios to help ensure that they deliver consistent client outcomes.Finally, any decision we make is backedby qualitative analysis; the application of experience and resources rather than relying solely on models and numerical analysis.Thomas Wells CFA®, Fund manager, multi- assets. Thomas joined Aviva Investors in 2012, he is a lead multi-asset fund manager at Aviva Investors. He co-manages the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund (MAF) and Multi-manager ranges. ThomasjoinedAvivafromCewCapital, where he was responsible for advising private clients and family offices on investments in commercial real estate.You can find out more about the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund Range at https://www. avivainvestors.com/en-gb/adviser/multi- asset-funds.htmlImportant InformationThis commentary is not an investment recommendation and should not be viewed as such. Except where stated as otherwise, the source of all information is Aviva Investors as at 31 May 2017. Unless stated otherwise any opinions expressed are those of Aviva Investors. They should not be viewed as indicating any guarantee of return from an investment managed by Aviva Investors nor as adviceof any nature. Past performance is not a guide to future returns. The value of an investment and any income from it may go down as well as up and the investor may not get back the original amount invested.The Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund range comprises the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund I (“MAF I”), the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund II (“MAF II”), the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund III (“MAF III”), the Aviva Investors Multi-asset Fund IV (“MAF IV”) and the Aviva Investors Multiasset Fund V (“MAF V”) (together the “Funds”).The Funds are sub-funds of the Aviva Investors Portfolio Funds ICVC. For further information please read the latest Key Investor Information Document and Supplementary Information Document. Copies of these documents and the Prospectus are available to download in English from our document library.Issued by Aviva Investors UK Fund Services Limited. Registered in England No. 1973412. Authorised and regulated in theUK by the Financial Conduct Authority. Firm Reference No. 119310. Registered address: St Helen’s, 1 Undershaft, London EC3P 3DQ. An Aviva company.]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[32Six questions on the market outlookPaul Craig | Portfolio Manager | Old Mutual Cirilium PortfoliosPaul Craig poses a series of questions that are crucial to the macro- economic and market outlook and helps to answer where we are in the current cycle, and how he is shaping his investment strategy against this backdrop.How strong is the global economy?Growth in major advanced economies is rising at a rate that is slightly above the trend in place since the financial crisis, albeit at a slower pace than in previous economic cycles. We expect this trend to continue.The constant hum of fears over deflation,or falling prices, has finally dissipated. Now, inflationary pressures – especially from wages – will prove crucial to determining the policy of central banks.Some are concerned that the US economic upswing is losing steam, given that it has been unusually protracted. However, the slower the pace of recovery, the longer it takes to absorb economic slack and the longer the economy takes to reach full capacity. A sluggish recovery, therefore, means the peak that signals the end of the economic cycle may take some time to be reached.That said, economic growth has shifted from acceleration to steady expansion. Over time, this should feed into upward pressure on wages and inflation.Are markets underestimating the risks?Because markets have been calm oflate, measures of expected volatility are remarkably low, leading many commentators to argue that market participants have become complacent.However there have previously been long periods of market calm, punctuated bybrief moments of crisis, meaning volatility does not always remain high. Consequently, today’s low-volatility regime may persist for longer than many expect.This presents us with an opportunity to mitigate the risk of owning equities via options. These strategies enable us to safeguard our portfolios without having to withdraw money from our favourite fund managers with whom we invest.Can current valuations persist?Since the financial crisis, most asset classes have performed exceptionally well – not least developed-market government bonds, whose yields remain stubbornly low despite steady economic growth and central banks taking steps towards removing stimulus.Even though we are yet to see wages grow at a pace that would stoke inflation – which erodes the value of the fixed payments offered by bonds and which central banks are tasked with controlling – central bankers are signalling a gradual end to emergency stimulus measures. These measures, such as asset purchase and interest-rate cuts have helped to suppress bond yields.As central banks become less accommodative, and inflation increases, long-term bond yields are likely to rise gradually, in our view, albeit to levels below historical averages due to structural factors such as aging populations, poor productivity growth and high debt levels across major economies.]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[33Growth in major advanced economies is rising at a rate that is slightly above the trend in place since the financial crisis, albeit at a slower pace than in previous economic cycles. We expect this trend to continue.Current investor sentiment is characterised by anxiety as to equity valuations, particularly in the US. But while the earnings yield for US stocks look expensive when compared to historical averages, it appears attractive when compared to bond yields.Moreover, as company earnings havebeen staging a recovery of late, it is not unreasonable to expect further gains from equities, despite the risks posed by the fact that labour shortages could cause wages to spike, eroding already-elevated profit margins.Where next for bond markets?We expect yields to climb, albeit gently, as steady economic growth is accompanied by rising inflation. At the same time, sovereign bond issuance for major developed economies is expected to be positive in 2018 for the first time in three years, meaning countries are issuing more debt than is being redeemed.But the rise in yields may be restrained by those deep-rooted factors we discussed earlier, as well as demand from investors, such as pension funds, which require bonds’ steady cash flows to match future liabilities.Company debt markets appear to be pricing solid economic expansion. Because the spread between the yield on company bonds and government debt has narrowed, as valuations have converged, future returns will probably come from income rather than capital appreciation. As any moderationin economic growth could lead to spread- widening, it pays to be selective.Against this backdrop, we have been increasing our exposure to alternative fixed- income assets, including tactical company debt funds, specialist credit and direct lending funds.Where next for equities?The global corporate earnings picture has certainly brightened, leading us to believe that the global economy is enjoying a period of sustained growth, and that the US will lead a pick-up in expansion later this year, following a near-term slowdown. The bad news? Clearly, the risk is that share prices already reflect strong earnings growth, leaving little room for disappointment.While equity markets offer an attractive prospective return relative to other asset classes, investors are best served by spreading their investment risk carefully and having realistic expectations for future returns, in our view.We expect a widening in the spread of returns among sectors and stocks, which would favour active, stock-picking managers over ‘passive’ strategies. In addition, we will continue to use option strategies to mitigate short-term risks, while maintaining cash balances a little higher than usual.How can ‘risk events’ be navigated?The coming months bring a plethora of ‘risk events’: elections in Germany and monetary- policy decisions across the globe, not to mention the ever-present potential for geopolitical flare-ups. In order to navigate them, we plan on continuing to prepare diligently ahead of political events with binary outcomes, as financial markets are often slow to appreciate the associated risks.However political events do not tend to be ‘game changers’ for markets, but they can generate more volatility than desired. And occasionally, as was the case with the Brexit vote, they can trigger material shifts in asset prices and currency markets.Even as we survey the path ahead, and seek to shift gears to fit the current investing environment, we endeavour not to focus on a single outcome – but to position fora variety of scenarios. This may dilute the spoils of victory somewhat, but should also help to safeguard against adverse market moves, in our view.For more informationwww.omglobalinvestors.comFor investment professionals only. Please remember that past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and the income from them can go down as well as up and investors may not get back any of the amount originally invested. Exchange rates may cause the value of overseas investments to rise or fall. OMGI 07_17_0168]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[34In search of rewardsJohn Redwood | Chief Global Strategist | Charles StanleyWe live in a world of low returns. If you hold cash you earn very little on your deposit. If you lend your money to an advanced country government there’s very little income paid on the government bond you buy. The main Central banks have driven the price of bonds up massively, leaving interest rates on the floor and savers scrambling to find a return.The aim of all this is to persuade people to take some more risk. There are better yields available on shares for those who can takea longer view and accept that from time to time their holdings may fall in value. There are also better incomes to be had from property. In the UK, the government has made it more difficult for the individual buy- to-let investor by increasing Stamp Duties on initial purchase, and by worsening the tax treatment of the interest on any mortgage. Meanwhile the yields on commercial property are, in most cases, more generous than bonds and many shares. Commercial property requires investment in specialist funds for most savers, or in portfolios of Real Estate Investment Trusts, given the high price of most properties.In this climate at Charles Stanley we do recommend clients to take some risk by having more in shares where they can afford to do so. We expect world stock marketsto make some more upward progress, and to pay out reasonable dividends. Many companies are now generating good cash and are paying special dividends on topof their regular payouts, or are boosting share prices by buying in some of their own shares. The world is enjoying a synchronised economic recovery. The Euro area is showing modest growth, the USA is continuing its recovery, and Japan is moving forwards despite a falling and ageing population.We do not think we are near the end ofthis cycle. Central Banks remain broadly supportive. The Japanese Central bank wants to keep its ten-year interest rate at zero, with negative short rates. The European Central Bank is still creating money to buy up bonds, keeping rates very low. It is also encouraging improvements in weak balance sheets by commercial banks, to allow more credit to then be advanced to fuel extra growth. The Bank of England is still sticking with 0.25%as its main interest rate, and is not talking about big or sustained rises. Only the Fed is gently raising rates, but at a pace so far that the Stock market can handle. None of these institutions want to slow their economies or think there is an inflationary problem they need to control.In this climate it can also make sense for the investor to keep the costs of investing down where possible. Europe is catchingup with the USA in now having a good range of Exchange Traded Funds that offera saver exposure to a given Stock marketat a low management cost. An increasing number of portfolios use these vehicles to get exposure to individual stock markets where the manager does not employ a team of expensive analysts to follow the individual shares. There are Active/passive funds where the fund manager concentrates on the big asset allocation decisions and then uses passive funds to implement the]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[35There are better yields available on shares for those who can take a longer view and accept that from time to time their holdings may fall in value. There are also better incomes to be had from property.strategy and keep the costs down. Thereare a range of mixed funds where specialist active management is used where there is a good chance of it beating the relevant index, but index trackers are used for investment elsewhere. At Charles Stanley we do both.Some have worried that if too many shares are bought up by tracker funds this will damage the investors’ role in corporate governance. Some tracker fund management groups do now take an active interest in the companies they have to own because they are in the index, voting in favour of better governance, against excessive remuneration and on other matters that they think can help shareholder returns. They do so onthe basis that they have an interest in the success of all the companies in the index. They cannot do what many active funds do, which is sell the shares when they have a disagreement with the management.In the US tracker funds have been helpful in steering more companies to better governance.Studies show that the main contributors to the performance of a portfolio are the overall decisions on how much to have in bonds or shares, and which main share markets and currencies to back within the equity portion. These decisions are not easy to get right, but you cannot duck them. There is no single index or model you can adopt for a portfolio.You do need to decide an asset allocationin the light of the client’s aims, appetitefor risk, and the outlook for the markets. When it comes to buying US or European or other regional shares you do have a choice as to whether you want to spend moreon trying to beat the index by selecting some shares and not others. Quite often matching the index gives you a good answer at a considerably lower price than an active solution. In practice many portfolios now use tracker etfs for some of their needs.What can go wrong for world markets? We always need to ask and to do some worrying. If the Central Banks moved too quickly to put up rates and reduce money in the system that would be bad for shares and bonds. If there were a hard landing in China or some big world crisis we have not foreseen that too could do damage. For the time being we remain optimistic, but ever vigilant.Source: IBES, MSCI, Thomson ReutersThis is not personal advice based on your circumstances. No news or research item is a personal recommendation to deal.]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[36Correlation fixationJohn Stopford | Portfolio Manager | Investec Diversified Income FundLow correlation doesn’t always mean better risk-rewardImagine a strategy which captured all of the FTSE 100’s positive returns and none of its losses. This, surely, would be the ultimate investment – one generating onlymore of the upside than the downside (called ‘skew’), or whether the relationship between these assets is likely to change at different points in the economic cycle. Yet the correlation of a fund with an investor’s domestic index is increasingly being used as a primary determinant of the suitability of an investment. We believe, correlation needs to be viewed in combination with other characteristics to get a fuller appreciation of an investment’s behaviour.Make hay whilst the sun shinesthe monthly returns on the S&P 500 index have been positive. More striking is that outside of the overheating or recessionary stages of growth (when the cycle is either very mature or in outright contraction) approximately 70% of monthly returns are positive.It makes sense then to harvest the returns offered by growth-sensitive assets by having a high correlation to equities when the economic risks of doing so are low, and only adopting a more defensive position, or a low correlation to equities, as risks begin to rise. It makes sense then to harvest the returns offered by growth-sensitive assets by having a high correlation to equities when the economic risks of doing so are low, and only adopting a more defensive position, or a low correlation to equities, as risks begin to rise.n fixationgains with no drawdowns. Sadly this articledoesn’t contain the secret of how to find this holy-grail. Instead we look at the correlation of this ‘ultimate investment’ to the FTSE. Surprisingly, the two would have been 84% correlated over the last 20 years.A simple statisticThis is because correlation is a blunt measureLow correlation doesn’t always mean better risk-rewardwhich cannot differentiate between gains Throughout the majority of a typical anIdmlaogssinees.aItsteralltseygoyuwhoicwh, coanpatuvererdagael,l of the FTSeEco1n0o0m’sicpocsyictilvee, grerotuwrnths-asenndsnitoivneassetsof its losses. This, surely, would be the ultimate investment – one generating onlyan asset moves relative to another. It says such as equities or high yield debt, havegains with no drawdowns. Sadly this instalment of Income Thinking doesn’tnothing about how much it moves relative historically generated positive returns. Overcontain the secret of how to find this holy-grail. Instead we look at the correlationto the other asset and whether it captures the last 50 years, approximately 60% ofof this ‘ultimate investment’ to the FTSE. Surprisingly, the two would have been 84% correlated over the last 20 years.Figure 1: The ultimate investment vs. FTSE 1009,000 8,000 7,000 6,000 5,000 4,000 3,000 2,000 1,000Correlation0.84350 300 250 200 150 100 50Apr12 Apr15 Apr17Apr97FTSE 100Apr00 Apr03 Apr06 Apr09 Ultimate investmentPast performance is not a guide to the future, losses may be made. Source: Bloomberg as at28.04.17.Past performance is not a guide to the future, losses may be made. Source: Bloomberg as at 28.04.17.oUltimate investment total returnFTSE 100 total return]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[37Figure 2: Rolling correlation DIF & FTSE 100 (90 days)Figure 2: Rolling correlation DIF & FTSE 100 (90 days)1.21.21.0C0O.8RRELATION FIXATION1.0 0.60.80.40.6A fuller picture of behaviour0.40.2The benefit of a correlation that varies over time can be an improvement in the skew of returns a strategy produc0.0Apr 14 Jul 14 Oct 14 Jan 15 Apr 15 Jul 15 Oct 15 Jan 16 Apr 16 Jul 16 Oct 16 Jan 17 Apr 17perhaps the most important measure of its attractiveness. Selecting resilient securities from the bottom-up, achiSource0:.B2loomberg as at 21.04.17. Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results. Sosutrcuec:Btuloroamlbdeirvgearsaifitc2a1.t0io4.n17a.Pnadsttpaecrftoicrmaallnyceheisdngotinagrealiagbaleininsdticeavtoernotfafuntudremreasrukltes.t risks, has led to lower drawdowns andupside capture for the Investec Diversified Income Fund since launch. This allows better compounding of returns oA f0u.0ller picture of behavioure ev beThe benefit of a correlation that varies over time can be an improvement in the skew of returns a strategy produces which isSpFoeigurhrucarepe:sB3tlh:oeoUmpbosesidtrgiema&psoadrttoa2nw1t.0nm4s.e1ida7s.euPrcaeasotpfptieutsrfeoatrotmrafacDntciIvFenisvesns.os.Ft SaTeSrleElicatb1inl0eg0irnedsiicliaetnotrsoefcfurtiutiresrefrsoumltst.he bottom-up, achievingstructural diversification and tactically hedging against event and market risks, has led to lower drawdowns and better6050Figure 3: Upside & downside capture of DIF vs. FTSE 100upside capture for the Investec Diversified Income Fund since launch. This allows better compounding of returns over time – a powerful attribute in a time of slim asset class returns.60 4050 3040203010 201049.3% 49.3%Upside capture26.6% 26.6%Downside captureUpside capture Downside captureFigure 4: Risk & return characteristics of DIF vs. FTSE 100 since inceptionFigure 4: Risk & return characteristics of DIF vs. FTSE 100 since inceptionDIF FTSE 100 T5.4%Compound annual returnC% o mp o p o s u i t n i v d e a mn n o u n a t l h r e s t u r n 5 . 4 %%Anpnousaitilviseemdosnttahnsdard deviation 73%Annualised standard deviation 4.36%73%4.36%1.22(4.0%) (2.0%) (0.6%)(0.5%)10.0%66%10.29%0.98(12.1%)(5.3%)(3.7%)(3.5%)Sharpe ratio (0.0%)Sharpe ratio (0.0%) 1.22DRAWDOWNS SINCE INCEPTION (PEAK : VALLEY) OF THE FTSE 100DRAWDOWNS SINCE INCEPTION(PEAK : VALLEY) OF THE FTSE 100Drawdown 130.04.13 : 30.08.13Drawdown 130.04.13 : 30.08.13 (4.0%)Drawdown 231.08.16 : 30.11.16Drawdown 231.08.16 : 30.11.16 (2.0%)Drawdown 331.03.15 : 30.04.15Drawdown 331.03.15 : 30.04.15 (0.6%)Source Figure 5: Bloomberg as at 30.04.17.2 8 . 1 1 . 1 24 8 : . 31 1 1 . . 1 1 2 4 . 1 : 4 3 1 . 1 2 . 1 4 ( 0 . 5 % )D D r r a a w w d d o o w wn n 4 4Past performance is not a reliable indicator of future results, losses may be made.P P a a s t s t p e p r e f o r r f m o r a m n c a e n i s c n e o i t s a n r o e l t i a a b l r e e i l n i a d b i c l a e t o i n r o d f i c f u a t t u o r r e o r e f s f u u l t t s u , l r o e s s r e e s s m u l a t y s , b l e o m s s a e d e s . mS o a u y r c b e e F i g m u a r e d 4 e : . I n v e s t e c A s s e t M a n a g e m e n t , i n G B P g r o s s Source Figure 4: Investec Asset Management, in GBP gross of fees and taxes with income reinvested, UK Equity returns are for FTSE AlloSfofueercseanFdigtuaxres4w:iItnhviensctoemceArseisnevtesMteadn,aUgKeEmqueintyt,rientuGrnBsPargerfosrsFToSfEfeAellsShaanrdeItnadxexs,fwroimth3in1c.0o8m.12etroei3n0v.e0s4t.e17d.,InUvKesEteqcuDitiyverrestifiuernds are for Share Index, from 31.08.12 to 30.04.17. Investec Diversified Income Fund average monthly gain and loss as a proportion of UK EquitiesShare Index, from 31.08.12 to 30.04.17. Investec Diversified Income Fund average monthly gain and loss as a proportion of UK EqIanvceoramge Fguanindanvderlaogses.monthly gain and loss as a proportion of UK Equities average gain and loss. Source Figure 5: Bloomberg as at 30.04.17. SaovuercaegFeigguarein5:aBnldoolmosbse.rg as at 30.04.17.DIFFTSE 100 TOTAL RETURNOTFT uitAchieving the best risk-adjusted returns by managing correlations appropriately through the business cycle should be more important than just targeting a low average correlation.In addition to having a correlation that is suited to the economic environment, we believe the return profile of an investment can be improved by adjusting risk tactically to limit performance drawdowns. This is because, even in expansionary stages of growth, markets can be subject to losses caused by other drivers (such as geopolitics or sentiment).As a result, a well-managed fund which looks to be positioned appropriately over both tactical and strategic horizons will vary its correlation to growth-sensitive assets over time. This can be seen more clearlyby looking at correlation on a rolling basis rather than the simple long-run average which will necessarily miss any steps taken to mitigate losses.Managing and evolving correlationThe effect of this can be seen in Figure 2 which shows the rolling correlation between the Investec Diversified Income Fund (DIF) andthe FTSE 100. The chart illustrates the severe damping of correlations between the Fund and risk assets during the Brexit event and ‘risk-off’ episodes of 2015 and 2016. Similarly, when growth assets are felt to offer unattractive reward relative to their risks (for example, if valuations are lofty against a poor technical backdrop – such as in summer and winter 2015) then correlation can be dampened down for these ‘market-risk’ based reasons. Efficient methods for controlling correlation include the sale or purchase of bond and equity futuresor the use of FX hedging. This allows the risk of the Fund to be controlled across multiple frontiers but without having to change the underlying positions and in so doing miss out on their income streams.A fuller picture of behaviourThe benefit of a correlation that varies over time can be an improvement in the skew of returns a strategy produces which is perhaps the most important measure of its attractiveness. Selecting resilient securitiesCORRELATION FIXATIONfrom the bottom-up, achieving structuraldiversification and tactically hedging againstCORRELATION FIXATIONevent and market risks, has led to lowerManaging and evolving correlationdrawdowns and better upside capture for theThe effect of this can be seen in Figure 3 which shows the rolling correlation between the Investec Diversified Income FundIMnvaensatgeincgDainvderesviofilveidngInccoorrmelaetiFounnd since launch.(DIF) and the FTSE 100. The chart illustrates the severe damping of correlations between the Fund and risk assets during theT h B e r e e f x f e i c t t e o v f e t h n i s t c a a n n d b e ‘ r s i e s e k n - i o n f F f i ’ g u e r p e i 3 s o w d h i e c h s s o h o f w 2 s 0 t 1 h 5 e r a o l n l i n d g c 2 o 0 r r 1 e 6 l a . t i o S n i mb e i t l wa e r l e y n , t wh e h I e n v n e s g t e r c o Dw i v t e h r s a i fi s e d s e I n t c s o ma r e e F u f e n d l t t o o f f e r u n a t t r a c t i v e r e w a r d This allows better compounding of returns over(DIF) and the FTSE 100. The chart illustrates the severe damping of correlations between the Fund and risk assets during therelative to their risks (for example, if valuations are lofty against a poor technical backdrop – such as in summer and winterBrexit event and ‘risk-off’ episodes of 2015 and 2016. Similarly, when growth assets are felt to offer unattractive rewardtime – a powerful attribute in a time of slim2015) then correlation can be dampened down for these ‘market-risk’ based reasons. Efficient methods for controllingrelative to their risks (for example, if valuations are lofty against a poor technical backdrop – such as in summer and winter20c1o5)rrtheelan tciornrelianticolnucdaen bthe edasmapleneodr dpouwrncfhoratshesoe f‘mbaorknedt-riaskn’dbaesqedurietyasfountsu. Ereffiscieonrt tmheethuodssefoor fcoFnXtrohlleindg ging. This allows the risk of the Fund asset class returns.correlation include the sale or purchase of bond and equity futures or the use of FX hedging. This allows the risk of the Fundto be controlled across multiple frontiers but without having to change the underlying positions and in so doing miss out onCORRELATION FIXATIONto be controlled across multiple frontiers but without having to change the underlying positions and in so doing miss out ontheir income streams.their income streams.– a Apporw14erful aJtutlr1ib4ute inOcat t1i4me ofJsanlim15asseAtpcr 1la5ss retJurln15s.Oct 15Jan 16Apr 16Jul 16Oct 16Jan 17Apr 17FOR MORE INFORMATION, PLEASE CONTACT US:enquiries@investecmail.com08003892299 www.investecassetmanagement.comTelephone calls may be recorded for training and quality assurance purposes.This communication is directed only at professional financial advisors. It should not be distributed to, or relied on by private customers. Past performance should not be taken as a guide to future returns. Your clients’ capital is at risk. English language copies of the Funds’ prospectuses, Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) are available from www.investecassetmanagement.com. The Fund may invest more than 35% of their assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state. The Fund is domiciled in the UKs which is ingtterver timeAL RETURN10.0% 66% 10.29% 0.98(12.1%) (5.3%) (3.7%) (3.5%)SE All iesPercentagPee(%rc)entage (%)]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[38Steering a smooth course in retirementSteve Lewis | Director of Sales and Marketing | LV= Retirement SolutionsThe introduction of the pension freedom and choice changes has seen an understandable focus on consolidating separate pension pots and making use of drawdown options as an alternative to purchasing a lifetime annuity.At a glance. . .The LV= Flexible Guarantee investments are especially suitable for clients concerned about the impact of stock market volatility and protecting their capital against losses.• Choice of three funds offering a unique averaged price mechanism that aims to smooth out market peaks and troughs and reduce short term volatility.• Ability to lock in gains by purchasing guarantees. Guarantees can be started, stopped or altered at any time.• Independently risk-rated funds to suit different attitudes towards investment risk.• Managed by Columbia Threadneedle Investments.• Competitive charges – including loyalty discount.The risk/reward challenges associated with stockmarket investment mean that building robust portfolios that offer the prospect of growth, but with the reassurance of downside protection, is more important than ever if a retirement portfolio is going to provide a sustainable level of income.The LV= Flexible Guarantee investments are designed to meet the challenges presentedby today’s pension landscape and are ideally positioned to help advisers deliver good retirement outcomes and successfully navigate uncertain times.The LV= Flexible Guarantee investments are three risk-rated multi-asset funds incorporating a unique average price mechanism that aims to smooth out the peaks and troughs of short-term market uncertainties. They also offer the reassurance of an optional capital guarantee that can be switched on and off as required.Although investment performance is clearlyan important consideration, for many cautious clients the ability to minimise investment risk is the main priority – and this is where the LV= Flexible Guarantee investments can provide an ideal solution.The funds are available in a Life format – through the LV= Flexible Guarantee Bond– or as Pension funds via the LV= Flexible Transitions Account. Leading fund managers Columbia Threadneedle have been selectedto manage the funds in line with a strategy and objectives set by LV=. The funds have been independently risk-rated by Synaptic and can be used to match differing attitudes to investment risk.Helping you develop your businessSome suggestions where the LV= Flexible Guarantee Funds could offer new opportunities to improve retirement outcomes for your clients:• Pension Consolidation • At age 55 • Final salary transfers • Guaranteed income drawdown]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[39Pricing Spread: Offer-Bid ● Data Frequency: Daily ● Currency: Pounds SterlingSource: FE 2017. 3/7/14 to 2/8/17. Offer to bid, sterling, indexed.been included.Data provided by FE. Care has been taken to ensure that the information is correct but it neither warrants,||represents nor guarantees the contents of the information, nor does it accept any responsibility for errors, inaccuracies, omissions or any inconsistencies herein.| |Financial Express Limited Registration number: 2405213. Registered office: 3rd Floor, Hollywood House, Church Street East, Woking, GU21 6HJ. Telephone 01483 783 900| |Website:www.financialexpress.netPast performance is not a reliable indicator of future returns.Points to remember:• Money is invested into the LV= funds at the underlying price. The averaging mechanism is not applied for the first 26 weeks. This chart shows the performance of an investment made in July 2014.• In exceptional market conditions (when the underlying price is 80% or less of the averaged price) the funds will be valued on the underlying price. LV= also reserve the right to do this at other times.• The performance of the LV= funds is based on returns before annual charges, which are taken by unit deduction. The calculation of the sector average figuresmay take the effects of annual charges into account.Risk/Return ChartOverall growth compared to annualised volatility over 3 years to 31st July 2017.MixedSharessectoraverages shownforcontext30.0 29.0 28.0 27.0 26.0 25.0 24.0 23.0 22.0 21.0 20.0 19.0 18.0 17.0 16.0 15.0%Risk/Return chartOverall growth compared tPoricinagnSpnreaud:aBidl-iBside• Cdurrevncoy: lPaoutndislSitterlying over 3 years to 31st July 2017 Mixed Investment sector averages shown for context3 August 2017B CDAEF0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 3.5 4.0 4.5 5.0 5.5 6.0 6.5 7.0 7.5 8.0 8.5 9.0 9.5 10.0 10.5 11.0 11.5 12.0 12.5KeyNameA  ABI Mixed Investment 40%-85% Shrs GTR in GBB  LV= - Flexible Guarantee Managed Growth Pn S2 GTR in GB C  LV= - Flexible Guarantee Balanced Pn S2 GTR in GBD  LV= - Flexible Guarantee Cautious Pn S2 GTR in GBE  ABI Mixed Investment 20%-60% Shrs GTR in GBF  ABI Mixed Investment 0%-35% Shrs GTR in GBAnn. Volatility31/07/2014 - 31/07/2017 © FE 2017Performance Volatility27.47 7.24 26.28 3.14 23.90 2.72 20.84 2.42 19.79 5.28 17.71 4.26The Life versions of the funds were launched in 2009 and now provide a track record stretching back 8 years.This chart illustrates the performance of the 3 pension funds since they were launched in July 2014. For context the chart also includes the performance of a selection of Mixed investments sector averagesThe chart shows the smoothing effect quite clearly. All 3 funds have delivered performances that compare favourably to the Mixed investment sector averages – but without the distraction of the peaks and troughs arising from changing market sentiments.Unique smoothing process:The smoothing process is transparent and aimsto reduce the impacts of market volatility.Money is initially invested into the funds at the underlying unit price and the investment is valued at the underlying price for the first 26 weeks. Thereafter, the fund values are smoothed by using a mechanism that takes the average of the fund’s daily underlying price over the preceding 26 weeks to calculate an averaged price. After the first 26 weeks the investment will normally be valued at the averaged price.The 2nd chart illustrates the impact of the smoothing process on the volatility of the funds compared to funds with similar asset allocations. Past performance is not a reliable guide to future returns.Flexible Guarantees:While the unique smoothing process provides a welcome shock-absorber against short-term market volatility, the LV= funds also offer the additional security of a capital guarantee that can be purchased at any time – not just at the outset. The guarantee applies to the value at the end of the selected guarantee period and the value of the fund may be less – or more – if it is moved or cashed in early. For extra flexibility the guarantee can be also be switched off at any time. This ability to start, alter or renew the guarantees, effectively creates a ‘lock in’ feature which can act as a defence mechanism to protect gains achieved and/or to remove the risk of investment loss.. This makes the funds especially attractive for more cautious clients.A custom page title hasFind out moreLV= Flexible Guarantee Funds - Performance since launch to 2nd August 2017 Mixed Shares sector averages shown for context.For more information about the LV= Flexible Guarantee Funds and what they could do for yourData provided by FE. Care has been taken to ensure that the information is correct but it neither warrants,represents nor guarantees the contents of the information, nor does it accept any responsibility for errors, inaccuracies, omissions or any inconsistencies herein. Financial Express Limited Registration number: 2405213. Registered office: 3rd Floor, Hollywood House, Church Street East, Woking, GU21 6HJ. Telephone 01483 783 900 Website:www.financialexpress.netA custom page title has been included.business, get in touch with your usual LV= Retirement Consultant or contact us on 08000 850250.Lines are open 8:30am – 5:30pm Monday to Friday. We may record and/or monitor your calls for training and audit purposes. Liverpool Victoria Friendly Society Limited, Pease House, Tilehouse Street, Hitchin, Herts SG5 2DX. LV= is a registered trademark of Liverpool Victoria Friendly Society Limited (LVFS) and a trading style of the Liverpool Victoria group of companies. LVFS is authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority, register number 110035. NM Pensions Trustees Limited (registered in England No.4299742), act as Trustees and are authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority, register number. 463402. Registered address for all companies: County Gates, Bournemouth BH1 2NF. Tel: 01202 2923333 August 2017Performance]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[40Business Protection and poor healthRichard Jessup | Protection Market Manager | JustLife cover can be crucial for a number of reasons - to support a residential mortgage, for business or inheritance tax planning (IHT) purposes or simply to have financial peace of mind.Life assurance becomes even more important if you have a medical condition and your application has been declined by a provider.The truth is that life offices do not have a consistent service on underwriting clients with poor health.Online aggregators, quick quotes on insurer’s websites and the large portal players all have one thing in common, their online journeys are built for healthy lives. So the quoteyou receive is based on your client being perfectly healthy.Some online services do ask a few underwriting questions, but the journeys are developed with the view that advisers and customers do not have much time and want a quick answer. Therefore, the quote you receive includes a caveat - subject to underwriting.“Mild impairments” may produce a binding quote (no need for medical evidence). However, for a client with high BMI and multiple health issues such as diabetes, this will require manual intervention from an underwriter.The journey differs from insurer to insurer. Behind the scenes the big life offices assess their risk appetite on a daily basis, basedupon analysis of thousands of pieces of management information.So achieving a consistency of decision across all life offices is difficult. Some specialist advisers build up knowledge of an insurer’s stance through regular telephone calls to underwriting departments. This isn’t always consistent as one underwriter has a different view to another, and this can be the same with reinsurers.Underwriting for poor health, it would seem, is a science.That’s why we specialise in underwriting life cover for those in poor health.• Our experience of underwriting impaired lives means we can provide cover for some of those people with medical conditions who may previously have been considered uninsurable .• Each case is looked at individually. Thisis what you would expect for a client with health issues, as online underwriting engines would not be able to cope with more complicated medical history.• Our products are straightforward with no bells and whistles keeping the premiums down.• We now offer terms for poor health, not just declined applications from other life offices. So we are no longer a last resort.• We can keep premiums affordable by calculating a sum assured to a client’s suggested premium.• We offer technical trust help for business protection requests.• We offer personal assistance for more difficult cases.EXAMPLE CASE STUDY FOR SHAREHOLDER PROTECTIONAndrew Smith, 57, is a business man. He’s one of three directors of a packaging company.At a review meeting with his adviser, it was explained that key person cover would not be enough to prevent the company having financial difficulties, if one of the directors, who each own 33% of the share capital, were to die.XYZ packaging is not a family business. Should either director fall seriously ill or die, this is likely to cause significant disruption and problems, to both the business and the family of the owner.]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Mr Phillips obtains life cover in an individual Business Trust for £100,000 with the beneficiaries being Mr Smith and Mr James.41Mr Smith obtains life cover in an individual Business Trust for £100,000 with the beneficiaries being Mr James and Mr Phillips.Mr James obtains life cover in an individual Business Trust for £100,000 with the beneficiaries being Mr Smith and Mr Phillips.A Cross Options Agreement is set up.For illustration purposes Mr Smith dies.Mr Smith’s shares are paid to his estate.The life cover pays out £100,000 to the beneficiaries (Mr James and Mr Phillips).Mr James and Mr Phillips use the proceeds of the life cover to buy Mr Smith’s shares from his estate.The purchased shares are then divided equally between Mr James andMr Phillips.If Andrew Smith was to die, his share of the business would automatically be owned by his spouse and she would then have an interest in the company.In most cases it will be a requirement that the business continues under the ownership of the surviving owners and the family/dependants of the deceased receive appropriate financial compensation. If all the business owners were members of the same family, for example, parents and children, then there would beno problem with succession when one ofthe business owners dies. The other family members would probably take over, with the family usually looking after the dependants of the deceased owner.To fund for purchase on death, ordinary life assurance will usually be appropriate.Unfortunately, Andrew has been declined by ABC life assurance because of heart problems:• Hypertension• High Cholesterol• A stent fitted 5 years agoThis is where we can help. Our expertise in poor health means that Andrew could be covered alongside his healthy directors.To make sure the funds for purchase are available in the right hands at the right time, it’s necessary to use an appropriate Trust. For business succession cases a “Business Trust” will be suitable along with a cross option agreement*.• Each shareholder (the directors) takes out life cover held in an individual Business Trust equal to the value of their shareholding (£100,000). In their Trust the appointed beneficiaries are the other two shareholders.• A Cross Option Agreement* is set up to allow each shareholder the option to purchase, in the event of death, the deceased’s equity.• In the event of death of one of the shareholders, the beneficiaries of the life cover (£100,000), pay the proceeds to the estate to buy the deceased’s equity.• The purchased shares are then divided equally between the two surviving shareholders.*A cross option agreement can also be known as the double option or put and call agreement. As the preferred vehicle for shareholder protection insurance, the cross option agreement provides the surviving shareholders with the option to buy the deceased business owners share of the business.Just offers a number of business protection products including Relevant Life, Key Person Protection, Commercial Loan/Mortgage Protection, along with Shareholder Protection.For more information go to - www.justadviser.com/products/life-assurance/]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[42Commercial interestsNigel Ashfield | Managing Director and Partner | TIME InvestmentsAn investor looking for a steady income stream 10 years ago could have invested in UK Government bonds and been rewarded with around 5%. Today that reward amounts to just 1%.Once rising inflation is taken into account the picture looks even starker. The retail price index (RPI) stands at 3.6%, currently meaning investors in so-called safe haven bonds are looking at a negative return.For nearly 10 years since the global financial crisis hit in 2008, the return from UK Government bonds has reached record low after record low as the Bank of England attempted to limit some of the damage.These crippling low interest rates are made yet worse by the recent return of rising inflation.At the same time, individuals are expected to take more personal responsibility for securing their financial futures, particularly in retirement.Defined contribution pension scheme members were granted the freedom to invest their pension pots with impunity from age 55, creating a wealth of opportunity to grow retirement savings long into the future. Yet, just as investment freedom expands so the availability of appropriate income streams contracts.So for investors grappling with the income trap it may be time to look beyond traditional asset classes.The long gameLong income commercial property offers the potential to deliver stable income over the long term without the volatility associated with traditional real estate investment.Long income property funds investingin commercial freeholds have long been available to large institutional investors, such as pension funds and insurance companies. Now these tried and tested funds are coming to the retail market via FCA authorised funds.The mechanics of long income commercial property funds are quite simple; they invest in commercial freeholds with long leases and ground rent agreements.Freehold properties with ground rents are let to commercial tenants at around 15% to 40% of the going market rate for the building, for terms in excess of 60 years.This provides stability of income for the freeholder and incentivises the tenantto maintain their ground rent payments, since failure to do so would mean giving up extremely attractive rent payments.And because the property’s market value can be worth as much as four times the underlying freehold, these properties are often over-collateralised offering additional protection to investors.Commercial freeholds with long leases are UK properties let to tenants for periodsof typically over 20 years and tend to offer a higher income return compared to commercial freeholds with ground rents.With both long leases and ground rents, rent reviews are typically linked to inflation and agreed at outset rather than subjectto negotiations as is usually the casewith traditional rental agreements over commercial property. These are typically linked to RPI which means income streams can be inflation protected.]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[43For nearly 10 years since the global financial crisis hitin 2008, the return from UK Government bonds has reached record low after record low as the Bank of England attempted to limit some of the damage.TIME: Commercial Freehold key benefits• Long term, steady and secure investor income - exceeded 4% pa since inception• Portfolio diversification with over 40 properties on long leases averaging over 60 years• Inflation protection for over 95% of freeholds• Low volatility and no gearing• Capital growth potential• First open ended long income fundavailable to retail investors• Access to an experienced team withproven track record• Easy to invest via ISAs and personalpensionsAdditionally, the commercial tenant is typically responsible for all property and maintenance costs which means these expenses are not passed on to the freeholder.Blazing a trailTIME Investments is the first manager to deliver a regulated long-income commercial property vehicle to the retail market.Building on the 24-years of investment experience gained running the TIME: Freehold fund, which has beateninflation every year since inception, TIME:Commercial Freehold targets an income return of 4% per annum and is suited to investors seeking long term stable income and the potential for capital growth.The current average lease length for the fund is over 60 years which demonstrates long term stability and compares favourably to traditional commercial property funds with average lease lengths of under 10 years.More than 99% of the value of ground rents and between 70% and 80% of the long lease value comes from contractual rental income, which means the fundis protected from the full effect of movements in property prices. This makes TIME:Commercial Freehold far less volatile than most commercial property funds that are reliant on rent negotiations and capital value movements.This stability and consistency was borne out in the immediate market shocks following the Brexit vote in June 2016. While UK property funds experienced an outflow of £1.4bn in the month of the referendumand many were forced to suspend1, TIME:Commercial Freehold performed above its target, delivering secure, stable returns and continuous monthly liquidity for investors.Today’s markets are uncertain and with political and economic events dominating the agenda, investors can expect conditions to remain unpredictable and volatile for the time being.With stable, bond-like income so difficultto come by, the addition of a long income property investment has the potential make a real difference for investors seeking steady inflation beating returns.1 https://www.theinvestmentassociation.org/media-centre/press- releases/2016/press-release-statistics0616.html]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[44What to look for in a financial adviserNeil Cowell | Head of UK distribution | Vanguard EuropeWhy is Vanguard so adamant in our belief in the value of financialadvice? The answer is simple. When it comes to investing, most people,most of the time, will be significantly better off with the support of afinancial adviser.Let’s think for a moment about the financial challenges facing many of us in the United Kingdom. Increasingly, individuals and families are expected to take direct responsibilityfor life’s largest expenses, a home, higher education and support in later life.These are real challenges but we should not feel overwhelmed.At Vanguard, we believe in the power of investment as a means to meet life’s financial challenges. Like any powerful resource, the more it is harnessed and directed, the more benefits it can bring. And that is the role of a financial adviser. Ideally, an adviser will help not just with your personal plans but with those of your family, including passing wealth to the next generations, business issues, estate planning and the like.Vanguard has done a lot of research on how advisers bring value to their clients. I would like to share some of those insights, which might help you to make the most of your adviser.Set the strategyThe first step in establishing a good investment strategy is to clarify what it is you need to achieve. Your adviser can help youto analyse your present financial situation asBy balancing out your current and prospective resources, your estimated required returnand your willingness to put your capital at risk, an adviser can construct a portfolio of investments that is right for you. This process,By balancing out your current and prospective resources, your estimated required returnand your willingness to put your capital at risk, an adviser can construct a portfolio of investments that is right for you.well as your future prospects. He or she can then help you to understand some realistic investment objectives, including the amount you will need to put in and the risks you are willing to bear.commonly known as asset allocation, is core to the adviser’s role. Whether it is a bespoke portfolio or a simple, all-in-one solution, it is ultimately the mix of investments that most determines whether you meet your objectives.]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[45We believe in the power of investment as a means to meet life’s financial challenges. Like any powerful resource, the more it is harnessed and directed, the more benefits it can bring.Minimise costsInvestment charges can eat significantly into investor returns over the longer term. But research shows that few investors know how much they are paying and a surprising number believe they are not paying anything at all.There are many reasons for this. On an annual basis, charges look small. It is only when they are compounded out over many years that the damage will be done. On top of that,they can be complex, covering a number of separate services, such as fund management, account management, audit, custody, trusteeship and so on. Different investment firms will charge for different services in different ways. Then there are add-ons that may or may not be charged, depending on various terms and conditions, such as initial charges, dilution levies and exit charges.Understanding charges and ensuring they are minimised to the benefit of the investor is another critical value that an adviser offers.Keeping a balanceThe long-term nature of investment presents the problem of how to managea portfolio through a number of changing economic and business cycles. We need only think of what has gone on overthe past 20 years to appreciate how dramatically conditions can shift: the techboom and bust, the emerging market rally, the housing boom, the financial crisis and the subsequent recovery interspersed with episodic crisis in the euro area.A good financial adviser is there to ensure that through all of these changing times, your portfolio is kept in balance and aligned with your circumstances and your goals. Personal circumstances can also change, and a good adviser, who has taken the time to get to know your goals for you and your family, will be able to advise on the best course to ensure your investments can adapt as needed.When times are calm, this may seem a fairly obvious function. But it can matter hugely when the market is falling, when there is catastrophe in the headlines, or indeed, when markets are soaring and profits look all too easy. At such times, whether from fear or greed, we are all tempted to give in to emotion, or act on our intuition, and it’s then that sensible counsel is most valuableTax efficiencyFinally, there is tax. Taxes differ as they relate to different types of assets, to income and capital, to inheritance or gifts or trusts, and whether you invest directly or through an Individual Savings Account or through one of the other many vehicles for saving for a pension.An adviser can take your complete circumstances into account and help youto structure your investments in a manner that can minimise your tax liabilities. This process should evolve through varying life phases, from when you are accumulating assets to when you need to access them (either as capital sums or as income) through transferring them to family members.Longer, healthier lives are wonderful blessings, as are educational opportunities and the chance of a nice home. But nothing comes free. If we are to make the most of our futures in a complex, challenging world, financial advice can make an enormous difference.Important information:This article is designed for use by, and is directed only at persons resident in the UK. Vanguard Asset Management, Limited only gives information on products and services and does not give investment advice based on individual circumstances. If you have any questions related to your investment decision or the suitability or appropriateness for you of the products described above, please contact a financial adviser.The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested.The opinions expressed in this article are those of the individual author and may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.VAM-2017-06-01-4756]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[46Portfolio construction - is Modern Portfolio Theory still relevant?Geoff Mills | Director | RSMRWhen the American economist Harry Markowitz developed modern portfolio theory back in the early 1950s he was looking at how investment returns can be optimised.Economists had long understood the common sense of diversifying a portfolio – or, ‘not putting all your eggs in one basket’.But Markowitz showed how to measure the risk of various securities and how to combine them in a portfolio to get the maximum return for a given risk. We use this concept in an effort to get a well-diversified portfolio, as investing across the well-known asset classes is the best way to manage risk and return.But how does the theory hold up in different times, and how has the approach taken by managers evolved over the last 60 years?One reason there are few great investorsis the complex nature of the subject withno guarantees. Approaches that seem to be delivering results for a time can often befound to have been suited by one particular investment style factor, which when it goes out of fashion leaves its investors disappointed.Success as an investor requires perceptive thinking and recognition that it is not always possible to have an edge for outperformance in all market conditions. Most investors recognisethat extraordinary performance only comes from correct non-consensus forecasts, but they may not recognise that these by their nature are hard to make consistently. For an investor to achieve superior results there is a need for non-consensus views regarding value. Furthermore, these need to be accurate; over time an investor needs to get more right than wrong.Chance or skill?It is important to remember that one or two good years prove nothing, as chance alone can produce just about any result. Someone in a casino making five consecutive winning bets on the roulette table hasn’t demonstrated skill, and in investments the same is true.True manager skill can only start to be ascertained over a minimum of five years (market cycle), and ideally over longer time periods. Most asset classes are quite efficient, though of course this does vary depending on how well researched they are. The better an asset class is known and the broader its following, the harder it is to make a non- consensus winning bet against the herd. Insome mainstream markets it can be arguedit is almost a waste of time to try and find winners, certainly without a specialised approach. Investors are more likely to find superior returns investing in inefficient markets.Investment stylesFinding inefficiency can be approached in different ways with investors very often described as either value or growth style oriented.Value investors look to buy businesses at a significant discount to their intrinsic value, while growth investors look to find businesses that will continue to grow faster and for longer than the market expects. Other investors try and combine bits of both these approaches. Many value investors rely on mean reversion, both for shares and company profitabilityor even economies. Even this long-standing approach has come into question where markets have been distorted by QE and traditional businesses have suffered disruption, while others with monopoly powers have hung on to super-high levels of margins with little sign that these are being competed away.]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[47Success as an investor requires perceptive thinking and recognition that it is not always possible to have an edge for outperformance in all market conditions.For investors wanting a lower risk approach, finding a manager who is rigorous on both quality factors and the price paid in absolute terms can deliver results with lower than market volatility, in part simply by avoiding big mistakes. Investment approaches favouring quality at any price, or value at any quality, may deliver results over short time periods, but there are likely to be occasional periods of blow ups or disappointment.Forced sellersOne important thing for investors to remember is that as well as buying at the right price, it is important to sell at the right price, and certainly not to be forced to dump an asset well below its intrinsic value. Never being a forced seller of an illiquid asset isan important mantra for every investor to remember.Risk vs returnTo make above-average returns over the risk- free rate, taking risk is inescapable. This involves understanding risk and also trying to workout when it may be high. Investors can also control risk through portfolio construction. This may initially involve deciding whether a given investment justifies the risk, that is, thinking about the risk-adjusted return.Many investors define risk as volatility although some would argue a better definition of risk is absolute loss of the capital invested.The risk of permanent loss is the biggest one an investor should worry about.Central bank policy today with zero or negative interest rates has encouraged many investors to make riskier investments than are actually suitable for their own personal objectives. As Warren Buffett has stated “it’s only when the tide goes out that you find out who’s been swimming naked”.In today’s world of low rates, risk avoidance will probably result in very low returns, but understanding and controlling the risk taken is more important than ever before. For long- term investment avoiding losers is just as important as finding winners.Within equity markets it is not changes in earnings that drive the largest profit or loss, but actually changing valuation, driven by investor psychology, and this psychology swings back and forth like a pendulum. Investors entering the market from mid- 2009 through 2010 were buying at a time when the pendulum had swung to extremely pessimistic levels which is why the returns have been so strong since then.It is also necessary to understand investor psychology or behavioural finance aspects when constructing a portfolio. Investorsneed patience as market valuations tend to overshoot on both the upside and downside, so for a while an investor will look wrong and, possibly to friends and colleagues, stupid. Mostinvestors are trend followers, whereas the most successful investors have done the exact opposite. Always remember that at the most extreme point in markets most investors, and therefore the conventional wisdom of the day, will be wrong.In any form of forecasting, whether it is stock markets or the weather, there is a tendency to extrapolate the recent past into the future. This can work for a time, but will miss turning points and this is when large amounts of money can either be lost or opportunities missed to make significant returns - and unlike in sport, it is possible to win in investment simply by making fewer mistakes than the average.This is an extract from our white paper ‘Understanding Markets and Risk July 2017 - Thoughts on Portfolio Construction’ written by RSMR Investment Director Graham O’Neill. If you would like a copy of the full paper please go to our website www.rsmgroup.co.uk/newswww.rsmr.co.ukemail: geoff.mills@rsmgroup.co.uk Research Hub – members.rsmgroup.co.uk Twitter @RSMRTweets / @thegeoffmills]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[48General Data Protection Regulation – What’s in IT for me?Tiina Stephens | Operations Manager | Synaptic Software LimitedThe General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) is a new law that will replace the Data Protection Act 1998 and will apply in the UK from25 May 2018. We look at how you can prepare for the changes and avoid the pitfalls.The personal data that companies hold on their systems, whether paper-based or digital, client or employee personal data, will fall under GDPR. Information security, governance and data privacy will be areas under scrutiny with the new legislation. The Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO) details 12 steps to take now in preparation for the impending changes1:1. AwarenessEnsuring key people within the organisation are aware of the implications GDPR is likely to have on business practices.2. Information you holdEnsuring personal information you hold can be evidenced, including how it was obtained and who you share it with. Information audit may be needed.3. Communicating privacy informationAll privacy notices should be reviewed and any necessary changes planned in, prior to May 2018.4. Individuals’ rightsThe new legislation expands individuals’ rights and it will likely impact business procedures. Ensure that you are covering all the new rights including how you would delete personal data from your systems as well as providing data in an electronic and commonly used format.5. Subject access requestsThe timescales and content of subject access request are changing so you should update any business procedures and plan how to handle the request within the new framework.6. Lawful basis for processing personal dataIdentify the legal basis for your processing activity, document it and explain it in your privacy notices.7. ConsentThe GDPR sets higher standards onseeking, recording and managing consent,so you should check how you currently capture consent to see if you need to make any changes.8. ChildrenIf you store or process any personal data relating to a minor, you need to ensure that you have systems in place for verifying their ageas well as how to obtain parental or guardian consent for any data processing activity.9. Data breachesData breaches notification period will reduce to 72 hours and you need to ensure that you have the procedures in place to be able to detect, report and investigate a personal data breach.10. Data protection by design and protection impact assessmentRefer to the ICO’s code of practice on Privacy Impact Assessments and determine how and when to implement them in your organisation.11. Data protection officersData protection compliance and responsibility should be built into a designated role within the company and consideration given whether your organisation is required to appoint a data protection officer.]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[49The personal data that companies hold on their systems, whether paper-based or digital, client or employee personal data, will fall under GDPR. Information security, governance and data privacy will be areas under scrutiny with the new legislation.12. InternationalIf you carry out cross-border processing operating in more than one EU member state, determine your lead data protection supervisory authority. Refer to the Article 29 Working Party guidelines which will help with this.Where to start?The Data Protection Act (DPA) 1998 already has detailed processes in place on how to protect individuals’ personal data. The DPA enforces firms to have proper controls in place ensuring personal information is handledfairly including helping clients to understand who is responsible for handling their personal information, what it will be used for and any other information needed such as who will be processing the information on the firm’s behalf.Good practice recommendations from the ICO aimed at financial advisers currently state to2:• Make sure employees are clear about what they can and cannot do with personal information and who it can be disclosed to• Make sure employees are clear what use they can make of personal information in the event they leave the firm• Make sure customers know whose client they are, what their information will be used for and to whom it may be disclosed toThe list of recommendations is likely to expand to cover GDPR specific additions, therefore a good starting point towards GDPR compliance is the ‘Getting ready for the GDPR’ data protection self-assessment toolkit3 from the ICO. This assessment will allow you to select the readiness level for your firm and givesyou a list of recommendations to follow up to ensure you are on your way to compliance with comprehensive but proportionate governance measures by May 2018.Data Information RegistersOne of the main areas of GDPR is a firm’s understanding of the data they hold and for what reasons. Data information registers are required to evidence the understanding ofthe personal information. Depending on the size and complexity of the firm, these can be in-house developed registers, or for ease of use and efficiency, a software tool can be used to manage the different data sets which all firms are likely to have, including employee, client and partner data.Synaptic Software has teamed up with the UK’s leading legal software provider, Eclipse, and together we provide a Data Asset Register tool, which is easy to use and can provide evidence to the ICO, should it be required,on what data is kept, where, who can access it and the retention periods amongst other requirements. Should you wish to learn more,contact our relationship team either by email sales@synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477.There is no time to delay – GDPR will be enforcable by May 2018 and good data protection practice will enhance your business value as well as ensure compliancy and avoid any potential enforcement actions.Synaptic Software – Readiness Programme for GDPRAs your technology partner, Synaptic Software is committed to GDPR compliance across our cloud and on- premise services. We are preparing our Synaptic Suite to allow you to have full control of your clients’ data, including processes for deletion, rectification, transfer of, and objection to processing of personal data.We recognise that compliance under GDPR is a shared responsibility, and as your data processer, Synaptic will do our utmost to provide you with the means to help you comply. To do this, you need to make changes to your privacy and data management processes. Any failure to do so could prove costly – the enforcement action could be substantial; fines ofup to 20 million euros, or 4 percent of annual worldwide turnover (whichever is greater), as well as reputational harm.1https://ico.org.uk/media/1624219/preparing-for-the-gdpr-12-steps.pdf 2https://ico.org.uk/media/for-organisations/documents/1604/tied_agents.pdf 3https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/resources-and-support/data-protection-self-assessment-toolkit/]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50Intelliflo’s Intelligent Office now integrates with Synaptic research softwareStuart Carmichael | Head of Proposition | Synaptic Software LimitedA bug bear for some years for users of both Intelligent Office and Synaptic Research, has been the lack of formal integration between the two systems.This has been remedied with the recent agreement between the two companiesto make an integration part of the current evolution of the Intelliflo suite into a more ambitious technological project, linking additional aspects of their customer’s business processes. Synaptic will benefit through the greater access that Intelligent Office users will have to Synaptic Research.It has certainly been the case that some adviser firms have felt constrained in their use of the default research tools available with their preferred back office system, so we at Synaptic are looking forward to this obstacle disappearing to provide new opportunities to re-engage.How it works• The design allows Intelligent Office users to download a Synaptic Suite ‘app’;• The ‘app’ will initiate a link through to Synaptic and will pass the client data (including holdings) across to form the foundation of your research;• Any reports or downloads that are produced will be copied into the Intelligent Office database and stored against the client record.]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[51The Synaptic Research Suite is the best way of embedding the professional research that you need to differentiate your business from generic or more widely accessed research.Intelliflo usersThe regulatory screws are turning and recent thematic reviews around suitability (FC16/1 particularly) indicate the importance that the FCA is attaching to good research, a ‘culture of challenge’ in firms and focus on risk and cost.This year’s FCA business plan provides the following warnings:1. Advisers need to be clearer on charges. ‘Relatively few advisers are transparent about their pricing’. Synaptic Comparator is the only tool that provides total solution cost / R.I.Y. calculation using accurate charging data verified by the providers.2. Pressure on platforms. The FCA intends to be ‘investigating competition between platforms’ to see if they offer ‘value for money’. Synaptic Comparator provides accurate illustrations in this area.3. The regulator will do more to ensurerecommendations ‘are risk-appropriate’. Synaptic Risk proposition, including Synaptic Modeller, are supported by the soundest and most accessible research in the industry, from Moody’s Analytics.The Synaptic Research Suite is the best way of embedding the professional research that you need to differentiate your business from generic or more widely accessed research.For Intelliflo users who are not currently Synaptic users, or wish to trial additional Synaptic tools, please contact us on 0800 783 4477, and speak to one of our team for any assistance you may require in activating the Synaptic ‘app’ in Intelligent Office.You will be able to use Synaptic software to meet and evidence the FCA’s requirements for suitability across the major advice areas – features, price and risk.RISKSynaptic Research SuiteSynaptic Comparator provides full charges analysis at adviser, platform, product and portfolio level. Accurate calculation of ‘Reduction in Yield’.Synaptic Risk offers client risk profiling and portfolio and fund risk ratings for full investment risk management.Synaptic Modeller is a financial planning tool providing access to Moody’s Analytic’s stochastic engine. Will provide probability based projections and full risk management to existing holdings and recommendations.‘Whole of market’ research and suitability reporting from the industry’s leading product and fund research application. Now with integrated Synaptic Risk Ratings.SYNAPTIC Protection and annuities quotation portal WEBLINE offering electronic submissions.Intelliflo integration offer: any Intelliflo user who contacts us in 2017 will be eligible to use the full Synaptic suite for £99 per month (rrp. £246 per month). Apply for full terms, prices quoted exclude VAT.Please call 0800 783 4477 or email sales@synaptic.co.uk for further information.]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52Current issues and future opportunities for critical illnessAndrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskThis is a brave article to write. Not so much because of the topic – although this does contain views that will displease some – but because of print deadlines meaning significant things could have changed between my writing of this on a pleasant summer evening and your reading as leaves start to change colour.The long term forecast is that the relative cool of the Protection landscape this autumn will be warmed by heated discussion around the future of critical illness products prompted by the ABI’s critical illness (CI) Statement of Best Practice (SoBP).The ABI produces this SoBP every three years. I chaired the last one and am avery interested observer of this year’s. The aim of this work is to produce a common market standard of a basic CI product and the terms used to describe it. It intends to ensure an effective market can operate with an understanding of the similarities and differences between products.The 2014 SoBP three years ago was (inpart fortunately and in part deliberately) a reasonably quiet affair. We distinguished and defined additional and partial payments, acknowledged the existence of ‘ABI+’ definitions and assigned a standard to these,and slightly amended some definitions to meet changing market and medical practice. We didn’t go round in circles about TPD (Total Permanent Disability), add loads of definitions or take a deep cut to the basic coverage offered.Reflecting on the experience, the initial meetings can be amazingly anecdotal. Ona human level it’s quite refreshing that in a world of actuaries, doctors and underwriters, many of the first insights are personal frustration where people have felt the coverage “does not do what it set out to do”. At times this felt like the people who set out the rules of the game were complaining about the outcome.That experience led to an early sense of foreboding whenever the great and the good start explaining what “the product set out to do”. This seems to become one of those great campfire stories about times of yore,which all choose to sculpt to their own views while reminiscing: “Aaagh, Old Chief he tell me Silent Heart Attack would never a CI definition make”.Common themes from these fables tend to be that:• someone must suffer before we give themmoney• technological advances may bring the endof the critical illness world• we must all keep flying to the bright,beautiful CI lightSo what about this time?It is expected that there will be more fundamental changes as a result of this SoBP. There are some good reasons for this - there are incrementally clearer threats to the traditional CI model now than there were three years ago.]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[53I would urge all with an interest in the CI market to engage with the SoBP when the opportunity arises, the really interesting work will come after as we see the real motivation for some of the changes coming through.The diagnosis of many of the lower impact critical illnesses continues to increase, and the prognosis for these continues to improve. These two levers mean that left unchanged, while the impact of suffering an insured condition is decreasing, the cost of the cover would have to increase.Furthermore, there are justifiably different approaches being taken by different insurersto the grouping of conditions being developed. Should we define dementia in one definition or four? Should we adopt the same approach to other conditions like heart conditions?To get (even more) technical - the SoBP guidance to date has said that if 75% of the market has the same definition heading,there should be an agreed ABI wording. Ifhalf the market are splitting out definitions to maximise the number of conditions covered, and the other half are putting together to try and simplify the appearance of the product, it is difficult to maintain this approach. The most pragmatic approach may now be to retreatto base camp – and just define the conditions at the very centre of the CI product (those causing over 80% of claims) and leave the market to do their best on the rest.The future of CII believe better products would have developed than the current form of critical illness if we didn’t have ABI industry wordings. The ABI wordings have such a strong gravitational pull, you need to develop something in another galaxy or you get sucked into the CI orbit. Many have listened to what people reallywant and built something based on impact and need, but found themselves burning up in the heat of contact with sales and marketing teams with the power of “numbers of conditions” and “ABI+ conditions”.Whilst some products more directly linking the impact of the illness to the financial support given might have grown without the ABI approach, I recognise the market would have been even tougher to navigate as a consumer or adviser. Therefore, it seems quite likely that fewer products would have been sold. This seems a case where a good outcome for many trumps a better for one for fewer.In this context, a retreat to fewer defined conditions may give the market the breathing space to create comparable but distinct products at last.Ultimately the ABI SoBP does need to ensure that the basic product it defines is insurable – but I do not believe it should be influencing the market beyond that.There are times when companies recognise that setting the “standard” cover at a deliberately cautious level allows them to take credit for doing something above the industry standard before the ink is even dry on the document. Therefore, while I would urge all with an interest in the CI market to engage with the SoBP when the opportunity arises, the really interesting work will come after as we see the real motivation for some of the changes coming through.I hope this will mean new products with simple claim triggers clearly linked partiallyto diagnosis and partially to observed impact. Others will have different ideas – and so long as some resonate with customers we should have an exciting marketplace to improve our ability to help people when they really need it.COVER ME NOW]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[54COVER ME NOWCover Me Now Protection Portal now combines ‘Buy It Now’ Protection with full range of provider optionsSynaptic Software LimitedAhead of other portals looking to create Buy it Now solutions, Synaptic Software have produced a template for the sale of Protection in the future, offering a genuine option to Buy-it-now with a guaranteed premium and immediate cover.Synaptic Webline technology has traditionally been preferred by the large volume Protection writers. We estimate that over 20% of UK term insurance is sold using Webline’s protection quote and e-commerce portal and infrastructure technology.A reminder of the key capabilities that you can choose to adopt by using both our Synaptic Webline & Cover Me Now propositions:Cover Me Now offers:· Guaranteed premiums based upon just 14 medical questions· Immediate cover or deferred start date of up to 30 days· Market leading user interface design· Option to ‘white label’ the interface to incorporate your brand colours and logos· Integration into your back office to remove the need to re-key unnecessarily· Quickly and easily allows a comparison of ‘Buy Now’ and ‘Apply Now’ prices on one screen· Automatic comparison of level and decreasing term products without the need to request separate quotesExample of firm ‘white label’ version of Cover Me NowThe Product selection screen demonstrates the ability to easily access the market which will include all the major protection providerswho distribute their quotes through Webline. It is important when considering Cover Me Now as an option that other providers’ quotes are compared also.]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[COVER ME NOW55The next screen shows how easy it is to complete protection quotes using Webline with the additional new Quick commission feature, which facilitates commission sacrifice.The screen below shows the simple health questions that will allow the majority of your prospects to avoid further medical assessments and additional underwriting.How to streamline protection sales. The real power of this portal solution is when you see the Cover Me Now option presented alongside standard quotes, offering guaranteed premiums, immediate start and guaranteed acceptance.Call now on 0800 783 4477 to discuss how you could benefit from Cover Me Now, or visit our website for further information www.synaptic.co.uk/covermenow]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Our Multi-Index Funds make it easier to keep everything on track.Active managementSimplicity Cost-effectiveness Ongoing suitabilityMulti-Index Fund RangeIn today’s complex environment, it’s easy for portfolios to veer off-track, but our Multi-Index Funds are bolted to their risk profiles at all times. And because they are actively managed, they can take the best route towards your clients’ goals.Our Multi-Index Funds are largely made up of our index funds so they remain simple and, more importantly, cost effective. We have over £1.7bn* under management in eight risk-targeted funds, each focused on either income or growth. All designed to get your clients where they want to be.0345 070 8684** • fundsales@lgim.com • www.lgim.com/multi-indexThis is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. The value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise, and investors may get back less than they invest. Exchange rate changes may cause the value of investments and the level of any income to rise and fall. Multi-Index funds are sensitive to interest rate changes. At times, especially over shorter timescales, lower risk rated funds may fall in valueby more than higher risk rated funds. Details of the specific and general risks associated with the funds mentioned are contained within the Key Investor Information Documents.*As at 30 June 2017. **Call charges will vary. Square Mile rating applies to Legal & General Multi-Index Funds only. Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 1009418. Registered office: One Coleman Street, London, EC2R 5AA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.]]></page></pages></Search>