<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q3 2016Selection of industry features for the professional adviserSynaptic Software• Introducing the new Risk Rating area in the Synaptic Research Suite• Investment risk – the challenge for advisers around risk - Eric Armstrong• Due Diligence on absolute return funds• Suitability and platform due diligence• Synaptic Webline and the benefits of Multi-Benefit quotes“No-one Here Gets Out Alive” Mark PolsonThe value of adviceInside...›› Theory of adviser evolution - the lang cat›› Abraham Okusanya looks at Retirement Income Modelling›› The value of advice - David Norman, TCF Investments›› Business continuity and succession planning - AEGON›› Drawdown governance – how much income are people taking? - Royal London ›› Building portfolios from the bottom up – Investec Asset Management›› Expanding the reach of protection - SCOR›› A £200billion opportunity - Swiss Re]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Enjoy an easy life with WeblineBuying financial products online has never been easier with the help of the Synaptic Webline portal, which can be accessed forNot only can you compare hundreds of online products against each other, you can also apply online directly into the chosen providers extranet, reducing time and effort usually spent re-keying data.By applying directly from Synaptic Webline firms may be entitled to an extra 10% of additional commission –For more information call us on0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.ukApplying Online - The Myths and Facts• The cost for applying via Webline is exactly the same astrading with the Provider on their site.• Webline portal will take a cut of the plan commission due to the adviser.• Applying via Webline means the data from the quote is populated, avoiding double data entry.• Application process cannot be re-started from within Webline service.• The Providers treat the application in exactly the same way as an application coming in via their extranet.• Advisers are often entitled up to an additional 10%commission when applying from Webline into provider extranet.• The client data is not kept by Webline, the application is input directly onto the provider’s system.• There is no cost to you or the client for sending the application in via Webline.Free to existing customersthis could result in huge gainsyou could even earn more commissionFact MythFactFact MythFact FactFact]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[CONTENTSNo One Here Gets Out Alive 04 Mark Polson, the lang catLongevity and Survival Probability in 06 Retirement Income ModellingAbraham Okusanya, FinalytiQMarket Outlook 10 M&G Multi-Asset team, M&G InvestmentsBuilding portfolios from the bottom-up 12 John Stopford, Investec Asset ManagementThe four pillars: Cost effectiveness 14 Justin Onuekwusi CFA, L&G InvestmentManagementHow to inspire brand loyalty in your clients 16 Neil Cowell, Vanguard Asset ManagementThe value of advice 18 David Norman, TCF InvestmentsAre we professional enough yet? 20 Kaavya Dijendranath, FEBrexit: the Power of Procrastination 22 Chris Darbyshire, Seven Investment ManagementAn introduction to Liontrust,Verbatim 24 JohnHusselbee,Liontrust 2016Your clients’ success is our priority 26 Columbia Threadneedle InvestmentsDue Diligence on Absolute Return Funds 29 Synaptic Software LimitedWhat does the recent Thematic Review Paper on 30 suitability tell us about platform due diligence? Synaptic Software LimitedInvestment risk – the challenge for advisers 32 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Risk Ratings Table 36Drawdown governance – how much income are 42 people taking?Fiona Tait, Royal LondonLife begins at... 43 Fiona Holmes, Royal LondonExpanding the reach of Protection 44 Hannah Cook, SCORBusiness continuity and succession planning – 47 why it shouldn’t be ignoredAegonProtection Insurance – a six out of 10 industry 48 Andrew Wibberley, Alea RiskA £200billion opportunity 50 Ron Wheatcroft, Swiss ReOvercoming the ‘indifference’ challenge 52 Justin Harper, LV=Multi-Benefit service on Synaptic Webline 54 Warren O’Connell & Simon Torr,Synaptic Software Limited3Optimism for the future lies in expertise and ability to changeContact DetailsSynaptic Software Limited Fusion 1, Parkway,Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO157AASales: 0800 783 4477 www.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Hardmannaomi.hardman@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969The range of content included in this edition serves as a reminder of the breadth of expertise required of the modern adviser. The challenge of offering effective financial advice grows all the time. There are references in this edition to the increasing influence of politics, demographics and macro-economics. I hope that you agree that this edition lifts the lid on some interesting topics, and I’d like to thank our varied contributors for their excellent submissions.It takes real wisdom to survey all that is necessary to keep the good ship Advice safe on the high seas – a tribute to the professional qualities of our adviser customers.Synaptic Risk RatingsWe bring your attention to the first ofa series of developments to provide easier access to our Synaptic Risk Rating Service. In addition to the normal publication of the results table, we have created a new area in the main Synaptic Suite log-on area, placing this resource right at your fingertips.We look at our role as making the life of the adviser easier and we hope that these articles reflect that commitment. We offer the reassurance that noother research software provider is as committed for the long term to the UK independent advice market as Synaptic.We believe that stochastics are thekey to planning for different possible financial futures, but it is the expertise of advisers that make it work – long may that continue.Eric ArmstrongEditorThe Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all nights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part thereof.]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4No-one Here Gets Out AliveMark Polson | Founder | the lang catIt’s August as I write this and we’re in the summer lull. I’m in a reflective kind of mood as we take the opportunity to look again at our plans for the year ahead and start to get working on our next adviser guide to platforms.Writing that isn’t going to be easy; mainly because there is such a dearth of interesting new stuff to talk about. First world problems and all that, but very few providers have anything happening which we’d think of as moving the industry on.This in turn has got me thinking about where the next wave of propositions will come from in terms of adviser-facing technology. And I think that’s my theme for this quarter – to what extent can you look to your direct peer-group and competition to get ideas on how to evolve your own propositions?All industries are guilty of being inward- looking and displaying confirmation bias. But I do wonder if financial planning and advice is a little more enthusiastic in this regard than others – very often I’ve heard advisers dismiss different ideas as unworthy of consideration on the basis that they haven’t come from financial planners or advisers.I think that might be a mistake.Here’s a case in point. Over the summer we’ve seen the launch of (yet) another online investing proposition; this time aport from the USA called Scalable Capital. Now, Scalable is a bit of a thorny proposition in terms of actually using it as a way of getting recalcitrant or first-time investorsto get going – for one thing its minimum investment is £10,000.What interests me about it in terms ofhow it might impact advisers’ worlds isits approach to portfolio management. It helpfully sets this out in a 32-page white paper which is worth a read (really). In short, it reacts against modern portfolio theory and Markowitz in favour of working much more closely to risk parameters – in fact its 23 portfolio gradations are all labelled with Value at Risk (VaR) figures. The theory goes that it is far easier to predict risk through modelling than returns, so the modelsare continuously adjusted to ensure they stay on risk budget. This, according to theNobel-winning research that SC quotes, will generally do a much better job of controlling outcomes than mechanistic rebalancing to an asset allocation model.I spent a bit of time poking this stuff with a stick, and while I’m no-one’s idea of a quant, I thought it had some resonance. But it won’t come easy to advisers, and here’s why.Since RDR, the overwhelming trend forfirms has been toward model portfolio usage; whether insourced, off-the-shelf or outsourced to a discretionary manager’s MPS. In recent research we published with CWC Research, we found well over 50%of firms saying they never made asset allocation decisions, let alone individual stock decisions. Virtually all of those portfoliosuse target asset allocations and periodic rebalancing back to target.Is that approach because there’s no alternative, or because it’s what advisers have been educated into wanting, and what]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[5The revolution in terms of how tech can influence the advice profession has only just begun. The big advances almost certainly won’t come from within the sector.adviser platform technology is able to house? The alternative approach of Scalable Capital requires continual monitoring, modelling and trading of the constituent funds and ETFs, and only some of this can be automated through algorithms – at least for the moment.Let’s assume, for a moment, that Scalable’s approach does give better results than efficient-frontier-modern-portfolio-asset- allocated-rebalanced. It might or might not do in real life, but it’s convenient for illustrating the point anyway. For it to take off for advisers it would need to:• Be available across multiple platforms• Be supported by free or near-free trading of ETFs as well as mutual funds• Be largely automated• Have completely different client reporting (constant contract notes etc. wouldn’t help)There are a bunch of tech hurdles in that; all of which are doable (nearly anything in tech is doable with enough energy and money). But more problematic for any provider selling this into advisers would be getting firms to change what they’ve just got used to doing since RDR. With sunset just past, some firms are only now getting to the latter stages of cleaning up their client banks and developinga systemised investment proposition (I’m excluding bespoke, discretionary firms here). How to explain to staff, advisers and clients that actually the approach you’ve just got them happy with isn’t all that and a bag of chips any more?I spoke at a regulatory offsite meeting a while ago at which the nice people expressed some frustration that all they needed advisers to do in order to deal with their latest proclamation on what colour your pants have to be on a Thursday or something was stop for a moment, think how it affected their business, put plans into place and then get on with it.Needless to say, very few of the people in the room had an appropriate understanding of what that means for businesses. It was my pleasure to put them straight; to this day apparently no-one has quite used language like that in any other meeting they’ve been to. I’m taking that as a positive.But here’s the thing. There will come a point when hanging onto something because it’s the last big change you made, or because it’s what the technology you picked allows you to do easily, won’t be the right thing any more. Advisers have ridden out more change than just about any other sector I can think of, and always come out on top.That’s because, in the end, nothing trumps the personal relationship between an adviser and a client. But in an environment where more and more firms are starting to find ways to serve clients remotely and at a lower cost, can we be sure that this trump card will still beup the sleeve of the industry at the next big go-round? How ready are advisers to leave behind the new normal and embrace even more radical changes to working practices?Going back to the regulator for a moment,I think this might be what’s behind its exhortation to foster a ‘culture of challenge’ in firms. In my firm we call it something different and borrow from William Faulkner’s writing tip. We call it ‘killing your darlings’ and it’s also what gave me the title for this column. We can’t hold our existing practices too dearly, or too tightly. Good ideas can come from anywhere.The revolution in terms of how tech can influence the advice profession has only just begun. The big advances almost certainly won’t come from within the sector. The question is whether existing firms will be able to acknowledge that the existing way things are being done (although it’s come a long way) won’t get out of here alive, and pickthe very best from what’s in development, wherever it’s from.]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[6Longevity and Survival Probability in Retirement Income ModellingAbraham Okusanya | Principal | FinalytiQThe fear of dying is right up there on the list of top fears people have. But maybe, the fear of public speaking is even higher on that list. Maybe I’ve got this all wrong but if that’s true, then it seems to me that when the average person goes to a funeral, they’ll rather be in the casket than do the eulogy?But I digress. Perhaps for many people, particularly those approaching retirement, the greatest fear shouldn’t be the fearof untimely death, but that of living too long! Planning for retirement is particularly challenging because we are planning fora finite, but precisely unknown period of time. And without the proverbial crystal ball, estimating clients’ longevity is rather tricky. Yet as part of the financial planning process, advisers are constantly called upon to make judgement/assumptions on how long clients are likely to live.Life Expectancy: A Flawed Measure for Retirement Income PlanningOne common but flawed approach for estimating life expectancy is to simply look at the life expectancy tables, based on the client’s age and sex. For instance, a 65-year- old man in the UK has a life expectancy of 19 years, while a woman of the same age has a life expectancy of 21 years.This approach is flawed, for several reasons. One, life expectancy is the ‘mean’ numberof remaining years and there’s at least a50% chance someone in that age groupwill outlive their life expectancy! But more crucially, it fails to account for improvements in mortality as people get older. The ONS has two types of life expectancy measure;1. the period life expectancy which shows life expectancy at a given period e.g. for a 65-year old male in 2015, and2. the Cohort life expectancy which tracks a given cohort who share the same year of birth and takes account of improvement in mortality.The table below compiled by Birmingham University academic Dr Paul Cox, shows that mortality improvements add about 3 years to life expectancy.Dr Paul Cox (2015) Helping consumers and providers manage defined contribution wealth in retirement.]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[7Table4Survival Probability at age 65Perhaps for many people, particularly those approaching retirement, the greatest fear shouldn’t be the fear of untimely death, but that of livingtoo long!Survival ProbabilityAn obvious way to manage longevity is simply to use an annuity to insure against the risk of living too long. Short of using annuities, longevity in the context of retirement planning is best approached in terms of survival probability. This gives us a clearer idea of the chances that someone will live till a certain age.This is one reason I believe that deterministic cash flow models are inadequate in retirement planning, because the challenge that we are dealing with is by its very nature uncertain and thus probabilistic. As these tables show, there is an 11% chance a 65-year old male will celebrate their 100th birthday and that rises to 15% for a female of the same age. The implication of this is that we need to bring the survival probability into context in retirement income modellingSurvival probability can easily feed into a Monte Carlo model to enable more robust discussions with clients about how long they are likely to live, what the likely success rate of their financial plan is and more importantly what financial resources they have in place in the event of extreme longevity. This enables the planner to calibrate the financial plans accordingly.It’s estimated that around 75% of people over age 65 live as couples and the chance that at least one of a 65-year old couple would live to age 100 is a whopping 24%!Estimating the Real Probability of SuccessConsider a case where a planner determines that a 3% inflation-adjusted withdrawal rate (net of 1% fee) from a 60/40 portfolio hasa 90% probability of success over a 30 year horizon – which means a 10% chance of failure or more precisely a 10% chance that theywill need to make some adjustment to their withdrawal in the event of poor return sequence.Yet, since there’s only a 48% percent change that at least one member of the 65-year old couple is going to live to age 95, the overall probability of failure is actually 4.8% (10% X 48%) – i.e. a whopping 95.2% probability of success! This is because there are two unrelated probabilities here –1. the probability of having a poor sequence of return over a 30-year period AND2. the probability that at least one member of a 65-year old couple is going to survive 30 yearsThe failure of this simple financial plan requires those two events to happen – i.e. poor sequence of return that ruins a 3% withdrawal rate over a 30-year period AND at least one member of the couple to survive 30 years. Those odds are completely independent and unrelated, and the probability of both happening is actually less than the probability of either of them happening. This is inthe realms of what math nerds refer to as ‘conditional probability!’The implication of all these is that longevity is a huge consideration in retirement income planning and it’s an area where financial planning can add real value. Managing longevity risk in the context of retirement is best approached using survival probability, rather than simply inputting a number, like say age 100 into the cashflow tool.]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[10M&G Multi Asset Team Market Outlook July 2016Unusual uncertainty?Financial markets have had a rather turbulent time in 2016, to date. It has been difficult to pinpoint a single cause of all this volatility, especially when looking at the fundamental picture. Market participants who are in the mood to fret have been able to take their pick of things to worry about: Certain US data points, China’s economic slowdown, central bank action, or inaction, politics, and so on.After the initial shock of the UK’s vote to leave the EU on 24 June, a sense of calm appears to have been restored in recent weeks. However, although most questions about the ongoing consequences of the referendum result remain unanswered, for many, attention now turns to the next ‘event’. Over the coming months we will see several meetings of major central banks, political events – including the US presidential election – and undoubtedly some things we do not even know about yet. Market commentators will argue that each event in turn will be critically important for investors, but many will be quickly forgotten as something else takes over the headlines.These phases of turbulence are highly unsettling and can have a negative impact on investor psychology that persists for an extended period, leaving sentiment nervous and fickle. This suggests volatility could easily re-emerge at any time. It feels like thereare heightened levels of uncertainty at the moment, but we must remember uncertainty is a permanent feature of the global investment landscape. Therefore, we have not changed our core approach in dealing with the current environment.For us, as always, it is vital to assess the likely genuine economic impact of any event and then ask ourselves whether we have had enough new information to changeour conclusions about the medium-term attractions of various assets? If not, we would then be on the lookout to exploit any unwarranted shifts in valuation.A shift in beliefs, not factsDespite the high degree of volatility in recent months, overall we do not believe we have seen enough new information in terms of changes to the fundamental picture to revise our view that, in aggregate, the global outlook remains broadly positive.We do recognise the need for cautious optimism, given that global growth hasbeen modest with a significant amountof divergence at sector and regional level. However, our base case at present is that global recession seems unlikely given positive trends in key areas such as US labour market data, easy monetary policy in much of the world, and still low commodity prices.That said, we believe current market conditions require us to be tactical. Thus, careful timing and scaling is of high importance. We understand that volatility can be very uncomfortable, but we believe that those who can tolerate it in the short term could well be rewarded with higher prospective returns over more meaningful time horizons.While we have found little fundamental evidence to support a case for global recession, sentiment has clearly shifted.We believe heightened volatility over the past year or so is attributable to an erosion in confidence about a return to ‘normal’, that is, higher levels of economic growth than those seen since 2008.Where do we find value today?A quick look at a range of conventional valuation metrics reveals the current situation as being one in which deep pessimism about the durability of economic growth prevails. The result has been a preference for assets with higher degrees of certainty about a return of capital, over those with some degree of hope of a higher return on capital. A myopic aversion to short-term volatility is prioritised over potential material upside.This demand for ‘safety’ and capital preservation manifests itself clearly in the very low or even negative real yields on many mainstream government bonds today. This means investors are often effectively paying for the privilege of lending money to developed market governments.The flip side of extremely low levels of return on ‘safety’ assets is elevated prospective returns on ‘risky’ assets. Therefore, selected equity, non-mainstream government bonds and corporate bonds are currently sittingat attractive levels of valuation. However,at such low levels of yield on mainstream government bonds, risk assets do not even have to be abnormally attractively priced in an absolute sense to be attractive to multi-asset investors. The main valuation anomaly we observe today remains the size of the equity-risk premium (see chart), which we believe reflects overly fearful sentiment.]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11Financial markets have had a rather turbulent time in 2016, to date. It has been difficult to pinpoint a single cause of all this volatility, especially when looking at the fundamental picture.It is worth pointing out that, since 2008, a ‘volatility-averse’ approach has been profitable in that biasing portfolios to being long of mainstream government bonds has been rewarded in recent years. This may persist or intensify in the short term but this is a finite game. Ultimately, strong capital gains from bonds come at the expense of future returns– as yields fall, prospective returns decline as investors effectively take some of the future returns up front. We believe the enjoyment of this journey has distracted investors from the fact that it is unsustainable. Ultimately, gravity reasserts itself and ignoring this could prove very risky indeed.Equities offer compelling real yield versus bondsGiven the evolution of economic beliefs towards a more pessimistic view of the world, together with the elevated equity-risk premium and credit spreads, the most appropriate strategy from here would seem to be to take on some of the volatility associated with ‘risk’ assets and avoid exposure to expensive ’safety’.We believe the current obsession with volatility is counter-productive and missesthe point about what actually matters on a multi-year view. Owning assets that have in the recent past delivered good returns but now stand at valuations that imply this cannot be repeated, is a very dangerous strategy.M&G July 2016Source: Datastream, Bloomberg, 30 April 2016. World equity proxy is MSCI World. World government bond proxy is the BofA Merrill Lynch Global Government Index. All data is inflation-adjustedWe believe the current obsession with volatility is counter-productive and misses the point about what actually matters on a multi-year view.For financial advisers only. Not for onward distribution. No other persons should rely on any information contained within. This Financial Promotion is issued by M&G Securities Limited which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority in the UK and provides investment products. The company’s registered office is Laurence Pountney Hill, London EC4R 0HH. Registered in England No. 90776.]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12Building portfolios from the bottom-upJohn Stopford | Head of Multi-Asset Income | Investec Asset ManagementOne of the aspects that we consider key in delivering a successful defensive return strategy – one that can improve an investor’s abilityto withstand losses and compound gains in order to meet their desired outcome – is the importance of building portfolios from the bottom-up.The best offence is a good defenceWe believe it is important to recognise the effectiveness of a bottom-up approach to investment selection and to understandhow individual holdings perform in different market conditions. After years of low interest rates following the financial crisis, many assets may look expensive when viewed using traditional valuation metrics.We think it best to avoid constructing portfolios based on simplistic, top-down ideas of value, and instead take a cautious and forensic approach to picking investments, with a focus on higher-quality assets heldin a conservative fashion. By doing this, webelieve, the severity of drawdowns can be reduced. The process requires investors take the time to thoroughly understand the true nature of their exposures by building their portfolio from the ‘bottom-up’.The chart opposite shows the maximum drawdowns experienced by different strategies which adopt a more or less conservative approach to asset selection in some of the key pro-growth asset classes. The results may be surprising to some, however, they validate our belief that by understanding asset class behaviours we are able to build a quality portfolio which can achieve a desired outcome.After years oflow interest rates following the financial crisis, many assets may look expensive when viewed using traditional valuation metrics.]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[130 -10 -20 -30 -40 -50 -60 -70-4%-47%-49%MSCI World qualityMSCI World high dividend yieldGlobal high yield BBB/BB only Global high yield (CCC)-57%Equities-62% MSCI WorldHigh yieldEmerging market debtEM Sovereign debt (local, hedged) EM Sovereign debt (local, USD)-31%-22%The Investec Diversified income Fund aims to fill the role that income can no longer fill.A defensive multi-asset fund, it seeks to provide attractive income with long-term growth.• Attractive income - aims to provide 4-6% p.a.•• Sustainable income - global multi-asset portfolio seeking to grow capital• Lower volatility - historic volatility less than 50% of UK equities• Taxefficiency-classifiedasan‘interest-paying’fund• Activity managed - by co-Head of Multi-Asset Income John Stopford and team. *Gross of fees, over a 3-year rolling period. This is an aim and not guaranteed.Maximum drawdown over 10 yearsWithin equities, the perception that a company’s high dividend yield conveys protection to its investors is erroneous. Simply because a company is paying outa high proportion of its earnings does not mean that there should be confidence in the sustainability of its business model or that its management are focused on maximizing the interests of shareholders. It can, instead, mean that the company is in distress or that investors have forced its share price down in anticipation of a cut in the dividend.Similarly, rather than looking at the immediate attractions of high yield bonds, a more defensive approach aims to understand a company’s relative profitability, earnings stability and debt-burden. We define businesses which compare favourably on these grounds, whether considered froma debt or equity perspective, as ‘quality’ corporations allowing us to judge the sustainability of the income they offer and properly compare their relative valuations.Source: Bloomberg, Investec Asset Management, May 2016As shown in the chart within the high yield asset class, it can be seen that those at the bottom of the credit rating spectrum (and whose average yield over the last 10 years has been nearly double that of their more highly rated peers) suffered a drawdown nearly 20 percentage points worse than the less risky BBB/BB issues.Finally, within emerging market debt,a thorough understanding of the risksposed by the nation’s debt also requiresan intricate understanding of its currency markets. In many cases the volatility of an emerging economy’s exchange rate will far outweigh that of its bond market and so expose investors to risks that extend beyond a county’s ability to services its debts. Itis therefore important to consider such investments on a currency hedged basis when comparing their relative valuations and to analyse their currency separately.Avoid unnecessary diversificationBy applying a bottom-up approach across the Investec Diversified Income Fund’s portfolio, we believe investors gain a further advantage: the avoidance of ‘diworsification’. This is the situation in which investments are madein the hope of diversification but actually have the effect of doing little if anythingto reduce overall risk and instead merely increase trading costs and erode the portfolio manager’s knowledge of and conviction in their investments.ConclusionBy consistently applying a defensivequality orientated bottom-up approach to investment selection within the Investec Diversified Income Fund, we believe, we are in a better position to produce a portfolio with structural integrity, making us better equipped to handle episodes of market weakness. This requires an intense focus on bottom-up analysis and the consideration of positionson a holistic basis, rather than in isolation. By reducing the impact of drawdowns on the portfolio, investors are able to improve the probability of meeting their goals over the long run.For further information please visit www.investecassetmanagement.com/DIFTHIS COMMUNICATION IS DIRECTED ONLY AT PROFESSIONAL FINANCIAL ADVISORS. IT SHOULD NOT BE DISTRIBUTED TO, OR RELIED ON BY PRIVATE CUSTOMERS. Past performance should not be taken as a guide to future returns. The value of investments can go down as well as up and your clients could end up with less than they invested. Your clients’ capital is at risk. Please note that equities rankin the lowest tier on the capital structure so, in the case of a company bankruptcy, bond holders would get paid before equity owners. Fund ratings may be provided by independent rating agencies based on a range of investment criteria and do not constitute investment advice by Investec Asset Management. English language copies of the Funds’ prospectuses, Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) and report and accounts are available from Investec Asset Management. TheFund may invest more than 35% of their assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state. The Funds are domiciled in the UK. The Fund Prospectus and Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) may be obtained from www.investecassetmanagement.com.Percentage (%)]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[14The four pillars: Cost effectivenessJustin Onuekwusi CFA | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementThe four Pillars of LGIM’s Multi-Index FundWith the ongoingreality of low-interest on fixed-income assets, low global economic growth and uncertain, volatile markets, the four pillars of a successful multi-asset solution are evenmore critical.This quarter we discuss the crucial role that costs play in helping investors achieve their investment goals and allowing advisers to close the ‘advice gap’.Fees matterFees matter in multi-asset funds because if investors pay less, then more of their moneyremains invested in the market. This amount, which may only be small in a single year,will start to add up over time with the extra investment compounding as the market (hopefully) delivers positive long term growth.This table provides an example of fees paid on different kinds of investment – here we’reFees Paidcomparing the OCF of I class units in our Multi-Index range, at 0.31%, with an average actively-managed multi-asset fund of 1.53%. This is just an illustration and assumes both funds deliver a uniform 6.9% annual growth before fees on a £100,000 investment.As you can see, the difference in the amount of money paid in fees is quite substantial. Another way of looking at it is examining the difference in investment returns. The chart opposite illustrates percentage growth after fees, again assuming a uniform 6.9% annual growth rate. You can see the difference in returns exponentially widening over time.Legal & General Multi-Index range – I class OCF 0.31%UK actively managed multi- asset fund – average peer ‘clean’ OCF 1.53*%Difference10 years£4,051£18,725£14,67420 years£11,791£50,382£38,59130 years£27,219£106,270£79,051*Source: Lipper, average active multi-asset fund fee - IA 40-85 sector as at 30 June 2016]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[15In reality, of course, no two funds will perform exactly the same, but the effect of the fees means that a traditional multi-asset portfolio that only invests in actively managed funds needs to generate significant additional performance just to keep pace with the return on our Multi-Index range.Closing the advice gap: Using low- cost index componentsMany advisers are choosing to focus on high-net-worth clients, leaving the moderate earning middle ground to fall into an ‘advice gap’ between those that have no investable assets and high-net-worth clients.Cost-effective multi-asset risk-targeted funds provide the kind of solution that can help advisers close the advice gap by providing a solution for investors that fall into the gap. By ensuring ongoing suitability, with an emphasis on cost and transparency, advisers can focus on helping clients at a much broader range of fee levels.Closing the advice gap requires closing the cost gap. Our Multi-Index Funds offer superb value for money by drawing on our decades of index expertise, we use straightforward transparent index fund building blocks for a large proportion of our exposure to equities and bonds. In addition to this, within Multi- Index Income Fund range we make use of certain dividend enhanced ETFs. We conduct thorough due diligence and only invest in physical ETFs.Together, this helps us offer transparent, high-quality asset allocation and wide diversification at a very low cost.Price is what you pay, value is what you getHowever, while fees are extremely important, they are by no means the only factor that needs to be taken into account when choosing an investment. Suitability for the client’s needs and overall value for money have to be the main considerations. You’ll also need to carefully consider the strengths andGraph is for illustration purposes only, based on hypothetical 6.9% growth per annum.Graph is for illustration purposes only, based on hypothetical 6.9% growth per annum.weaknesses of different multi-asset funds, including their diversification, whether they are risk-targeted or not and to which risk profiling system, how they manage their asset allocation, and the expertise of the team behind them.However, whichever fund you choose and whether it is acting as the core of a portfolio or a stand-alone holding, it is always important to remember the profound impact that fund management fees can have on long-term investment returns.]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[16How to inspire brand loyalty in your clientsNeil Cowell | Head of Retail Sales | Vanguard Asset ManagementBrand loyalty is harder than ever to achieve, thanks to technological advances that have made it easy for a new breed of flexible and disruptive businesses to flourish. Amazon, Uber and Airbnb are all examples of these: brands that challenge old business models, leaving established companies wondering where they went wrong.Customers who have grown up in this world - millennials (people who are currently aged 18-33) - will make up 75% of the global workforce in ten years’ time. If they’re three quarters of the global workforce, they’re also going to be a large slice of your potential client book.So how do you attract and retain clients for whom a traditional sense of brand loyalty is a thing of the past? In this article, I’ll discuss two ways of fostering brand loyalty: having a sense of purpose and making and keeping your promises.According to Michael Hayman, who we were lucky enough to have speak at our Investment Symposium earlier this year, having a senseof mission is more important than ever. Inhis book, Mission, he explains that successful businesses now need to explain why they exist. It’s not enough to focus simply on products or solutions – that’s what you do. Nor is it enough to focus on processes and people – that’s how you to it. The mission provides the why.To convey a sense of mission, first of all you need to create one that feels authentic to you and your business. At Vanguard, we see our mission as follows: to take a stand forall investors, to treat them fairly, and to give them the best chance for investment success. We try to ensure that everything we do links back to that core purpose. When defining your mission, it needs to be convincing not only for you, but for your whole team. The best communicators of your firm’s missionwill be those of your employees who are inspired by it, and get a sense of meaning from it.The next step is to define this mission at every touch point you have with your client, especially on your website and on any literature you produce.The second important factor that has an impact on brand loyalty is to do with the promises you make to clients. It’s not onlyIt’s not enough to focus simply on products or solutions – that’s what you do. Nor is it enough to focus on processes and people – that’s how you to it. The mission provides the why.]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[17While brand loyalty can be an elusive quality to inspire, creating and articulating an authentic sense of mission can be a powerful tool for differentiation.about keeping your promises, but also about ensuring you make the right ones in the first place, as well as understanding that even an implied promise needs to be kept.Many advisers have implicitly based their client ‘promise’ on an uncontrollable outcome, such as the performance of their chosen asset classes and managers. Butas we’ve seen over recent turbulent years, performance-based promises can quickly and easily destroy credibility. It’s better to anchor a service promise only on things that you can confidently predict and control.A service promise should focus specifically on client needs, with everything you do being a means to a client’s end. You can demonstrate this to your client by relating your actions explicitly and clearly to your promise, for example saying, “As promised, here is your quarterly review statement. Let me talk you through it, in light of your plan to retire five years early.” An adviser’s brochure should let a prospective client know exactly what is being promised. However, don’t fall into the trapof overpromising. It’s tempting to think that the more you promise a client, the better.It’s actually best practice to keep promisesto a credible minimum. The longer a list of promises is, the less credible it is, and clients begin to doubt whether a firm can really deliver. By making and delivering a shorter and more achievable list of promises, you canstart building trust with clients. Perceptions are built up by repeated experiences – if you continually exceed service expectations by delivering on your promises again and again, you will create powerful client loyalty.How can you ensure you deliver on your promises? Work back from the desired outcome for your client by asking yourself what it will take to make this a realityfor them.each step of the process must be understood, planned and resourced. So, understanding your firm’s talents and capabilities should inform the promise you make to your clients in the first place.While brand loyalty can be an elusive quality to inspire, creating and articulating an authentic sense of mission can be a powerful tool for differentiation. This, coupled with a solid record of delivering on your promises, will help your firm attract and retain clients.This information is directed at professional investors and should not be distributed to, or relied upon by, retail investors. It is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments.This information is designed for use by, and is directed only at, persons resident in the UK.The opinions expressed in this article are those of individual author and may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Limited.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.© 2016 Vanguard Asset Management, Limited. All rights reserved.A service promise should focus specifically on client needs, with everything you do being a means to a client’s end.This will highlight the dependencies needed in order for each step to become a reality. What you are doing here is process mapping, and this will enable you to see gaps in your ability to provide what’s needed or any other factors that are a risk to the promise that you’re making. It’s impossible to fully deliver on the promise you’re making unless you know what is involved in making it happen;]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[18The Value of AdviceDavid Norman | CEO | TCF Investment and MAPSThe role of industries and the companies within them is to generate value for themselves. They do this by creating value for customers and then sharing in this value. If companies don’t add value, for example, if their jewellery is “crap” (as Gerald Ratner famously said about his own company’s products) then the customer stops buying the product and the company goes bust (Ratner wiped £500m off the value of his company with his infamous quote).Customers are happy to share some of their value with industries that generate value for them. People pay the car industry because they value the ability to get them safely and reliably from A to B.The Financial Services industry and the companies within it create value for themselves. Financial Services has many layers in the complete value chain – when investing, for example, there are financial advisers, platforms, CRM systems, messaging services, stockbrokers, foreign exchange dealers, fund managers, wrapper providers etc., all of whom extract (to varying degrees) some of the value. But, of course, without the customers’ money in the first place there is no value for any element of the value chain to share in! So it is often the element closest to the customer that can demand the largest share of the value chain.In simple terms we might think of three key elements – manufacturer (who assembles the product), distributor (who moves the product from the manufacturer to the customer and the brand (that finds the customer) and sells the product/service.An example might help:Intel is a microchip manufacturer. It supplies chips to many computer brands such asDell, HP etc. If it had no relationship orvalue to the customer, then it would be a simple commodity and have to take theprice demanded by the more powerful (in a customer relationship sense) brands. But Intel spends money on advertising to convince the customer of the value of the “Intel Inside” effect – faster, better, smarter processors. And thus demands a greater share of the value chain because they are happy to pay more for a PC with an Intel chip inside.Brands (close to the customer) dominate value chainsReturning to Financial Services, it is the financial adviser / planner that has the customer relationship (finding the customers, building the advice plan, pulling togetherthe investment, protection tax wrapper components and taking the risk of complaint / compensation for errors). But oddly, historically, the adviser didn’t get the largest share of the value chain. This is a hangover from pre-RDR days.]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[19Without the customers’ money in the first place there is no value for any element of the value chain to share in! So it is often the element closest to the customer that can demand the largest share of the value chain.The dominant brand was the product provider with the IFA just the distributor, indeed the investment industry will often still refer to IFAs as “a distribution channel”. The Brand (provider) pulled the tax wrapper and investment components together, managed the customer communication (statements and valuations), provided the customer call centre, and took the strain of new business. They also paid the distributor a fee (known as commission) for finding “their” customers!Pre RDRBut the world is changing – slowly but surely. Advisers are starting to demand more ofthe value chain. They, after all, are takingon more of the role of a brand – service, reporting, CRM and risk!In the process, they are demanding and will rightly continue to demand more of the value chain. An old-fashioned fund of fund (with trail commission, underlying funds, supermarket rebates, dealing fee) might have cost the customer 4.4% pa – out of which the IFA was paid 0.5% pa (only 11% of the value chain). Today many advisers and planners are trying to keep the totalcustomer cost to a maximum of 2% pa and charge an ongoing advice / servicing fee of 0.75% pa (still only 38% of the value chain).The New Value ChainThe overall price charged (or value extracted) by the whole value chain is under pressure– partly from regulators but also fromthe simple fact that for the investment component the long run returns of asset classes cannot sustain high cost levels. Historically (over the last 50 years or so) Equities and Gilts in the UK have returned about 5% and 2% over inflation respectively (source: Barclays Equity Gilt Study 2016).So a typical 60:40 split would generate 3.8% pa. Trying to charge more than 2% is just not sustainable – because the customer will rightly say, “you are taking more than half the total value – and it’s my money you are putting at risk!”The Other Advice GapAn issue for advisers wanting to grow their share of value is that they need scale and good processes to drive the price of the components (CRM, Platform, Investment, PI etc.) down. And some of thesecomponents e.g. fund managers, have spent many years investing in the brands to defend / argue their value.If a discretionary manager or fund offund manager wants 0.5% pa (plus VATand dealing), the underlying funds in the portfolio have an average fee of 0.7% pa and the platform wants 0.4% pa (plus tax wrappers) – then there is precious little gap left for an advice fee!One way the advisers (and fund managers) are driving down costs is by the useof passive funds. A broadly diversified portfolio of passive funds and ETFs canbe constructed for around 0.25 % pa or less. Finding more efficient platforms with inclusive dealing fees may cost around 0.3% pa. Using risk managed models or advisory portfolios can reduce or remove the DFM fee. Assuming a DFM of say 0.3% pa inc. VAT then the total cost would come it at around 0.85% pa – for a well-diversifiedrisk managed portfolio. Plenty of room fora 0.85% pa advice / service fee and still coming in at less than 2% pa total cost – and with the adviser rightly taking half of the value.The next challenge for advisers and planners is how to show that they are worth 0.85% pa – we will look at that in the next article.]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[20Are we professional enough yet?Kaavya Dijendranath | Marketing specialist | FELet’s for a moment rewind to the summer of 2012 – the personal finance section of the Daily Telegraph published a research study that found that the television character most closely associated with the term ‘’financial adviser’’ was the market trader Del Boy, from the popular sitcom Only Fools and Horses.It’s no wonder the Financial Conduct Authority’s most far reaching set of regulation, more fondly called the Retail Distribution Review was enforced in December that year. The RDR set out to overturn such negative stereotypes of advisers by making the provision of financial advice to investors more professional and fair.At the time, most advisers were broadly supportive, with a number of adviser networks and trade bodies backing the Personal Finance Society’s Consumer Confidence Campaign that used the RDR to change consumers’ views and build trust in financial advice.Fast forward to 2016 and one can’t helpbut wonder if the objectives of RDR havebeen fully achieved? Was the overall bid for professionalism lost in the detail of the more controversial aspects of the regulation (fines, fees, future of financial advice...)? Has the RDR really helped to promote and build trust in the financial advisory profession?Investor behaviour research published in the last few months has indicated that the rift between advisers and investors still exists. Boring Money’s Spring Census published in April 2016 that surveyed 2,042 UK adults found that only 8% of adults are preparedto pay more than £100 an hour for advice.A third of the households with £100,000 to £150,000 of savings and investments said they would pay up to just £50 an hour for advice – the same percentage said they would not be prepared to pay anything for service.The report further highlighted the fact that 25.45 million UK adults have a savings or investment product, yet just 4.1 million adults are reported to be in an ongoing relationship with an adviser. Similar research from Legg Mason found that 60% of the 5,000 over 40 high net worth individuals were not prepared to pay anything for advice. Adam Gent, Head of UK sales at Legg Mason said that the research was rather surprising three years after the introduction of the RDR...So why don’t people engage in financial advice?Engage Insight research sponsored by IRESS highlights the lack of trust in financial advisers by the wider public as one of the top reasons. FT Adviser analysis around this issue points to the issue of lack of perceived value in advice compared to other professions.Improving professionalism is key to building trust and the RDR set out to achieve this byOnly 8% of adults are prepared to pay more than £100 an hour for advice.]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[2125.45 million UK adults have a savings or investment product, yet just 4.1 million adults are reported to be in an ongoing relationship with an adviser.making professional qualifications mandatory and setting out requirements for CPD inthe run up to 2012. But at the time, in the midst of having to rebuild business modelsto accommodate fees and pass a number of exams, CPD was generally viewed as just another box to tick in order to attain the required Statement of Professional Standing (Professional Adviser, 2016).However, investing more time and resource into well diversified CPD programmes can be of great value to advisers. Tom Hegarty from New Model Business Academy views CPDas an extremely rewarding process which is beneficial not just for an adviser or his/her firm but also the investors and clients that they serve.Although the FCA specifies within its training and competence requirements that a number of areas should be covered under the CPD rules, it does not recommend any guidelines or provide a framework on what these areas should be. Tom adds that often advisers pick up their 35 hours in a ‘piecemeal’ fashion which means that too many advisers arestill not reaping the benefits on offer from a balanced and tailored personalised CPD plan. (‘’Making sure CPD is on your side’’, Professional Adviser, 2016)Staying relevant in today’s fast paced financial landscape is a concern for many advisers, asthey are faced with the challenge of having to alter their propositions in response to the rise of D2C platforms, self-investing websites, robo-advice and a growing new millennial market.A thoughtfully created CPD plan covering areas such as technology, business development, personal development and industry insight can help advisers stay up toby providing additional training, knowledge and ongoing support. This takes the formof quarterly webinars, educational content, weekly reviews and most importantly through exclusive investment forums.FE conducted its Regional Investment Forums in ten locations across the country in the last year offering clients structured CPD certified content and insight.Investor behaviour research published in the last few months has indicated that the rift between advisers and investors still exists.date and current– equipping them with the tools to identify opportunities and protect themselves from threats in their commercial and regulatory environments. CPD accredited content is now readily available from a number of independent industry bodies, the financial and trade press but it should go beyond reading articles - Advisers stand to benefit from seeking more in depth learning that can enhance the way they provide advice.After a decade of helping advisers with their research and investment needs, FE has expanded its commitment to advisersEarlier this year, FE also launched a dedicated FE Training Academy that offers customised modular training to advisers and paraplanners to help them get the most of the services and tools they use from us. Following the CPD accredited training and examination, Advisers can qualify as ‘FE Analytics certified’.Since its launch, the certification has been quick to be adopted as it not only indicates a level of knowledge of FE Analytics but also the key skills involved in researching investments and providing robust investment advice.]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[22Brexit: The Power of ProcrastinationChris Darbyshire | Chief Investment Officer | Seven Investment ManagementWelcome to the new UK after its encounter with direct democracy. Currently, it’s a shambles. No-one yet knows what ‘Leave’ actually means – there certainly wasn’t any attempt to describe it on the voter slip. We do at least have a leader, but the country is without a plan, or an effective opposition at a time of great uncertainty. Meanwhile we are at the mercy of capital markets, who have delivered their immediate ‘vote’ through a collapse in Sterling to levels last seen in 1985.The referendum result pits 52% of the country against the other 48% – hardly a recipe for social harmony. If direct democracy is about reflecting the will of the people, then Scotland’s resounding vote in favour of ‘Remain’ effectively ends the 300-year old Union. They didn’t put that on the ballot.We have a Prime Minister who actually voted for ‘Remain’. May can be expected to continue making the right noises about enforcing the will of the people, simultaneously placating the Eurosceptic wing of the party. The fact is, however, that about 60% of Tory MPs voted to ‘Remain’ in the European Union. On the other side of the chamber, about 95% of Labour MPs voted to ‘Remain’, meaning about three quarters of all MPs voted to ‘Remain’. This majority must now preside over legislation to implement a policy they think is wrong.All the while, confidence in the UK economy will be ailing, companies will refrain from making investments, property markets will be in a mini-collapse and the media will be gleefully peddling new scare stories of the economic, rather than the immigration kind.The electorate is fickle - opinion polls will show public opinion changing due to an uptick in inflation, economic distress and job insecurity. ‘Bremorse’ is already rampant. Politicians will get the blame, and they will want to adjust their positions. A vote of no confidence in the Government only requires a simple majority to succeed, so there is a very real possibility that the referendum result is ‘trumped’ by a General Election in which the same battle is fought again, this time with the benefit of hindsight.Without an overwhelmingly strong mandate either from the electorate or from Parliament, therefore, Brexit may not be a foregone conclusion. Even if it progresses, it is virtually inconceivable that any feasible form of Brexit will meet the expectations of ‘Leave’ voters. Not only would the scale of the projectThe referendum result pits 52% of the country against the other 48% – hardly a recipe for social harmony.]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[23Without an overwhelmingly strong mandate either from the electorate or from Parliament, therefore, Brexit may not be a foregone conclusion. Even if it progresses, it is virtually inconceivable that any feasible form of Brexit will meet the expectations of ‘Leave’ voters.overwhelm Britain’s civil service resources,but Britain’s negotiating team will have aweak political mandate, and will be waryof the rug of popular support being pulledout from underneath them at any time. Economic distress in the UK will further whet the appetite of European negotiators for a tough deal. It is highly unlikely that we will emerge with anything other than broadly the same arrangements, but without a voice in Europe. Politicians will get the blame for having deluded voters as to what could be achieved – turning public opinion against the ‘Leave’ camp.There never was a more poisoned chalice for an incoming Prime Minister. Absent a General Election, the best negotiating position seems to be to play for time. Time to see how the economy, the housing market, the commercial property market and the banking sector develop. Time to assess the extent of Bremorse. Time to develop a Brexit negotiating team, and a plan. Time to let events play out and, frankly, hope for a ‘Get Out of Jail Free’ card.The recent robust performance of our portfolios has been dominated by exposure to foreign currency-denominated assets, whose values have appreciated in proportion to the decline in Sterling. The focus on potential Sterling weakness was a conscious decision on our part, made easier by a series of increasinglyweak UK economic data before the referendum. Our holdings in gold, alternatives and US government bonds also helped. These positions offset the initial decline in the levels of most stockmarkets, although then rallied to pre-referendum highs.Looking forwards, we walk a difficult line between the role of foreign currencies as asafe haven and the potential for a good Brexit outcome to boost Sterling. I would characterise the path of our portfolios as being driven more by politics, rather than economics or markets, than at any time in their history.The quick resolution of the Conservative leadership contest removed one source of political uncertainty and delay, but a ‘good Brexit’ is still by no means assured. Political developments will continue to have a bearing on our positioning, especially in currencies. Meanwhile, any economic impact is likelyto be centred on the UK and, to a lesser extent, continental Europe. Therefore wehave repositioned our stockmarket holdings tactically away from the UK and Europe, and towards the US, while maintaining a significant investment in Asia. We feel confident thatthe US economy is on a sound footing and economic growth there is likely to surprise to the upside. This makes it possible for US profits to get back on track after 18 months in thedoldrums, and an increase in US economic activity is generally good for larger Asian companies too. The US stockmarket is not cheap in aggregate, but our value strategy puts an emphasis on stocks trading at more attractive valuations, where we see better medium-term prospects.So while currencies are working well at the moment as a risk management device, we also hope to find more alternatives that can help preserve capital in a wide range of market conditions.Seven Investment Management LLP is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Member of the London Stock Exchange. Registered office: 55 Bishopsgate, London EC2N 3AS. Registered in England and Wales No. OC378740Contact detailsFor further information about Seven Investment ManagementT: 020 7760 8777 W: www.7im.co.uk]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24An introduction to LiontrustJohn Husselbee | Fund manager | Liontrust 2016Verbatim Asset Management is an independent asset management company who provide a range of risk target managed investment solutions. We work closely with some of the most respected names in the fund management industry to offer a range of multi asset funds, model portfolios and a unique discretionary portfolio service. All of our solutions are guided by the core principles of our investment process and philosophy, allowing advisers to recommend solutions for their clients that will deliver in line with agreed client expectations.Liontrust, one of the leading names in fund management, were recently appointed to run the mandate for the entire FP Verbatim Growth Fund Range following their success in running portfolios FP Verbatim 4 andFP Verbatim 6. Below, we hear from John Husselbee, fund manager, on the processes they apply in running client money.Our Multi-Manager Multi-Asset processat Liontrust has risk at its core, with every portfolio run within volatility bands and targeting a return appropriate to those bands. Employed on FP Verbatim Growth fund range since 1st July 2016, the process is designedto achieve two main objectives. The first isto target the outcome expected by investors in terms of risk, as measured by volatility, which enables them to select an appropriate portfolio; the second is to maximise the return for each level of risk.While returns will always depend on movements in underlying markets, the strictvolatility bands on our portfolios are designed to ensure more consistent outcomes for investors.There are four stages to our process,strategic asset allocation (SAA), tactical asset allocation (TAA), fund selection and portfolio construction. Risk management is central to each of these stages and the portfolios are designed to provide diversification across asset classes, geographical regions and investment style in order to enhance the risk- adjusted returns.As stated, all of our portfolios have a distinct risk profile, expressed in terms of target volatility.Each year, we collate and analyse historical returns and volatilities of a range of asset classes, as well as their correlations witheach other, to determine the strategic asset allocation that should meet the volatility targets for each portfolio over the long-term. When building the SAA, we assume the historic characteristics of different asset classes provide a reasonable guide to their future behaviour.This is essentially the default asset allocation should we have no views on the relative attractiveness of different asset classes. Of course, we do have views on relative value and these will influence the tactical asset allocation stage, increasing exposure when assets look cheap and reducing it when they appear expensive.To work out tactical tilts, (see Fig.1) we first rate the overall investment environment– taking into account valuation levels and investor sentiment – rating it, and then each asset, from one to five. We review several factors in determining our scores, such asthe macroeconomic environment (growth, interest rates, inflation), where we are in the business cycle and valuations (both absolute and relative). We may also use technical analysis to help understand short-term market movements to aid the short-term timing of such decisions including moving averages, RSI, and bull/bear ratios.]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[25Strategic Assset Allocation Current Assset Allocation1 Year5.16%3 Year*16.61%5 Year32.40%Front 1st day of trading40.76%1 Year1.52%3 Year*15.55%5 Year28.11%Front 1st day of trading50.05%We believe in backing our asset allocation policy with conviction.We believe in backing our asset allocation policy with conviction and when mandated an unconstrained portfolio, it is not uncommon to see a zero weighting in unfavoured asset classes or regions.relevant as a smaller number of discretionary and wealth managers control an ever larger proportion of assets in the retail market. Funds can grow to a size that can detrimentally impact performance.POTENTIAL RETURNSThe graphs below show potential returns at 5%, 50% and 95% for the given risk profiles against the actual corresponding Verbatim fund performance since launch in 2010.Figure 1 – FP Verbatim Portfolio 4 June 2016Fund selection is the next stage and a keyarea where we look to add value: we invest in a range of funds, including active, passive and alternative investment strategies. Our analysis has shown that many funds with headline- grabbing cumulative returns have been remarkably inconsistent when analysed on a discrete basis. Often, one period of extreme outperformance can mask subsequent longer- term underperformance, so we will never look at cumulative performance in isolation. For us, the key elements that should underpin fund selection are investment process, plus manager experience, knowledge and remuneration.Our selection process incorporates quantitative and qualitative analysis. The quantitative allows us to highlight attractive opportunities in the investment universe of approximately 5,000 funds, with the aim to identify managers with a process that consistently outperforms an appropriate benchmark.We are looking to establish if a fund’s return has been generated by genuine manager skill or if it is more down to chance, and if the manager is consistent in the application of his or her process.Having passed through the quantitative process, the funds are then subject to a qualitative review that looks at additional characteristics and risks and typically involves us meeting the managers.Key factors include the size of a fund andhow much it has recently enjoyed inflows or suffered outflows. This is becoming increasinglyStyle – and style drift – is another part of our analysis and can be particularly important considering the strict volatility bands on the portfolios. We select funds and managers that complement each other in terms of style, so it is key they maintain their approach and do not drift away from it. If they do, this is a reason for us to sell out of a fund.A large part of our work is identifying key personnel who have historically contributed to a fund’s performance and we always meet individuals who are likely to have a materialimpact on future returns – we conduct more than 200 detailed one-to-one manager meetings each year.We are keen to understand the motivations of a fund’s key contributors. This includes the remuneration of fund managers but we also evaluate changes in the contentment and commitment of managers, which can be a warning signal of a future deterioration in performance.Source - FE ANAYSIST* Userdefinedperformance30/06/2013to30/062016Overall ** User defined performance 01/03/2010 to 30/06/2016 OverallDisclaimer:The views expressed are correct only at the time of publication andare subject to change. This material is confidential and intended solely for the use of the person/s to whom it is given or sent and may not be copied, reproduced or given in whole or in part, to any person. It is not an invitation to subscribe and is only intended to provide information and opinion. Nothing contained within this document constitutes investment, legal, tax or any other advice. It should not be relied upon when making an investment or other decision. Returns do not take account of platform, product provider or Adviser fees. Any figures shown have not been externally audited. The value of investmentsand any income may go down as well as up and will depend on the fluctuations of investments and financial markets outside of the control of Liontrust Investment Solutions Limited. As a result a client may not get back the amount originally invested. Past performance is not indicative of future performance and any reference to a security or fund is not a recommendation to buy or sell. This material is issued and approved by Liontrust Investment Solutions Limited, authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. FRN: 495713Liontrust Investment Solutions Limited2 Savoy Court, London WC2R 0EZBroker Sales +44(0)20 7412 1777 Administration and Dealing 0844 892 1007 Email admin@liontrust.co.ukWebsite www.liontrust.co.ukAuthorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26FINDING THE RIGHT BALANCE IN LIFEMULTI ASSET FUNDSA solution to your clients’ goalsWith over 20 years’ experience in managing multi-asset funds, our team aims to achieve the right balance of asset classes, actively adapting to changing market conditions.Threadneedle Dynamic Real Return FundnAn unconstrained, dynamically managed asset allocation fundnAims to deliver strong real returns while smoothing out volatilitynDelivered in excess of CPI + 4% since launch, with less than two thirds the volatility of equities*Threadneedle Global Multi Asset Income FundnA straightforward fund aiming to deliver a sustainable level of income while growing your clients’ capital long termnTop decile performance since launch**With a track record of strong risk-adjusted returns, your clients can relax knowing that their success is our priority.AGlobal Multi Asset Income Fund Dynamic Real Return Fund columbiathreadneedle.co.uk/multiassetinvestingImportant Information. For Professional and/or Qualified Investors only (not to be used with or passed on to retail clients). Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income is not guaranteed and can go down as well as up and may be affected by exchange rate fluctuations. This means that an investor may not get back the amount invested. *Source: Factset, gross of fees since launch 18.06.2013 to 30.06.2016. Volatility of equities measured as MSCI World Index (gross). **Source: Morningstar, net of fees since launch 31.07.2014 to 30.06.2016. Ranked within the IA Mixed Invest. 20-60% shares sector. Ratings as at July 2016. Threadneedle Opportunity Investment Funds (TOIF) is an open-ended investment company structured as an umbrella company, incorporated in England and Wales, authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) as a UCITS scheme. This material is for information only and does not constitute an offer or solicitation of an order to buy or sell any securities or other financial instruments, or to provide investment advice or services. Subscriptions to a Fund may only be made on the basis of the current Prospectus and the Key Investor Information Document, as well as the latest annual or interim reports and the applicable terms & conditions. Please refer to the ‘Risk Factors’ section of the Prospectus for all risks applicable to investing in any fund and specifically this Fund. Issued by Threadneedle Investment Services Limited. Registered in England and Wales, Registered No. 3701768, Cannon Place, 78 Cannon Street London EC4N6AG, United Kingdom. Authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority. Columbia Threadneedle Investments is the global brand name of the Columbia and Threadneedle group of companies. 08.16 | J25145]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[A 27 Global Multi Asset Income Fund Dynamic Real Return Fundcolumbiathreadneedle.co.uk/multiassetinvesting08.16 | J2514504/08/2016Important Information. For Professional and/or Qualified Investors only (not to be used with or passed on to retail clients). Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income is not guaranteed and can go down as well as up and may be affected by exchange rate fluctuations. This means that an investor may not get back the amount invested. *Source: Factset, gross of fees since launch 18.06.2013 to 30.06.2016. Volatility of equities measured as MSCI World Index (gross). **Source: Morningstar, net of fees since launch 31.07.2014 to 30.06.2016. Ranked within the IA Mixed Invest. 20-60% shares sector. Ratings as at July 2016. Threadneedle Opportunity Investment Funds (TOIF) is an open-ended investment company structured as an umbrella company, incorporated in England and Wales, authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) as a UCITS scheme. This material is for information only and does not constitute an offer or solicitation of an order to buy or sell any securities or other financial instruments, or to provide investment advice or services. Subscriptions to a Fund may only be made on the basis of the current Prospectus and the Key Investor Information Document, as well as the latest annual or interim reports and the applicable terms & conditions. Please refer to the ‘Risk Factors’ section of the Prospectus for all risks applicable to investing in any fund and specifically this Fund. Issued by Threadneedle Investment Services Limited. Registered in England and Wales, Registered No. 3701768, Cannon Place, 78 Cannon Street London EC4N6AG, United Kingdom. Authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority. Columbia Threadneedle Investments is the global brand name of theYour Clients’ SuccessColumbia and Threadneedle group of companies.Is Our Priority17:17J25145_FP_210x297_MAA UK_Aug16_Connection magazine.indd 1Columbia Threadneedle Investments is a leading global asset management group that provides a broad range of actively managed investment strategies and solutions for individual, institutional and corporateclients around the world.Our priority is the investment success of our clients. We aim to deliver the investment outcomes they expect through an investment approach that is team-based, performance- driven and risk-aware. By sharing our insights across asset classes and geographies we generate richer perspectives on global, regional and local investment landscapes. Importantly, we believe this will result in better informed investment decisions for our clients.Columbia Threadneedle Investments• AUM: £344 billion1• Over 2000 people globally includingmore than 450 investment professionals• Present in 19 countries across Europe,Middle East, Asia Pacific, North Americaand South America• 4th largest manager of retail funds inthe UK2• Named “Best performing fund groupover the last decade” in study by FE Trustnet3NotesPerspective AdvantageWe believe that we can deliver strong risk- adjusted returns for our clients through:• An active approach that takes advantage ofmarket inefficiencies• Our global perspective advantage - thecombination of macro and micro insights • The appropriate allocation of riskOur well-established investment approach provides a global perspective advantage that enables us to deliver the investment outcomes our clients want. This perspective advantageis gained by combining macro and micro insights with an active approach to portfolio construction. Independent thinking, rigorous debate and sharing of ideas balanced with a disciplined approach to risk ensures we can deliver better informed investment decisions for our clients.Building A Strong PartnershipAs part of our committment to helping advisers we have created our Adviser Centre, an onlineresource of materials to aid you with different aspects of your business, whether it be articles to help improve your technical knowledge, handy guides to use with your clients when discussing investments, or bite-sized educational videos with expert views and tips on a rangeof business topics. We also offer innovative thought leadership and market views from our investment experts.To find out more about our adviser and investor support, visit columbiathreadneedle.co.uk/ adviser-centre.By sharing our insights across asset classes and geographies we generate richer perspectives on global, regional and local investment landscapes.1Source: Ameriprise Financial at 30.06.2016. 2Total retail and institutional funds under management at 30.06.2016. 3Source: “The Investment Association’s best performing fund group over the last decade” - Alex Paget, FE Trustnet, 13 November 2015.For Professional Investors only. Past performance is not a guide to future performance. The value of investments and any income is not guaranteed and can go down as well as up and may be affected by exchange rate fluctuations. This article is for information only and does not constitute an offer or solicitation of an order to buy or sell any securities or other financial instruments, or to provide investment advice or services. Threadneedle Investment Services Limited. Registered in England and Wales, Registered No. 3701768, Cannon Place, 78 Cannon Street London EC4N 6AG, United Kingdom. Authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority. Columbia Threadneedle Investments is the global brand name of the Columbia and Threadneedle group of companies.]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[After 21 years we still hold the key to complianceSYNAPTIC PRODUCT & FUND SOFTWARE• Providing independent and objective whole of market research. • Helping advisers navigate the challenges of compliance.• The cornerstone of compliance advice in the UK.• Integrates fully with the entire Synaptic Research Suite.For more information call us on 0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[29Due diligence on Absolute Return FundsSynaptic and many other industry experts rely heavily on stochastic modelling, which is increasingly acknowledged as the pre-eminent methodology for risk assessment. In the analysis available to advisers, the stochastic model will only work where a conventional asset allocation exists.Most absolute return funds’ risk and return profiles conform to the Moody’s ‘Hedge’ category, of which they form a sub set. However, there is greater diversity within the sector than most, and this needs to be examined. Accuracy can also be lacking within the data feeds – some have no asset allocation data, some are registered as alternative and some attempt to represent asset allocations in a manner that is probably not reliable. Standard Life GARS for example is registered in the F.E. feed as mainly global bonds, but scrutiny of the underlining strategies shows this to be loose approximation at best.A lack of consistency may mean that some of these funds may not be recommendable by an adviser, unless a very high risk assessment is attributed. A good example of the unpredictable nature of one of these is the City Financial Absolute Equity Fund. It is the best performing fund in its sector over 3 to 5 years which is barnstorming. But for several months up to August it nosedived, dropping 25% in 6 months. That is a spectacular drawdown.However, to advise on such a fund, there is some analysis that can help, and that will form the basis of due diligence if required. We focus on the ‘distribution of returns’. This involves measuring the consistencyof the returns (long tail versus peak – see graph), equating this to the consistency of the performance of the fund. It is the same as looking at the ‘Kurtosis’ value, which you can look up in Synaptic Fund Research. For example, if you wish to take risk out of your UK asset allocation, you could legitimately use Henderson UK Absolute Return, as the shape of returns mirror the UK sector, but the distribution of returns (and returns themselves) are muted as a result of the (hedging) strategies employed.The above is an example of a grid that you can create within the Synaptic Fund Research tool, which allows you to examine some of the attributes of absolute return funds:Our first graph confirms the success that some absolute return funds have had in managing risk and return historically.The second graph maps the distribution of returns – and evidences consistency in management styles.Synaptic Product and Fund Research is part of the Synaptic Research suite – call 0800 783 4477 for more information including our ‘Suitability’ promotional deal.]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[30What does the recent Thematic Review Paper on suitability tell us about platform due diligence?Although it doesn’t grab the headlines to the extent it used to, the subject of platforms within the context of compliance is still very much alive.The adoption of investment platforms has influenced the evolution of financial advice more than anything else, and continues to do so. Online access to platforms heralded the wrap revolution, where full control of clients’ assets could be assumed by advisers.The long anticipated ban on commissions was no big deal as ‘adviser charging’ was facilitated by the platforms. In fact Synaptic and other published data suggest that in some cases, advisers are charging more ‘ad valorem’ inthe current AUM gathering culture than they did through the old provider products.The full wrap functionality that many take for granted today is just another stop on this frenetic technological journey. Further down the line, advisers who are not clear about the value that they represent to their clients and how they evolve their business models will suffer. The ability to provide custodyto investments, to offer proven bargain basement price asset allocation strategies and managed solutions will be ubiquitous, forcing even the fittest to adapt to survive. The advisers who see themselves as ‘wealth managers’ may go the way of dinosaurs if they are only focussed on the accumulation of assets. They need to be monetising the aspects of their expertise that are valued by clients, the financial coaching, the planning and the problem solving.But where we are today with platforms does present a potential conflict of interest; one that has been specifically highlighted inthe recent Thematic Review Paper TR16/1, and one that rounds up concerns identified by the regulator over some years. Taking advantage of the full wrap functionality offered by the best platform solutions brings its own risks, and though the regulator may be ‘extremely concerned’, there is nothing a bit of sensible due diligence using Synaptic tools cannot put right.TR16/1 is succinct. It states:‘the poor quality of an advisory firm’s research and due diligence is one of the three root causes for poor consumer outcomes. The other two are incorrect risk profiling and costs.’We deal with risk profiling elsewhere in this edition, but we would offer another perspective from the paper which is theregulator’s concern with the use of platforms – where the ‘service’ element that benefits advisers and the way they manage their businesses can appear to override the best interests of customers:‘Many firms demonstrated inconsistent and insufficient research and due diligence in the selection of platforms’.The way to bat away this concern is to provide sufficient research to evidence suitability at the client level – which means ideally performing client specific research, and crucially not over relying on a platform’s own tools, where a wider market perspective cannot be achieved. A wrap creates its own financial ecosystem, and without care, may appear to constrain an independent adviser.The full wrap functionality that many take for granted today is just another stop on this frenetic technological journey. Further down the line, advisers who are not clear about the value that they represent to their clients and how they evolve their business models will suffer.]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[31Illustration results (source Synaptic Comparator). ISA 10 year term / £50kPlatformProductR.I.Y.Finalfund valueTotal chargesAdviser chargesOption 1.CofundsPension Account1.50%£68,100£10,600£2,926Option 2.--2.06%£64,500£14,200£2,840Our experience echoes the regulators. We meet some firms who resist due diligence. They assess platforms according to the usual criteria (stuff that you can tick off on a list) – financial strength of parent, terms and conditions, range of funds and tax wrappers, functionality, accessibility – and when it comes to cost, they look at the headline costs, such as the generic charge of the platform and fund TERs, failing to capture the nuances of charges that exist. The first element is the relatively easy part of the due diligence which can be summarised on a single Synaptic Research grid along the lines of:What advisers don’t always do is look at cost at an individual case level, taking into account the specific fund or portfolio selection theyare recommending, or look to understand how the myriad of different combinations involving platform, wrapper and fund work. Those who haven’t performed this research may be surprised to know the extent of these variations in cost.Of course advisers shouldn’t be chasing minute increments of savings, but they should be able to perform Reduction in Yield calculations that can confirm the value that they are delivering. Working to keep the costs down for the client puts additional income in the adviser’s pocket. Our illustration is based on a £50k ISA transfer.Our illustration shows that on any case,the difference between two premier league platforms can be significant - in this case several thousand pounds of avoidable charges. The point is to understand these variations as they are unpredictable and varied.If your platform due diligence is generic and stops at platform level, you cannot accurately evidence the quality of the advice you impart to clients.For more information about the Synaptic Research Suite, please visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call us on 0800 783 4477.]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[32Investment risk – the challenge for advisersEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedThe principles-based regulatory system that we have in the UK means that there is no prescription or right or wrong in how to operate at a risk level, only guidance and descriptions of good and poor practice. What IS obligatory is that the adviser can demonstrate that he or she knows their client and understands their objectives, as well as their tolerance and capacity for loss. This is set out in the 2011 paper ‘Assessing suitability’. Operating effectively around risk can be phenomenally complex, especially when you are trying to design an advice process that can be replicated across a group of advisers.The central problem is that risk is subjective, allied with the fact that the markets and therefore investment returns are unpredictable. Advisers must evidence suitability none-the- less - something that many firms are falling short of today. The recent follow-up paper,the Thematic Review TR16/1, spells this out in respect of risk profiling:‘the poor quality of an advisory firm’s research and due diligence is one of the three root causes for poor consumer outcomes. The other two are incorrect risk profiling and costs.’The importance of an effective risk framework underpinning your investment strategyWe believe the best approach is to take the (Moody’s) stochastic route. This takes amodel based on assumptions (about markets, interest rates, inflation and so on) and then runs mathematical simulations – which provide a probability based model for the full range of outcomes. Working back, you can then plan for worst and best case scenarios, as well as ‘the most likely’. The key advantage of this approach is that the view of the future is something you can present to clients – offering a ‘framework’ for decisions based on quantified possible outcomes.There is a lot of negativity about (ATR) questionnaires – but they perform the invaluable function of anchoring your client into a relative framework, meaning that your perspective on your clients’ attitudeto risk can be benchmarked against a wider population. The questions also mean that you as an adviser can efficiently cover off an in depth discussion around risk, especiallythe dynamics of risk and return, as you are required to by the regulator. It provides a context for the ‘conversation’ as people often refer to it as, and in no way constrains the adviser. It is hard to imagine a more effective alternative.In the Synaptic approach, the ATRQ aligns with 5 different Risk Categories, and because it is a probability based model, a mathematically derived value known as the ‘Minimum gain’* is produced – a bit like drawdown. The ‘Minimum gain’ is expressed as a percentage probability, of the extent of loss ascribed to the worst year in 20 years of expected returns. Equipped with this value, you are able to frame the all-important ‘Capacity for Loss’ discussion, on which the regulatory approach is built. This is how to turn risk into an objective discussion.]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[33The central problem is that risk is subjective, allied with the fact that the markets and therefore investment returns are unpredictable.A snapshot of the Moody’s Risk Framework:Strategic Asset AllocationClassesMin Gain*Average GainMax GainCautiousCash 50.00%UK Corporate Bonds 29.00% UK Equities 8.00%Global Equities (ex UK) 7.00% Global Property 6.00%-5.26%4.99%15.27%Moderately CautiousUK Corporate Bonds 55.00% UK Equities 15.00%Global Equities (ex UK) 14.00% Global Property 12.00%Cash 4.00%-10.73%6.14%22.70%BalancedUK Corporate Bonds 36.00% Global Equities (ex UK) 30.00% UK Equities 20.00%Global Property 9.00%Emerging Markets Equities 5.00%-15.28%7.08%28.27%Moderately AdventurousGlobal Equities (ex UK) 43.00%UK Equities 24.00%UK Corporate Bonds 20.00%Emerging Markets Equities 7.00%Global Property 6.00%-18.50%7.71%33.01%AdventurousGlobal Equities (ex UK) 61.00% UK Equities 29.00%Emerging Markets Equities 10.00%-24.21%8.56%40.85%Review of the historical accuracy of a model such as Moody’s is something that can be done in retrospect. Moody’s have proventheir expertise by accurately capturing the probability of investment outcomes overthe years. There is also comfort in knowing that they have invested heavily over a long time, and teams of actuaries have accepted their assumptions and methodology in the due diligence that has been performed by institutions including Royal London, Prudential and many Fund Managers who rely on their risk model for their own operations.The Moody’s framework gives you an Attitude to Risk Questionnaire, that is aligned to different risk categories, onto which canbe mapped your existing holdings and recommendations. All of this is availablewith the Synaptic Research Suite’. Moody’sare constantly refining the model, updatingon a quarterly basis. The many ‘movingparts’ and academic angles are attended toby the experts, so you don’t have to. Using Synaptic also means that you do not haveto pretend that risk is static. It’s not. It’s fluid, and this is reflected in the model which perfectly illustrates the two pillars of effective investment – the benefits of diversification and time in the market.]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[34Review of the historical accuracy of a model such as Moody’s is something that can be done in retrospect. Moody’s have proven their expertise by accurately capturing the probability of investment outcomes over the years.As a sales support for our adviser customers, we have run a wide range of frequently recommended solutions through the Moody’s engine, and ‘risk rated’ them based on the metrics returned. This helps fulfil the compliance requirements pf any firm aligned to the Moody’s model, including of course Synaptic users.In addition to publishing ratings in this magazine we have created a new online arena:1. The Risk Rating Service TabClick here for access to the table and downloads.2. Synaptic Risk Categoriesa. Cautious through to Adventurous b. These are interactive buttons thatcan be used to filter the rated investments according to risk category.3. Risk Service Downloadsa. The Synaptic Risk Rating Table – in an easy to download pdf formatb. The Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnairec. Attitude to Risk Scoring Method – this must be used with the Attitude to Risk Questionnaire –it provides the scoring which identifies the risk category appropriate for the client.Any Synaptic subscriber can now access these Ratings via the single log on to the Synaptic Suite. Call us now for a free user name and password on 0800 028 0033.What stochastics can do for you: the graph opposite shows how Synaptic can create a risk and return profile for an investment strategy (green line), a portfolio recommendation including charges (blue line), and model impact of inflation (red line).]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[The Suitability SuiteRisk . Costs . Due diligence . Best adviceProof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research• The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costsSynaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reportingSynaptic ComparatorDetailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculationsSynaptic RiskA.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfoliosSynaptic ModellerModels investment outcomes for new existing holdings. Manage and assess investment riskProtection and Annuity quotes and on-line applications Synaptic Webline (including enhanced annuities)Synaptic Suitability offer £140 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp is £226Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.SAVE OVER£125 PER LICENCE]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund 1 F&C MM Navigator Distribution 1 F&C MM Navigator Moderate 1 F&C MM Navigator Progressive 1 F&C MM Navigator Select 1 F&C MM Navigator Boutiques 1 Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) 1CF Canlife Portfolio III 1 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 1 CF Canlife Portfolio V 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VII 1 Canlife Portfolio 3 1 Canlife Portfolio 4 1 Canlife Portfolio 5 1 Canlife Portfolio 6 1 Canlife Portfolio 7 12 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Cautious MPS 1 Income MPS 1 Balanced MPS 1 Growth MPS 1 Global Equity MPS 1Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund 1 Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund 1 Close Conservative Portfolio Fund 1 Close Balanced Portfolio Fund 1 Close Growth Portfolio Fund 1 Close Managed Income Fund 1 Close Managed Conservative Fund 1 Close Managed Balanced Fund 1 Close Managed Growth Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund 1 Close DMS Income Plus 1 Close DMS Conservative 1 Close DMS Balanced 1 Close DMS Growth 12 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Risk Level 1 Short Risk Level 2 Short Risk Level 3 Short Risk Level 4 Short Risk Level 5 Short Risk Level 1 Medium Risk Level 2 Medium Risk Level 3 Medium Risk Level 4 Medium Risk Level 5 Medium Risk Level 1 Long Risk Level 2 Long Risk Level 3 Long Risk Level 4 Long Risk Level 5 Long Income1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Multi Asset AdventurousMulti Asset Allocator Adventurous Multi Asset Allocator Defensive Multi Asset Allocator Growth Multi Asset Allocator Strategic Multi Asset Allocator WorldMulti Asset Balanced Income Multi Asset DefensiveMulti Asset GrowthMulti Asset IncomeMulti Asset Income & Growth Multi Asset Open Adventurous Multi Asset Open DefensiveMulti Asset Open GrowthMulti Asset Open StrategicMulti Asset StrategicOpen WorldWealth Builder1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Diversified Income FundDiversified Growth FundMAP 12345 Managed Growth FundInvestec Cautious Managed Fund1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 5Multi-Index3 12345Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-riskMulti-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7Multi -Index Income 4 Multi -Index Income 5 Mulit-index Income 61 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 5]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[M&G Episode Allocation Fund M&G Episode Income Fund M&G Episode Growth Fund M&G Global Dividend Fund M&G Property PortfolioAdventurous Portfolio Income Seeker Portfolio Growth Seeker Portfolio Income Focus Portfolio Temperate Portfolio Growth Focus Portfolio Lower Risk Income Portfolio Lower Risk Growth Portfolio Protective Portfolio1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5MP3 12345 MP50 12345 MP4 12345 MP5 12345 MP6 12345 MP7 12345CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset AllocationPremier Liberation IV Fund 1 Premier Liberation V Fund 1 Premier Liberation VI Fund 1 Premier Liberation VII Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth 1 Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund 1 Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund 1 Premier UK Money Market Fund 1 Premier Defensive Growth Fund 1 Premier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund 1 Premier Diversified Fund 12 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 3Funds4 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Premier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income PortfolioPremier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced PortfolioPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth PortfolioPremier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth PortfolioRMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income Strategy 1Strategy 2Strategy 3Strategy 4Strategy 5Strategy 61 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 21 2Portfolios3 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 53 4 5MPS Global Growth MPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global Income MPS IncomeMPS ConservativeMPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive PortfolioPositive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus Portfolio1 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 5Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[RL Governed Portfolio 1 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 (s) RL Governed Portfolio 4 (l) RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 (s)1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Schroder MM DiversitySchroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK GrowthSchroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed Balanced1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5RL Governed Portfolio 7 RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 RL GRIP 1RLGRIP2 RLGRIP3 RLGRIP4 RLGRIP5Vanguard Vanguard Vanguard Vanguard Vanguard(l)(s)LifeStrategy 20% LifeStrategy 40% LifeStrategy 60% LifeStrategy 80% LifeStrategy 100%1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 512 32 3CautiousModerately CautiousBalancedModerately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation12345123451234512345Cautious / Personal InjuryModerately CautiousIncome 12345 Balanced 12345 Moderately Adventurous 1Adventurous1 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 5]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Verbatim PortfoliosFP Verbatim Portfolio 3FP Verbatim Portfolio 4FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Income FP Verbatim Portfolio 6FP Verbatim Portfolio 71 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 5Verbatim VDSVDSJH3 12345 VDSJH4 12345 VDSJH5 12345 VDSJH6 12345 VDSJH7 12345 VDSJH8 12345 VDSRSM2 12345 VDSRSM3 12345 VDSRSM4 12345 VDSRSM5 12345 VDSRSM6 12345 VDSRSM7 12345 VDSRSM8 12345 VDSRSM9 12345 VDSRSM10 12345 VDSTCF3 12345 VDSTCF4 12345 VDSTCF5 12345 VDSTCF6 12345 VDSTCF7 12345 VDSTCF8 12345 VDSS&W3 12345 VDSS&W4 12345 VDSS&W5 12345 VDSS&W6 12345 VDSS&W7 12345 VDSS&W8 12345 VSDHR3 12345 VSDHR4 12345 VSDHR5 12345 VSDHR6 12345 VSDHR7 12345 VSDHR8 12345Verbatim RSMRRSM Model Portfolio 2 RSM Model Portfolio 3 RSM Model Portfolio 4 RSM Model Portfolio 5 RSM Model Portfolio 6 RSM Model Portfolio 7 RSM Model Portfolio 8 RSM Model Portfolio 9 RSM Model Portfolio 101 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Verbatim Total ClarityTotal Clarity Portfolio 3 Total Clarity Portfolio 4 Total Clarity Portfolio 5 Total Clarity Portfolio 61 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 512345(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further informationbefore recommending.About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[42Drawdown governance – how much income are people taking?Fiona Tait | Pension Specialist | Royal LondonRoyal London’s Drawdown Governance Service (DGS) is now live, allowing advisers to monitor the level of income withdrawals their RL clients are taking and manage sustainability. It also gives usa snapshot of what clients are currently doing and the chance to monitor trends over time.General informationThe average fund size among Royal London drawdown plans is £75,000. A third of plans are currently paying out regular income,of which the majority (72%) are in capped drawdown and the remainder in Flexi-Access Drawdown (FAD).Income levelsAverage withdrawalsThe average level of income being withdrawn is 11%, however the median is 7% indicating a greater variation amongst those who are taking higher levels of withdrawal, as might be expected in an environment where there are no income limits.This is borne out by a comparison between FAD plans, where the difference between average and median is 12% (21% and 9% respectively), and capped drawdown where the trend is actually the other way but much less significant (6% and 7%).The fact that there are more people taking lower levels of withdrawal is positive, however the median of 7% is probably too high to be sustainable for life unless other sources of income are forthcoming at a later date.SustainabilityAccording to our stochastic modelling the majority (54%) of RL drawdown plans where regular income is being taken have lessthan a 1 in 5 chance of sustaining current income levels for life. Taken in isolation this is extremely concerning, and may suggest that our customers are either underestimating how long they will need income for, or have no way of translating this into a sustainable figure.It must be emphasized however that these figures do not take into account the client’s actual objectives. Now that the DGS is live, advisers will have a chance to make changes to the parameters used for assessment.Some clients may be deliberately running down the value of one pension in the knowledge that others exist, others may have started out taking a higher level of income which they already intend to reduce. Results over the next few quarters will therefore be interesting.Happily, the next most popular group contains those who have the greatest chance of sustainable lifetime income, which is a definite indication that the issue of sustainability is being discussed and acted upon.ContributionsOf course sustainability is not just about what’s being taken out, but also what is being put in. Unfortunately very few plans – only 11% - are still being topped up, although of course under the freedom rules they could be, regardless of age or earnings.InvestmentsOf specific interest to Royal London is the increasing use of our Governed Retirement Income Portfolios (GRIPs) with regular withdrawal plans. Overall the 20% of income policies are invested in GRIPs, however this has increased to 48% among new plans set up since the freedoms were introduced in April 2015.In September we will revisit these figures to see what has changed and how plans are performing against their individual income targets.Further informationVisit adviser.royallondon.com/pensions.]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[43Life begins at...Fiona Holmes | Proposition Communications Manager | Royal LondonHaving reached a certain age (it’s the new 40 by the way), I’m having to come to terms with the fact that my peers and I aren’t as immune from illness or death as we’d like to think.That’s the problem with 30 being the new20 and 40 the new 30, when you reach your 50’s and you’ve gone through life relatively unscathed, you really start to think you’re invincible. But then things happen around you and you realise that’s not quite the case.At the risk of sounding like my mother-in-law whose main topic of conversation is illness, death and funerals, in the space of six months an old University friend died from cancer, another friend was diagnosed with terminal cancer and a good friend has just been diagnosed with breast cancer.While my immediate thoughts are with those friends and their families, I can’t help but think I’m glad I held onto my critical illness policy.Working in the protection industry I’m only too aware of the need for cover should the worst happen but there have been times over the years when I’ve toyed with the idea of cancelling it. It’s the usual ‘it won’t happento me’ scenario. But I never thought it would happen to those friends and it has.A few weeks ago my friend with breast cancer was lying on a beach in Thailand without a care in the world. Next week she’ll undergo a mastectomy and breast reconstruction and will endure at least four months of treatment. This is life changing stuff and something neither she nor her family were prepared for.I hope she’ll be fine financially, but emotionally it’s hard to say how she will cope. According to Macmillan Cancer Support, 45% of people with cancer say the emotional effects of the illness are the most difficultto cope with, compared to the physical and practical aspects.1It’s statistics like those that make you realise just how important added value serviceslike Royal London’s Helping Hand are. Inour experience the emotional and practical support a customer received through Helping Hand has often been more of a lifeline than their actual pay out.While improvements in cancer treatment mean more people are surviving or living longer following their illness, all too often, the stress of managing everyday life following diagnosis and treatment is huge with the psychological and emotional impact continuing long after the cancer itself is treated.The number of people living with cancer inthe UK is increasing by 3.2% every year. Ifthis rate continues this could see four million people living with cancer by 2030.2 Cuts in NHS spending, lack of aftercare service and the psychological impact of being diagnosed with a critical illness all bring with them a need for added value services like Helping Hand.So as I embrace my half century – and no, it isn’t all about varifocals and cruise ships – I hope I’ll never have to make a claim on my critical illness cover. But knowing it’s there with additional support services that I could call on if needed, gives me peace of mind. After all, we never know what life’s going to throw at us.1 Worried Sick: The Emotional Impact of Cancer. Research for Macmillan Cancer Support conducted by Opinion Leader Research. 2006.2 Internal analysis by Macmillan Cancer Support. Taken from and based on Maddams J, et al. Cancer prevalence in the UK: estimates 2008. British Journal of Cancer. 2009. 101: 541-547.This is a Royal London promotion.]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[44Expanding the Reach of Protection*HannahCook| MarketingActuary|SCORInnovations – the current state of playIt would be fair to say that the Protection industry is not the most dynamic. Things happen slowly and there has been littletrue innovation in the market with many providers and distributors offering similar customer journeys and products with littleto differentiate them.Whilst there is some innovation on the front line where distributors are facing off to customers, providers (and reinsurers) are slow to innovate.It’s a comfortable, stable industry with many of us in very comfortable, stable jobs. The industry is filled with barriers to innovation such as systems legacy issues and large inforce portfolios that can constrain genuine creative innovation for new business. The market remains flat and yet we keep hoping for it to grow. As Einstein was quoted, the definition of insanity is ‘doing the same thing over and over again and expecting different results’.Our ‘Expanding the Reach of ProtectionSeminar’ set out to challenge the status quo and look for ways to grow the market for the benefit of everyone.Where is the innovation going to come from? During the seminar we surveyed the delegates and asked them who they thought had the greatest responsibility to lead innovation in the market. The overwhelming response was providers.We then asked the delegates who they thought in reality was most likely to lead innovation in the future. The responses were very different, with the two groups felt mostlikely to lead innovation being the Distributors and FinTech companies. There is a danger that we’re all sitting here waiting for somebody else to act and we’ll end up being in exactly the same position 10 years from now.Behavioural Economics shows us that we have a natural tendency to have a herd like mentality. It takes a brave soul to distance themselves from the crowd.We keep talking about change and expecting the rise in directto consumer and more digital innovation, but it doesn’t really happen. This is all in a backdrop of fairly poor financial capability amongst consumers. A survey conducted by The Money Advice Service found that 4 in 10 people wouldn’t have the means to cope with an unexpected bill of £300 and only 5 in 10 have financial goals.What works well in current distribution models?We often talk in the industry about the need to stimulate demand but how true is this? Our distribution session heard the thoughts of experts from companies with three very different distribution models: Andy Walton (Intrinsic), John Nelmes (Cavendish) and Mark Jones (Sunlife). Whilst our three wise men might disagree with how best to engage with customers, all three painted a positive picture for demand in the UK and all feltthat there are opportunities to grow their respective models. Between 2012 and 2014, the number of people searching for the words ‘Life Insurance’ on Google doubled, but yet we certainly haven’t seen an uptick in sales of that magnitude. Why is this and what can we do about it?As an industry we can be pretty poor at engaging customers and using a language that makes our products accessible to them.We talk about the Protection industry andBehavioural Economics shows us that we have a natural tendency to have a herd like mentality. It takes a brave soul to distance themselves from the crowd.]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[45The industry is filled with barriers to innovation such as systems legacy issues and large inforce portfolios that can constrain genuine creative innovation for new business.the Protection gap – ask most customerswhat they think Protection means and they’ll probably suggest sunscreen, bodyguards or contraceptives. We need to shift the language we use – stop talking about products andstart talking about outcomes. What is it that customers actually want? They want to know that should they die, that their loved oneswill have enough money to live on after their death. They want to know that should they get ill, that they will be able to stay in their homes. We should take a huge pride in our industry that we can do this for people and make sure that we don’t confuse them in a fog of jargon.The future - a call for actionSo what does the future hold? Our safe, comfortable industry could start to be invaded from the outside. Given the lack of innovation from within the industry, who is to stop the likes of a Google coming in and shaking things up? With the rise of Wearables and the gizmos and gadgets that can be attached to our smartphones to monitor blood glucose levels, blood pressure, heart rate as well as others, there is plenty of opportunity to use all this data to offer the young and healthy, cheap, easy, affordable life insurance that really meets customer needs and adapts and grows with them.Most efforts to digitalise our industry to date have been to start to collect email addresses from customers so that we can save the cost of a stamp when trying to communicate with them. Whilst this is not a bad aim, actually many of us simply ignore our emails as easily as we do a piece of marketing material that comes through the front door. The next generation who are coming through are more likely to be found reading their Instagram or Twitter feed than their emails so we needto find better and more diverse ways of communicating with the next generationWe also risk our industry imploding from the inside. The relentless pursuit of pricing for the healthiest individuals naturally leads to increases in price for others.Making cover more expensive for those who can arguably least afford it can only haveone impact – to shrink the market. This was precisely the experience in the US when it moved to preferred pricing and we risk it happening here too, with ever more rating factors being applied to the cover that we provide. It’s an often held view that insurers only offer cover to those who don’t really need it. Whilst of course we need to protect ourselves against fraudulent or ‘certain’ claims, we do need to remember that insurance is supposed to be about a ‘pooling’ of risk and the more we sub-divide those pools, the more we reinforce this view.So what were the key takeaways from the seminar? To me, they were:1. Demand is out there.2. Recognise the need to test and learn.3. Keeppacewiththewaytheworld communicates.Over 90% of the delegates who responded to our survey after the seminar said that they would do something differently as a result which feels like precisely what our industry needs.The relentless pursuit of pricing for the healthiest individuals naturally leads to increases in price for others.*Reflections from the SCOR Seminar, Wednesday 10th February 2016]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Looking for an expert in business protection? Speak to AegonOur experience and expertise with business protection means that support is something you’ll never be short of. We’ll make sure you’re heading in the right direction to develop professional connections, identify opportunities and find suitable clients. And we have the tools and solutions to help you meet all your clients’ needs.So, let the experts in the field guide you through the business protection market.Visit aegon.co.uk/businessprotectionFor financial advisers only. Aegon is a brand name of Scottish Equitable plc. Scottish Equitable plc, registered office: Edinburgh Park, Edinburgh EH12 9SE. Registered in Scotland (No. 144517). Authorised and regulated by the Financial Services Authority (FSA register number 165548). An Aegon company. www.aegon.co.uk © 2016 Aegon UK plc*Source: Aegon/So Here’s the Plan - High net worth & business protection adviser research, October 2015]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50 11% 25% 44%For financial advisers only. Aegon is a brand Registered in Scotland (No. 144517). Authorise Regulation Authority. Financial Services Register47452297_SD_274070_07_16_p3.indd 1Business continuity and succession planning – why it shouldn’t be ignoredBusiness continuity and succession plannBusiness continuity andTowonemrsadkieed?sure your client’s business can• who they’d want to get control of their the ownership and control of a business – most likely throughresuccession planning may notBusiness protection makes sure businesses can continue to trade, and– why it shouldn’t be ignoredpriority list. But how would a business cope financially if it lost a keyThe need to have business succession plans incope financially if it lost a keymfiatneraianlsB,cvuieashilinclylesifasnisdtuslcocosents. sHaiokwnevpyelr,aetnhmenipvnalgsot myiseajaeor;kitaey nydodpn’at rlotoikn protecting theemployee? What might the implications be if one of the businessto insure their biggest asset – their key employees. The need to have business succession plans in place isowners died?impmleadciaete iasndimcoumldebde diaevtaestatningdfocroyouulrdclibenet’sdbeusvinaesstatingemployee? What might theTo make sure your client’s business can continue, your client –• woultdhehaovwenethrsehinpeacnedsscaornytrocal oshf aflbouwsinteoss – most likifetlhyeyt’hreronoutgthought through properly. who may be key to the business – needs to consider whether it:97% claims paid in 2015Business succession – why does it matter?Business succession planning is a key part in protecting the stability and continuity of the business. It involves transferring the ownership and control of a business – most likely through retirement – to new management.Business owners need to think about what they’d want to happen if they suddenly died orBusiness continuity and succession planning97% claims paid in 2015Business owners need to think about what they’d wantto •hahpopewn ifathnedy swudhdenrlyedtiehdeormbeocanmeycrwiticoalluy lildl. come from You should speak to your clients about:• whtoothmey’dakweantstuorgettchoinstrohl aofpthpeeirnbeusdin.ess; and– why it shouldn’t be ignoredtowyhoyudroceliseinttms atbtoeur?t: –Business continuity and succession planning may not be high on the Bu skpriority list. But how would a business cope financially if it lost a key Buisinessgsuccession planning is a key part in protecting theemployee? What might the implications be if one of the business stability and continuity of the business. It involves transferringcontinue, your client – who may be key to thebusiness; andallows the owners to maintain control of their business while making sure their dependants receive a fair value for their share of it.business – needs to consider whether it:be high on the priority list.Business cBonutintuhityoawnd swucoceussliodn aplabnnuinsginmeaysnsot be high on the Business succession – why does it m• hoawtatnedrw?here the money would come from to makestability and continuity of the business. It involves transferringBusiness protection makes sure businesses can continue to trade, and retirement – to new management. for your client’s business if they’re not thought • croeupldlacocnetinaune yto ltorasdse or fwopurlod fisutffeor rfinraencpially ifaitnloyst Tools to help youallows theiomwnperlsictoamtaiiontnaisn cbonetroifl oof tnheir obufsintehssewhile making a key eBmuplsoiynee;sasnodwners need to think about what they’d wtahnrtough properly.sure their dependants receive a fair value for their share of it.outstanding loans, including directors’ loans.business owners died?of not could destroy their business.It’s vital business owners consider their business continuity • would htoavehtahpepnecnesisfartyhceayshsfluodwdtoernelpyladceieadnyolorssboefcparomfite criticalnlyd silulc.cession plans sooner rather than later as the impactbecame critically ill.Ytirousinemeneshssouuldsccepst – to new management.seaionBusiness continuity – is there a need?• could continue to trade or would sufferYes, definitely. It’s well known that businesses look to protectthemselves against many things, protecting their buildings, contents,sure this happened.Business continuity – is there a need?Business protection makes sure businessesor repay any outstanding loans, including directors’ loans.Yes, definitely. It’s well known that businesses look to protect themselves against many things, protecting their buildings, contents,can continue to trade, and allows the owners Probability of at least one Probability of at least one dying besfuorreethaigseh6ap5p*ened. having a critical illnessbusiness continuity and succession plansYou should speak to your clients about:Tools to help youAs the tables below highlight the probability of a partner Aegon has recently launched a new business protection• who they’d want to get control of their business; andPorodibreactborildityiyngoofr ahatvilnegaasctritical illnPerssobeafobreiltihteyaogef at least video to help you discuss the importance of putting businessprotection plans in place with your clients. You can find theone pa•rthnoewr/adnirdewcthoerre the monoenepyawrtonuelrd/dcoirmecetofrrom to mIta’ksevital business owners consider theirof 65 exists.video at aegon.co.uk/supportmaterials, vehicles and so on. However, the vast majority don’t look partner/director dying partner/director having a For more information contact yourto maintain control of their business whilebefore age 65**to insure their biggest asset – their key employees.before aTgehe65n*eed to have buscirniteicsasl isllnuecscsebsesfoiorenagpela6n5s**in place isusual Aegon sales representative,making sure their dependants receive a fairor visit aegon.co.uk/protection could destroy their business.To make sure your client’s business can continue, your client – who may bvealkueeyftorththeebirusihneasres –onfeite.ds to consider whether it:ught throup yoowneSource: www.actuaries.org.uk/learn-and-develop/continuous-mortality-investigation/cmi-mortality-and-morbidity-tablesAs the tabloesobketlowprhoigtehclitghtht tehme sperolvbeasbailgityaionfsat pmaartnyer or director dying or having a critical illness before the ageAegon has recently launched a new business protection video to help you discuss the importance of putting businessof 65 exists.nkraRegulation Authority. Financial Services Register number 165548. An Aegon company. www.aegon.co.uk © 2016 Aegon UK plcthings, protecting their buildings, contents,As the tables above highlight the probability ofProbability of at least one Probability of at least onererusualvast majority don’t look to insure their biggestFor more information contact your usual Aegon sales representative,ialpartner/director dying partner/director having a beforeagaes6se5t*–theirkeyemployecersit.icalillnessbeforeage65**Aegon sales representative, or visitimmediate and could be devastating for your client’s businessNumber ofif they’re not thodirectors/partnersAgeToo2ls5tosucceshel1040It’s vi13%andtal bu29%siness49%sion pr ongh oairoy timportance of putting business protectionuAge40sooneNumber ofgh properly.directors/partners2nsider49%r rathngacsh E5their81%er thaquitablepl10rs cobusine97%later5011%of no25%t coul44%d dest50heir b44%usiness.76%94%c.Fsooner rather than later as the impact of not• could continue to trade or would suffer financially if it losta key emBpulosyeine;easnsd continuity – is there a need?• would have the necessary cash flow to replace any loss of profit or repayYaensy, oduetfistnaintedliyn.gItlo’sawnse, lilnkclnuodwinng dthiraetctbourss’ilnoeasnse. sAegon has recently launched a new businesslans          n    as the impact*Based on mortality data from TMN00 (temporary assured lives,male non-smokers, 1999-2002) at five or more years’ duration.ss continuityprotection video to help you discuss the**CIBT02. Based on 1971-2003 population data and experience,published in SIAS paper Exploring The Critical Path, 2006. Males,stand-alone extended cover, including own occupation and totalplans in place with your clients. You can findthe video at aegon.co.uk/businessprotection protection plans in place with your clients. You can find theand permanent disability.materials, vehicles and so on. However, thedoisRegistered in Scotland (No. 144517). Authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority andtoe aForpfianrantcnviaiedl aredovisraerdts iaornelygc. Ay.auig/ndsounaprf rv Stclmpe illness before the age of 65 exists.o.cnboScottish Equitable plc, registered office: Edinburgh Park, Edinburgh EH12 9SE.ttiriticaogurmlated boytreinhe Finafonaegon.co.uk/protectionciralComandtuioctAncuthooritnyatnadthctyePruodeuntNumber of directors/partnersAge 2 5 10Number of452297_SD_274070_07_16_p3.indd 14050 11% 25% 44% 50 44% 76% 94%or visit aegon.co.uk/protection directors/partners Source: www.actuaries.org.uk/learn-and-develop/continuous-mortality-investigation/cmi-mortality-and-morbidity-tables18/07/2016 12:22and permanent disability.Age 2 5 10 *Based on mortality data from TMN00 (temporary assured lives, male non-smokers, 1999-2002) at five or more years’ duration.13% 29% 49% 40 49% 81% 97% **CIBT02. Based on 1971-2003 population data and experience, *Based on mortality data from TMN00 (temporary assured lives, male non-smokers, 1999-2002) at five or more years’ duration.Source: www.actuaries.org.uk/learn-and-develop/continuous-mortalityinvestigation/cmi-mortality-and-morbidity-tablespublished in SIAS paper Exploring The Critical Path, 2006. Males,**CIBT02. Based on 1971-2003 population data and experience, published in SIAS papsetraEnxdpl-oarliongneThexCtreitnicdael Pdatcho, v2e0r0,6i.nMclauledsi,nsgtanodw-anloonceceuxpteantdioedncaonvedr,tionctlaulding own occupation and total and permanent disability.d97%97%]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[48Page needs logo and brand colProtection Insurance – a 6 out of 10 industryAndrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskIn an industry full of data sometimes the most interesting numbers can be the most subjective ones. Numbers that pass you by because you’re absorbed in the detail of something else.The details that people like me obsess over are nuances like:• straight through processing rates – trying to get 80% of people insured immediately rather than 75%• underwriting quality – trying to reduce errors made from 2% to 1.5%• claims payout rates – trying to increase claims paid from 97% to 98%By getting details like this right the hope is that the ongoing decline in protection sales can be reversed. If we build a slightly better process to go with a slightly better product things should get slightly better – or so we delude ourselves.By the last talk of a conference my mind drifts to those details – particularly when a speaker straight bats back an answer to a question “what mark would you give the protection industry out of 10 at the moment” with a middle of the road “I’d give it a 6 out of 10”. Never mind that the opinion was that of MailOn Sunday’s Financial Editor Jeff Prestridge – I confess to breathing a sigh of relief and getting back to thinking of other things.Because 6 out of 10 is OK, right? 60% is a good pass in most exams. In Jeff’s newspaper terms it’s an OK performance by a footballer or a decent album by a band. Not many people lose their jobs for delivering a 6 out of 10 performance every day of the week.And there’s the rub. The challenge – how do we motivate ourselves to do better than OK? How can we motivate ourselves to be worried and angry when we hear all of our hard work given a 6 out of 10 rather than being slightly relieved?6 out of 10 doesn’t keep the leaders of our industry awake at night. It doesn’t cause multinationals to invest heavily to change performance. It doesn’t cause the regulator to get their magnifying glass on what we’re up to. It is hard to force yourself to move from being OK to risking being great.Many of the things that enable you to be OK stop you being great. The safety-first culture, the risk-averse decisions, the committee group- think, all limit our likely range of outcomes to a 5-7 out of 10.Compare this with start ups, where a more individualistic streak is at play. Companies and micro industries may rate as 9 out of 10 or 2 out of 10, many will fail but some will succeed.Stories not statistics – emotion not education need to be at the forefront of our work.o]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours49Working in a 9 out of 10 industry sounds something to work together to aim for. But it needs us all to get scared today to not settle for OK tomorrow.Ultimately a 3* review for a movie or album is likely to mean that existing fans of the director or band will buy it (and be happy with their purchase) but it is unlikely to get people who aren’t currently fans to go and see it.The exceptions probably occur when there’sa massive marketing campaign or when your partner bullies you into it – neither of which is likely to happen with Protection soon.Insurers must wake up to the risk of not doing anything – or not doing enough. Fintech currently struggles to meet the challenge posed by life insurance. There are easier pickings in general insurance and even investments and pensions that catch the eye. But this new approach, supported by new technology, will come – and when it does it will be quick, and some of those companies will be operating at 9 out of 10 levels.So how do we change? How do we get urgency into those who are not fearful and who are not inspired and motivated to really make change happen?• Emotionally engage with the customer, don’t educate them. A sentiment I totally agree with, distilled by Helen White of MAS / ABI at the Protection Review conference. I hate education. To wish or even lobby for education is improbable,paternalistic and patronising. Too often it enables us to continue to justify building complexity and confusion into products and processes.We shouldn’t educate the customer about why we are right and they are wrong – why we know more than they do about whatis best for them. Stories not statistics – emotion not education need to be at the forefront of our work. Like it or not we need to recognise the “post-facts, anti experts” world that Brexit encapsulates and learn from the successful techniques of this and other campaigns.• Deliver targeted process improvementsat clear groups of people. For all the self- loathing, well over a million people a year start a new protection policy. One size doesn’t fit all. Get bespoke – 10% of the existing market is a serious number and you may even grow it whilst you’re there. Whether you focus on the healthy young lives who haven’t engaged with protection before, the lives who have been declined by others, or the new business owners, get focused and make your whole journey relevant to them.• On the front line selling protection is a seriously competitive marketplace, with much more variance between companies– there are some 9s and some 2s out there in terms of both quality and quantity of protection sales. Insurers are desperate to work with sales channels that are hungry to sell protection the right way. If you have or want to build something that you’re proud of in the protection space, let those companies know and let them show you how hungry they can be to help boost your training, sales materials, processes and ultimately financials.If we do each of these well then I would be prepared to argue with anyone who gives usa 6 out of 10 review in the future. I think the shift in results if we achieved these aims could earn an extra point for each of these truly delivered. Working in a 9 out of 10 industry sounds something to work together to aim for. But it needs us all to get scared today to not settle for OK tomorrow.COVER ME NOW]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50A £200billion opportunityRon Wheatcroft | Technical Manager | Swiss ReThe UK falls behind the rest of Europe when it comes to its citizens being protected against the financial consequences of prolonged disability. Swiss Re reported in 2015 that the UK has a Disability Protection Gap totalling £200billion p.a., the largest shortfall in any European country.Many people continue to assume that their employer or the State, will provide for them. Some indications that people are gradually getting the message that the State is withdrawing have not translated into taking any action with new IP sales in 2015 just over100,000, being just 9% of new term life and critical illness policies. The number of in-force IP policies has declined by more than 20% since 2006.Although the number of people insured under employer-sponsored arrangements rose by 20% over the same period, the number of insured schemes is falling. We have seen atrend towards shorter benefit payment periods, both through new individual IP product options and, in the employer-sponsored market, the gradual reduction in benefit payment periods to a maximum payment period, typically no more than five years.Overall, no more people are covered than in 2006, at best, around 20% of the UK workforce either on an insured basis or where their employer chooses to self-insure.Of the new individual IP policies, 35% only pay for a limited period rather than through to expected retirement age, giving peoplebreathing space to adapt their finances to changed circumstances rather than addressing the longer-term need. What happens when benefits come to an end? Presumably people are happy to rely on their savings to see them through if, indeed, they think that far ahead. What about the other 80%, including self- employed people, with no cover at all.Purchasing income protection and selecting the appropriate level of coverage without advice or guidance is not simple - evenif people have every intention to do so. Consumer research carried out by Swiss Re identifies perceived product complexity as a big factor determining whether consumers feel sufficiently confident to purchase products or services without advice.Maintaining income is a classic area where quality advice adds real value. Going alone is not easy - a Google search brings up a mixture of products protecting against the financial consequences of redundancy or unemployment as well as IP.Although the number of people insured under employer-sponsored arrangements rose by 20% over the same period, the number of insured schemes is falling.]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[51Purchasing income protection and selecting the appropriate level of coverage without advice or guidance is not simple - even if people have every intention to do so.Existing employer provision is, of course, a vital consideration when looking at need. There is a strong case for annual benefit statements to reinforce the cover that the employer has arranged. So often, our research shows people overestimating what their employer will provide.Advisers can help people to understand their likely entitlement to State Benefits since, depending on their circumstances, private cover could simply replace benefits which would have been paid by the State. Deepening welfare budget cuts could mean that State Benefits become negligible or non-existent when disability occurs.It’s a sobering thought that work on a suiteof simple protection products, led by HM Treasury, began more than five years ago yet we still remain a very long way away from an income protection product which consumers could buy directly with any confidence. Thisis primarily down to the complex relationship between private and State Benefits. Universal credit, based on the household rather than the individual, makes it even harder to quantify the need for cover.Protecting long-term income is one of the most fundamental financial needs people have, arguably more important than saving for apension since, without income, other desired financial behaviours simply can’t happen.While this is a classic advice opportunity, new ways to access the market will be essentialif fewer customers have access to advice about their protection needs in the future, or just choose to purchase directly in the same way that they make other purchases. This might include a bigger role for employers as facilitators and raising awareness through workplace education rather than necessarily as providers.Simple steps to aid consumer understanding will make people more aware of the financial consequences of prolonged disability and what to do to protect against them. The Money Advice Service work on financial capability highlights just how far we have to go to help make people more resilient to life’s shocks.7 Families shows how powerful real case studies can be in presenting a compelling case: the material has led to increased intermediary sales. Levels of financial literacy are low yet, historically, the industry way of delivering messages has often been through statistics setting out the chances of prolonged disability and claims paid rates. These are useful but purchasing IP is, for most people, an emotional decision rather than one based on statistical analysis.While the choice as to whether to advise on income replacement needs is ultimately a commercial decision for intermediaries, that £200billion figure represents a real opportunity to build on and grow customer relationships.Simple steps toaid consumer understanding will make people more aware of the financial consequences of prolonged disability and what to do to protect against them.]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52Overcoming the ‘indifference’ challenge by harnessing the best of human and artificial intelligenceJustin Harper | Head of Marketing & Industry Relations | LV=The UK is vastly underinsured; most people find it difficult to understand and appreciate the everyday risks that they face – and are ignorant to the consequences and implications of those risks happening. When presented with the idea of financial protection a common brick wall reaction is ‘it won’t happen to me.’Many advisers we’ve spoken with have said that they struggle to handle and overcome this objection; they find it difficult to ‘quantify’ the risks and get clients involved at an emotional level.Whether we like it or not, the old adage remains true ‘protection needs to be sold’. Yet if your client doesn’t understand and buy in to the importance of protection, then they won’t buy into your recommendations.The rise of all things digital has changed the world we live in. But when it comes to the matters of protection, is technology your friend or your foe?A trip down memory laneI cut my protection selling teeth back in the days of the direct sales force - you might remember the likes of Allied Dunbar and the Pru. The 80’s pre-dated FCA and the FSA, and Lautro was just a young baby. Adviser status, commission disclosure andmost certainly RDR were years away. Mobile phones resembled heavy bricks and ‘social media’ meant catching up with your mates down the pub on a Friday night.Sales training was conducted with flipcharts and ‘gadgets’ such as the Overhead Projector, with training boot camps lasting weeks on end. Advisers ventured out to meet clients armed with rate table books and weighty tomes such as Visual Aid Folders (a big lever arch folder containing a variety of static ideas, concepts and diagrams).Sale questioning techniques were all the rage - remember SPIN? So too were simple concepts such as the ‘money making machine’ and ‘four boxes’. But the trusted friend of many a salesperson was the freedom of a ‘blank sheet of paper’.Whilst the days of yore weren’t all great, we were schooled in the art of selling. ‘Emotional disturbance’ was encouraged alongside the more rational aspects ofprocess, fact find forms, calculations and technical detail.Life was simple, an adviser was often at the centre of the community and insurance was a people business.Fast forward to the present dayFast forward 30 years or so to today, and we live in a completely different world. Technology and digital are woven intothe fabric of our everyday lives. Directsales forces are few and far between and arranging a mortgage requires many hours of form filling. The likes of Google and comparison sites are the go-to destinations for information and insurance.More advances are in train with developments in reflexive technology, devices and algorithms all combining to raise the prospects for robo-advice. In fact, the FCA has recently launched a new unit dedicated to these developments.]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[53If your client doesn’t understand and buy in to the importance of protection, then they won’t buy into your recommendations.Are such advances good or evil? Technology offers speed, consistency and accuracy, but ultimately its power for good, or otherwise, rests in the hands of the user and in its application.For the open minded pragmatists among us, there are opportunities for combining the best of human ability and the advantages of technology. I share two particular examples that have proven to change minds, influence behaviours and enable advisers to really engage clients in the need for protection.Triggering the power of emotionFew people wake up in the morning with a desperate urge to buy protection insurance; it remains a ‘grudge’ purchase. Overcoming ‘it will never happen to me’ through the logical arguments of reeling out incidences and claims stats don’t always cut through. That’s where the power of the human story comes into play.In the 80’s there was the (in)famous ‘Widow’s Story’; a fictional piece that attempted to highlight the financial and emotional impact of death on those left behind. It was ‘of its time’ and the acting was a little wooden... but many from that era still recall it with fondness.The most powerful film about protection.... Ever?Today, film is a common, flexible and accessible medium. An excellent exampleof portraying real stories comes from the 7 Families campaign. Sitting at the core of this consumer-focused charity based initiativeare seven real families. All have suffered from life changing illnesses and conditions; all have compelling stories to tell.The support for thefamilies under thecampaign is drawing to aclose, yet the films and the initiatives live on. If you haven’t checked them out yet, please do so at www.7families.co.uk. I challenge you or your clients to remain unmoved by the stories told sensitively and powerfully through film - particularly the introduction to Paul and Vicky Pickford.The best sales aid in the history of mankind?At LV= we’re passionate about lookingafter people financially through their extraordinary journey of life. However, many are oblivious to the risks they face, the importance of financial protection and the real value of professional financial advice.Through four simple numbers, the LV= Risk Reality Calculator shows the likelihood of your clients being off work for two months or more, suffering a serious illness, ordying - and importantly the probability of any of these happening - before a chosen retirement age.In just a matter of seconds, they’ll grasp the importance of protection. The results can kick start an eye opening conversation about what’s really important to them and the real value of financial advice. And the calculator automatically generates a personalised risk report which you can print, email and share.The simple website design also features support, facts and videos to help your conversation with your client. And because it’s so simple, advisers find it easy to integrate into their advice process; some send it to clients ahead of their meetings, some introduce it at the meeting and others are using to support ongoing protection reviews. You can try it yourself, and with your clients, at www.riskreality.co.uk/gen.The best of human and artificial intelligenceAt LV= we believe in the power of advice and the value of protection. We’ve highlighted just two examples of how modern day tech can help you when talking protection with your clients. You can explore many more tools, calculators and stories at www.lv.com/adviser.]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[54Multi-Benefit service on Synaptic WeblineWarren O’Connell and Simon Torr | Synaptic Software LimitedA survey by the Money Advice Service (MAS) recently found that almost half of working age couples and families don’t have life cover. Take up of Income Protection in the UK is even lower at around 11% (which is low by international standards).Research commissioned by the ABI has found that 10.6m households representing more than 60% of working families would see their income fall by more than a third, if the main earner had to stop work due to ill health.We also know the probable impact of a critical illness and death on families.Some advisers say that protection can take time to write, but others find it a quick and very profitable way to fulfil clients’ needs. So how can recommendations and the advice processbemadeeasier? ByusingWebline.Let’s look at the benefits offered by Multi-Benefit on Synaptic Webline:• Multi-Benefit provides the best chance of maximising Protection cover and assists with compliance• A client is more likely to accept a ‘bundled’ product and more likely to reject separate recommendations, making Multi-Benefit an easier sell• SynapticWeblineallowsyoutoconsiderup to nine permutations of the same product at the same time – allowing you to consider multiple options• Efficiency of the sales process can be greatly enhanced through the time saved in making applications and completing underwriting where required, benefitting both adviser and client.Income ProtectionOffering the flexibility of ‘stepped’ deferred periods will help fit around any existing arrangements such as work schemes. The cost can be reduced making it easier for the client to accept.How it works – Standalone or ‘Multi-Benefit’ journeySynaptic Webline will identify an opportunity to recommend a Multi-Benefit product when standalone productshave been chosen. Thismay or may not be advantageous to pursue, so both standalone and Multi-Benefit options will be displayed together.Alternatively you can quote directly on a Multi-Benefit basis.Did you know?Webline currently manages up to 1m quotes requests per month (that’s more than 10m responses) and facilitates about one fifth of all term assurance policies written in the UK?]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[55Research commissioned by the ABI has found that 10.6m households representing morethan 60% of working families would see their income fall by more than a third, if the main earner had to stop work due to ill health.The Multi-Benefit specific journey is very similar to the individual products journey. Simply select the benefits you require for your quotation from the following products:Each product then has its separate quotation input page (as in standalone guise)As with all protection products on Synaptic Webline:• The user can apply electronically with a simple click and have all of their details pre-populated on the chosen providers’ extranet site• Quotes for each individual product selected will be returned as they are now, allowing the adviser the opportunity to see the prices and terms and conditions of each indivdual product• Oncetheproductsbeingrecommendedareaddedtothe‘basket’,SynapticWeblinewillnow show you whether a Multi-Benefit product could be used with the same levels of cover and benefit from one single provider (see below)• Synaptic Webline will request quotes and compile results as you perform your research, combining multiple options in a manner that will allow you to further adjust the parameters if required ‘on the fly’.For more information contact us sales@synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[A NEW BREED OFMODEL PORTFOLIOSAs the markets continue to face high volatility; now more than ever Advisers stand to benefit from working with specialist investment managers to support their investment process and manage clients’ money.FE Invest offers a new breed of risk optimised model portfolios targeted at the complete range of investor risk profiles. Our approach leverages the efficiency of cutting edge technology with the oversight of experienced professionals to deliver an optimal investment service that will add real value to your business and your clients.www.feinvest.netCONTACT US ATenquiries@financialexpress.net or 0207 534 7667 BOOK A FREE DEMO]]></page></pages></Search>