<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?><Search><pages Count="56"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ConnectionIssue:Q4 2016Selection of industry features for the professional adviserSynaptic Software• Masters of the Universe – the golden age of advice• No longer is retirement the finish line• Platform Centric. Perspective on platform due diligence• Managing Risk• Customer Experience Health Check• 5 great reasons to use Synaptic WeblineMasters of the UniverseThe value of advice - David NormanInside...›› Stop the world I want to get off! F&TRC›› Where to find reliable yields? Alistair Evans›› Looking beyond labels to protect the portfolio, Investec Asset Management ›› Politics, policy and perceptions. Susanne Grabinger, M&G Investments›› Why that fund for that client? Verbatim Asset Management›› Currency Risk, Ben Raven, Tavistock Wealth›› The Brainless Portfolio, FinalytiQ›› Time to look beyond price, Royal London›› The truth... Andrew Wibberley, Alea Risk]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[The Suitability SuiteRisk . Costs . Due diligence . Best adviceProof of suitability is easier with Synaptic Research• The regulator is making proof of suitability the cornerstone of its enforcement policy• Synaptic provides proof of suitability in the key areas of product features, risk and costsSynaptic Product and Fund Whole of market product and fund research, full suitability reportingSynaptic ComparatorDetailed price analysis for platforms, products and funds including R.I.Y. calculationsSynaptic RiskA.T.R.Q. and Risk Rated funds and portfoliosSynaptic ModellerModels investment outcomes for new existing holdings. Manage and assess investment riskProtection and Annuity quotes and on-line applications Synaptic Webline (including enhanced annuities)Synaptic Suitability offer £140 per licence, per month (excl. VAT) - rrp is £226Apply today, call us on 0800 783 4477 or email us at sales@synaptic.co.uk quoting ‘Suitability Offer’.SAVE OVER£125 PER LICENCE]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[CONTENTSMasters of the Universe 04 Eric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedThe value of advice 06 David Norman, TCF Investments & MAPSA convenient way to help clients 10 reach retirement goalsNeil Cowell, Vanguard Asset ManagementWhere to find reliable yields in times of turmoil? 12 Alistair Evans, Bedford Row Capital AdvisersStop the world I want to get off! 14 Kerry Nicolaides, Digital Wealth InsightsIncome Thinking: Structurally 16 diversifying sources of riskJohn Stopford, Investec Asset ManagementPolitics, policy and perceptions 18 Susanne Grabinger, M&G InvestmentsThe four pillars: The benefits of Simplicity 20 Justin Onuekwusi CFA, Legal & General Investment ManagementWhy that fund for that client? 22 Davinia Rogers, Verbatim Asset ManagementBrainless Portfolio: The natural benchmark for 24 multi-asset fundsAbraham Okusanya, FinalytiQA steady outlook but watch out for 26 the banana skinsAlex Scott, Seven Investment ManagementCurrency risk – a real and present danger to 28 advisers and clientsBen Raven, Tavistock WealthFeeling the Squeeze 31 Fiona Tait, Royal LondonNo longer is retirement the finishing line 32 Pete Bayliss, Synaptic Software LimitedPlatform Centric 34 Ellen Ashcroft ACII, Synaptic Software LimitedManaging Risk: a clear winner is emerging 36 for advisersEric Armstrong, Synaptic Software LimitedSynaptic Risk Table 38 Customer Experience Health Check 44Tiina Stephens, Synaptic Software LimitedTime to look beyond price 47 Fiona Holmes, Royal LondonNew occupation trends are emerging, 48 do we have them covered?Nick Jones, The ExeterThe truth, the whole truth and 50 nothing but the truthAndrew Wibberley, Alea RiskThe rise of more affordable income protection 52 Justin Harper, LV=5 great reasons to use Synaptic Webline 54 Synaptic Software Limited3The skill and wisdom of advisersContact DetailsSynaptic Software LimitedFusion 1, Parkway, Solent Business Park Whiteley, Hampshire PO15 7AASales: 0800 783 4477To sign up for Connection magazine visitwww.synaptic.co.ukAll editorial or advertising enquiries should be directed to:Eric Armstrongeric.armstrong@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882994Naomi Hardmannaomi.hardman@synaptic.co.uk 01489 882969A few years ago, I remember Justin U-S providing an insight based on his experience. Most investors, he argued, need to know that their investments are secure and in good hands. In addition however, many also enjoy the opportunity to do a little ‘experimentation’ at the edges. I didn’t really understand what he meant, but I do now, because I find the insight applying directly to me. I have learnt a lot about the value of advice, and the strategies employed by advisers from my mistakes around ‘the edges’ over the last few years.It has taken 18 months to get backon even keel following a false sense of complacency in early 2015 followed by a near death experience. Having over-egged it, I suffered a classic panic, de-risked ‘at the bottom’ and failed to benefit fully from the subsequent global recovery. I sold out of the Aussie Dollar before Brexit (as I thought the pound was obviously going to go up and the Aussie Dollar down) and pumped up on Property, so taking both barrels when the opposite happened. Astonishingly, many hedge funds have fared worse!Many of you will be dismissing this as obvious, but I mention it as it really does bring home the importance of sensibly constructed, well diversified portfolios based on the kind of research that characterises best practice in our industry.Getting personally burnt by uncontrolled risk is a great way of appreciating why the kind of risk models developed by Moody’s really are so valuable and so effective, and should be used to mitigate against poor research or speculation in client portfolios. (More inside).The skill and wisdom of advisers is the theme of this edition of Connection, and the articles in some way or another reflect the knowledge and expertise that underpins advisers’ work. In this edition we look at the possibility that we are living in a golden age of financial advice in the UK and we find ourselves feeling more than a little proud ofthe contribution made by Synaptic in enabling the research and due diligence capabilities of so many outstanding firms.Eric ArmstrongEditorThe Connection magazine is published by Synaptic Software Limited. The views expressed throughout do not necessarily reflect the views of Synaptic or any other party affiliated to Synaptic, and no liability can be assumed for the accuracy or completeness of the content, nor should any of the content be used as the sole basis of any advice offered or received.Content is offered on an information only basis, and intended only for an audience of professional advisers regulated by the FCA. Content is published with all rights reserved and any reproduction of content, wholly or in part, can be made with the written permission of the publishers. This applies to all forms of the magazine - digital and print, and any part there of.]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[4SYNAPTICMasters of the universeEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedThe proposed pension’s dashboard is the latest gift from policy makers that will ensure a golden period of financial planning. For the foreseeable future advisers will be reaping the rewards, but what is it all about?From time to time it is worth ‘stepping back’ and getting the macro lens out to survey the territory. We at Synaptic have been trying to think hard about the future, particularly in respect of our industry, our role as technology providers and the evolution of advice. Frankly there are so many variables – from changing consumer habits, political, economical and regulatory considerations, that this is by no means simple.However you dress it up, people seem to need people to reassure them when it comes to the big financial decisions in their lives.We notice that some consultants’ reports, and wider discussions around the evolutionof ‘automated advice’, do not necessarily agree with this centrality or need for advisers. With its FinTech and workplace related initiatives, the government is trying very hard to engineer outcomes that rely on scale and automation – in some respects by-passing the adviser. By changing the definition of ‘a personal recommendation’, advice can be partguidance and ‘simplified’ to the extent that automation and the provision of advice can go hand in hand.Of course the question of who pays when things go wrong becomes a lot more complicated, but the government has never overly worried when saddling the bills run up by rogue operators on the shoulders of the compliant and responsible. A lot of advisers would argue that the policy is simply misguided. What is the point of promoting savings when the average UK household is net in debt? You will always be better off paying off expensive unsecured borrowing over saving. (Household debt is increasing, even with the prospect of higher interest rates around the corner).Government policy is trying to reach out to accommodate the ‘squeezed middle’ who cannot or will not afford advice, and therefore are compromising their financial securityby failing to save adequately for retirement. Ironically, one of the reasons why the Treasuryand government are trying something newis because they (partly) caused the collapsein pension’s savings through their meddling. They couldn’t resist treating pensions as their own resource and raiding pensions. Gordon Brown abolished tax relief on dividend income for pensions in 1997 to raise well over £100bn to date - money that could should have remained invested in pensions.The fact is the challenges of the wider market do not necessarily affect financial advisers, as they cater for the wealthy minority. Currently there are not enough financial advisers to cater to this segment. It is not the adviser’s fault if Joe Public is skint.Moreover, the well explored narrative of wealth in 2016 tells us that the baby boomers (born 1946-64) own the majority of all kinds of wealth including property and savings (although they will soon be outnumbered in the workplace). As this cohort moves more into retirement phase and looks to replace salaries with withdrawals from investments,]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC5Government policy is trying to reach out to accommodate the ‘squeezed middle’ who cannot or will not afford advice, and therefore are compromising their financial security by failing to save adequately for retirement.they will need a lot of advice, and we assume they will continue to want to be served by the advisers they have always trusted, who see and experience the world much as they do.Several more major trends are working in favour of our traditional adviser:(i) The majority of adviser incomeis earned advising on pensions (FCA Product Sales Data show a whopping 72%). We have looked at how baby-boomers will be retiring in droves, freeing up increasing amounts of pension savings. Some commentators have described this opportunity as a ‘tidal wave’ of money. Pension Freedom means that most wealthy individuals will stay invested in the long term. Within this sector, this surge of money will overwhelm any other trend;(ii) There is more incentive than ever to come out of DB schemes, especially with the option to pass on pensions savings;iii) There are not that many advisers. Inthe US there are over 1 million advisers and brokers to help you make financial decisions. In the UK it is more like 35k. Broadly speaking there are just over 300 potential clients for each adviser in the US compared to just under 2000 in the UK. Talk about opportunity!One point of perspective though. The ‘golden age’ can be measured by the shape of the demographic wave that represents baby boomers. In a decade or so, the adviserswho service this market will themselvesbe growing long in the tooth, and they will begin to ‘fall off the perch’ alongside their customers. By this time Generation ‘X’ and their following cohort ‘the millennials’ will form the majority of the workforce, and will be starting to take stewardship of assets from their parents. PwC in 2011 estimated that advisers lose over 50% of wealth when it transfers down a generation. The prospect of falling off the next cliff may not worry today’s advisers unduly if they can enjoy profitable years in between – there may be enough time to adapt in any case.Going back to our original point, the pension’s dashboard could become a major catalyst for the identification of retiree funds in need of advice (its stated aim in fact). We at Synaptic are bringing the dashboard opportunity to the centre of our thinking. Although the dashboard is not conceived for the benefitof traditional advice firms, whoever the customer chooses to trust with their pensions choices, we’re pretty sure an adviser will be at their shoulder and there will be mountains of cash to tidy up.So whereas financial services policy is designed to support new ways of servicing the great British public (there’s lots of talkof new ‘Apps’ and behavioural ‘nudging’), it looks as if UK advisers and their customers are increasingly in a privileged position that is unlikely to be undermined in this generation. Advisers are indeed the Masters of their universe.The fact is the challenges of the wider market do not necessarily affect financial advisers, as they cater for the wealthy minority.Mapping the generationsAge in 2016 18 - 35 36 - 51 52 - 70 71+Baby BoomersBorn 1946 - 64Generation ‘X’Born 1965 - 80MillennialsBorn 1981 - 98Silent GenerationBorn 1928 - 45]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[6The Value of Advice (or free BMWs?)David Norman | CEO | TCF Investment and MAPSIn my last article I looked at the overall value chain for financial advice and how advisers and planners (IFAs) were responding to the challenges of RDR (Retail Distribution Review), looking to take a fairer and greater share of the whole value chain, while at the same time keeping overall costs under control.One of the biggest challenges of RDR is that customers now know in pounds and pence the precise cost of advice – but do they know the value?Our survey says:Over the last few years, in the run up to and post RDR, I have seen endless surveys saying that a customer will only pay £40 per hour for advice, or a maximum of £250.Well of course if you ask someone in the street how much they are prepared to pay for financial advice, getting divorced or selling a house, they'll say as little as possible! What the surveys rarely show is how much customers are prepared to pay for these services when the benefits are explained to them!I meet many IFAs in my travels and I often ask them to tell me what the value of advice is. “Having a good plan”, “staying on track”, "achieving your goals,” I often hear. Would you pay £1500 a year to stay on track?The good old daysI remember my first few months in the industry – sitting in the training room of London Life in Bristol – the sales managers and sales trainers spent hours and hours drumming into us raw recruits “features and benefits”, features and benefits”!And that to me is still one of the great challenges the IFAs community needs to grasp – how can we get a wider appreciation of the value or benefit of advice – and ideally in a form that customers and the media can quickly and easily understand?Any ideas?In typical thorough and analytical style, the fine people at Vanguard had a good attempt at estimating what they described as Adviser Alpha: https://www.vanguard.co.uk/ documents/portal/press_releases/value- of-advice-research.pdfVery comprehensive but not very pithy.Claude Montmarquette, Professor Emeriuus at CIRANO in Canada, did a study of “econometric analysis of the value of advice in Canada” in 2012. He found, in summary, that the value of household financial assets for those receiving advice for 15 or more years was a whopping 273% higher than those with no advice.“Would you pay 1% a year of your assets to be 273% better off in 15 years’ time?” Seems like a good deal to me!]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[7FeatureWhat we doBenefitTax efficiencyMake sure that we utilise as many of your tax reliefs and allowances each yearYour money grows fasterIncrease investor protectionLook at how best to maximise your protection under the Financial Services Compensation scheme (FSCS)Your investments are “safer”Reduce portfolio riskWe use sophisticated modelling tools to try to maximise your return for a given level of risk / risk toleranceBetter potential performance with less downsideConduct rigorous due diligence on all your investmentsWe conduct thorough and robust due diligence and research on all the funds and products that we useWith over 9000 instruments in the UK we use our expertise in order to save your time while giving you peace of mindHold your hand through difficult timesDivorce, death, business transition are stressful times – good to have our experience and expertise to assist and guide you through themWe are there when you need us mostPre-fund investment dealingWe look at the most efficient platforms to hold your investments to make sure your costs and time delays are minimisedCould save you many £s over the years (and is often missed by investors)How can we get a wider appreciation of the value or benefit of advice – and ideally in a form that customers and the media can quickly and easily understand?The robots are coming?I suspect there will be a battle hotting up in the coming years between some mass market robo-advisers (probably the banks and other online retailers) and the cost of their internet offerings versus financial advisers. Though I suspect many of these entrants will be roboselling rather than robo-advising – and we all know where that might end!Eating an elephantI think one of the best ways to approach the idea of advice is to break down each element of the service that advisers provide and produce a simple table showing the feature, the work / activity undertaken and the benefit to the customer.For example:This allows a range of financial, emotional, time saving and other benefits that will appeal to a range of customers to be created. They can then be used in service agreements, websites, client documentation etc.Perhaps firms with a number of RIs can have brainstorming sessions to come up with more ideas (if you would like a few more to kick it off just drop me a line).In £s please?All these ideas are great but they still don’t achieve the holy grail of showing the value of advice in pounds.But if you could:1. Reduce the cost of an existing portfolio by 1% a year2. Improve risk adjusted returns by 0.5% pa by use of a more efficient / diversified portfolio3. Boost investment returns by 10% or more by maximising tax allowances (that would be worth 0.5% pa based on 5% pa along run returns)4. Provide “insurance” against fraud and theft by providing Professional Indemnity cover and FSCS cover for client assets - that is probably worth 0.25% pa (on the same basis as paying £250 pa to protect you £100,000 car from theft).5. Help customers avoid the “buy high sell low” behavioural loss – that Dalbar and others suggest costs investors over 2% per yearIt is easy to show how your advice might save the client 4.25% pa or more over them “doing-it- themselves.” Net of an advice fee of 1% pa they are still over 3% pa better off.For an investor with a £150,000 portfolio invested with just a 2% pa boost from your advice (or 2% pa less drag) they could be £42,000 better off over 10 years assuming a total gross return of 7% pa.And £42,000 is enough to buy a shiny new 5 series BMW.Imagine your advice being worth a free brand new BMW every 10 years .... you don’t need to imagine it, you really are worth it!Notes:http://www.cirano.qc.ca/pdf/publication/2012RP-17_Presentation_ Value%20of%20Advice.pdf]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[10A convenient way to help clients reach retirement goalsNeil Cowell | Head of UK Retail Sales | Vanguard Asset ManagementThe pensions landscape has undergone a number of significant reforms in recent years. Among key changes is the removal of the requirement for retirees to annuitise their pension savings. This has opened the way for significantly greater flexibility in accessing pension savings fromthe minimum pension age, (currently 55). Another key change is auto- enrolment, the requirement for employers to enrol qualifying employees into a pension scheme.What do these changes mean for investors? Investors need to take greater personal responsibility, think long term and seek an enduring solution to meet their retirement goals. To ensure investors have adequate savings for retirement, they should save during their working life and establish clear goals when investing to meet their aspirations for a sufficient standard of living through retirement.However, research shows us that many investors lack time for, or interest in, retirement planning. Even a motivated saver can make mistakes or fail to manage a portfolio’s strategy effectively over time. Target Retirement Funds (TRFs) address these challenges by offering a convenient single fund solution which adapts over time to the investor’s stage of life up to and beyond retirement. TRFs allow investors tobenefit, with minimal intervention, from a professionally constructed, diversified portfolio, simplifying the asset allocation process over a long-term investment lifecycle.The removal of the requirement to buy an annuity on retirement means that some investors may be able to achieve higher expected incomes in retirement by exploiting their expected long time-horizon and staying invested in growth-oriented assets for longer, even in the years beyond retirement. TRFs are generally designed to exploit this preferred approach to retirement saving. This is done by choosing an asset allocation that adapts over time to the investor’s stage of life, not onlyin the years up to retirement, but also in the years beyond retirement. This is important because while retirees draw spending from their savings in retirement, those savings stillneed to sustain them through retirement for possibly 20-30 years.Asset-allocationThere are two strategic principles that support the way that TRFs are built: firstly, that there are potential rewards for taking equity market risk over the long term, and secondly, that younger investors are better able to withstand that risk than older investors because a larger percentage of their total wealth is in ‘human capital’ versus their financial holdings.The principle that younger investors are better able to withstand risk recognises that an individual’s total net worth consists of bothhis or her current financial holdings and their future earnings. For younger individuals, the majority of their ultimate retirement wealth is in the form of what they will earn in the future,]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[11Research shows us that many investors lack time for, or interest in, retirement planning. Even a motivated saver can make mistakes or fail to manage a portfolio’s strategy effectively over time.or their ‘human capital’. Therefore, it is likely to be appropriate for a younger person’s portfolio to have a larger commitment to equity, to balance and diversify his or her risk exposure to work-related earnings.Glidepath constructionThe human capital theory supports a significant commitment to equities foryoung individuals, declining to a moremodest allocation as the investor approaches retirement and eventually leaves the workforce. TRFs will therefore usually maintain a significant level of equity exposure, sayto around 80%, until the investor’s early to mid-40s, because one’s human capital remains dominant over one’s financial capital during the early stages of asset accumulation. After the early to mid-40s age range, the equity allocation should typically continue to decline until the investor is over 70, compensatingfor the shifting balance between human and financial capital.Once retirement is reached, the retiree’s pool of savings will gradually run down as their spending remains steady but their contributions decline. By remaining invested, the portfolio could continue to grow as long as the spending rate throughout retirement is prudent. To help meet retirees’ needs for diversification and growth potential for possibly 20-30 years in retirement, and tooffset inflation and longevity risk, TRFs might still offer significant equity exposure at an investor’s designated retirement year, which is gradually reduced over the next seven years to 30% and remains constant thereafter.It’s important to remember that retirement is not necessarily a one-time event, but insteada transitional period. Many pre-retirees and recent retirees still have the ability - though far less so than younger investors - to alter their retirement plans if absolutely necessary. The modest exposure to equities can diversify their portfolios and help them realise their long- term goals. In addition, in the UK, most retirees have a portion of their wealth in the form of relatively safe, inflation-adjusted State Pension benefits, which should be diversified with some exposure to the equity markets.Why TRFs?TRFs automatically adjust the asset mix to help ensure that the investor has the right portfoliofortheirstageinlife,whichmakes them a convenient retirement solution. As well as this, they also automatically rebalance, either constantly through cashflows orat regular intervals. This helps to keep the portfolio aligned to the investor’s established investment objectives, correcting the asset allocation, for example, following strong market movements.However, investors should assess their personal situation and decide if their chosen TRF continues to be appropriate for their financial goals. In addition to costs, they need to monitor investments from time to time to ensure that the asset allocation remains aligned to their specific investment objective, time horizon and risk appetite.TRFs offer financial advisers an excellent choice for those clients suited to a simple, transparent, low-cost, long-term solution. Like any good solution, it is not a universal panacea, but it helps to solve the problems it was designedto meet. Neither does it replace the adviser, whose role in tax planning, spending strategies and behavioural coaching remains essential.Important information:This document is directed at professional investors in the UK only, and should not be distributed to or relied upon by retail investors. It is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell investments.The information in this document does not constitute legal, tax, or investmentadvice.Youmustnot,therefore,relyonthecontentof this document when making any investment decisions.The value of investments, and the income from them, may fall or rise and investors may get back less than they invested.The opinions expressed in this document are those of individual author and may not be representative of Vanguard Asset Management, Ltd.Issued by Vanguard Asset Management, Limited which is authorised and regulated in the UK by the Financial Conduct Authority.© 2016 Vanguard Asset Management]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[12BEDFORD ROW CAPITAL ADVISERSWhere to find reliable yields in times of turmoil?Alistair Evans | Director | Bedford Row Capital AdvisersPick up any financial publication and the common theme is the lack of safe, reliable income or yield available to investors. With Sterling falling to historic lows in the aftermath of Brexit, the FTSE 100 has risen to all-time highs, possibly due in some degree to the boost the weak pound has given to exporters.It would take a brave investor, however, to rely on income from equity dividends, particularly with stock markets at such lofty levels. What use is a 6% equity dividend if the underlying stock drops by 10 or 20%? Sovereign bonds such as Gilts and Treasuries represent nothing more than return-free risk, in stark contrastto what they have traditionally offered! This only leaves a couple of options, the most obvious of which is corporate bonds. They can provide reasonable returns but it must be remembered that corporate bonds generally represent unsecured corporate credit riskand this is inherently correlated to the stock market. So why would you want to assume corporate credit risk with the equity indicesat all-time highs? The other common option, remaining in cash, may seem like a sensible ploy in times like these but this has never been a viable long term option in times of inflation.A quite sobering fact is that a third of all listed debt currently in circulation has a negative yield, and the only explanation I can offer for institutions continuing to purchase negative- yielding debt is that they think rates are going to become “even more negative”. Whilst economists have a poor record for forecasting interest rates (with a success rate that is statistically likely to be bettered by tossing acoin) the Bank of England official (repo) rate is currently 0.25% and it is not an unfeasible prospect for the UK to join countries such as Denmark and Switzerland in negative interest rate territory.With all of this in mind, you would thinkthat as savers are being so poorly rewarded, borrowers would benefit from low rates,but in reality there is currently a total disconnect between the rates that saversare receiving and the rates being charged to borrowers. Banks have historically dominated the lending market, particularly in the SME sector where it is often most required, but they have largely stepped away from such markets in recent years. Given that SMEsare the main engines of growth in the economy, why would banks not want to lend into this particular space? Much of this can be attributed to bank de-leveraging in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis. The need to “deleverage” causes banks to shed assets and reduce lending, resulting in tighter borrowing constraints for businesses. This has led to a process of disintermediation, in terms of which banks are being left out of the equation and savers are lending (almost) directly to borrowers.The first wave of this disintermediation was the advent of peer-to-peer and crowd-funding platforms, and it is part of a larger movement that has been hailed as the rise of the “non- bank banks” (that is to say, institutions who lend money but do not take deposits). There is, however, a way to achieve similar returns to the peer-to-peer space but with increased investor security.Asset-backed bondsBedford Row Capital Advisers (BRCA) is a corporate finance firm comprised of capital markets, investment management and banking professionals and was created to capitalise on the disintermediation of banks. BRCA creates high-yielding listed debt instruments or asset-backed bonds using a secure trust structure which is specifically designed to protect the interests of bondholders.Firms such as BRCA can step into the gap to offer both attractive yielding investments as well as additional options for borrowers, particularly in the SME space. We do this by creating listed, asset-backed bonds.]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[13Case studyBRCA recently structured an asset- backed bond for Just Cash Flow Plc, a specialist SME lender, who have operated since 2012 without a single capital loss. In this instance, a pool of SME loans originated by Just Cash Flow was created to give investors either an 8.5% annual return over 5 years or a 7.25% annual return over 3 years. The SME loans themselves are over-collateralised on average by >10x whilst the segregated pool is pledged to the security trusteein favour of the bondholders, thereby ensuring that the investors essentially have two levels of security.The asset-backed bonds are then listed on an HMRC recognised stock exchange and are therefore freely transferrable, meaning they are SIPPable, ISAableand meet the FCA “standard asset” criteria. They also have an appointed market-maker to provide secondary market liquidity. Purchasing the bondsis very straightforward as they are “dematerialised” or electronically settled within the CREST central clearing system and can be identified by their ISIN number, as well as being priced by all the major data providers such as Bloomberg and Financial Express.Finding yield hard to come by? Consider asset-backed bondsif you are lookingfor a secure, easy to understand product with a healthy return.Asset-backed bonds are bonds backed bya loan, lease or receivable held against specified assets (for instance real estate or other tangible, realisable assets). They are an attractive alternative to investing in corporate debt, which is most often unsecured. They offer appealing returns at an acceptable level of risk with a high likelihood of recoverability should something go wrong. Asset-backed bonds structured by BRCA are created usinga secure trust structure, meaning that the segregated assets producing the yield are pledged in favour of a security trustee, which is part of a 300 year old London law firm. The result is that investors are not taking on corporate credit risk or issuer risk, but a risk that is purely determined by a segregated pool of over-collateralised assets.How to evaluate asset-backed bonds:Clear Distribution work closely with Bedford Row Capital Advisers, and provide a dedicated IFA support service tasked with providing fulfilment and educational support for these and other products. We have a wealth of additional information to share. If you would like to attend one of the educational roadshows or simply need some help with your due diligence then please contact Andrew Rockey at enquiries@cleardistribution.co.uk.He will be happy to help.More information is available at www.cleardistribution.co.uk or www.bedfordrowcapital.comAndrew Rockey | Clear Distribution]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[14Stop the world I want to get off! (But just for 5 minutes)Kerry Nicolaides | Lead Analyst | Digital Wealth InsightsTechnology is bringing about one of the biggest storms to hit civilisation as we know it, the Digital Age, leaving in its wake significant changes to the way we engage in our daily activities and carry out our jobs.Financial Services is fast approaching the eye of the ‘digital storm’. It’s hard not to get lost in the plethora and excitement of it all with FinTech, Big Data, robo-advice and Chatbots all making their debut.Established financial service organisations preferring to wait out the storm in the hope that it passes, will very shortly find their business being buffeted by organisations standing out in the open field, embracing the storm head on with conducting rods in their hands.Like it or not, this storm isn’t passing.Although initially behind the FinTech curve, not only is the UK financial services catching up to the rest of the world in developing and providing automated financial services, but having learnt from early international adopters, in some cases are already showing signs of leading edge superior functionality.With an actively engaged, forward thinking, and pro-digital government and regulatory body, you can safely bet on the UK continuing to make great waves intoautomating financial services to engage the mass market in saving for their future.While the UK is churning out a significant number of low cost investment propositions, our analysis identifies a gaping hole in the market. This presents a real danger thatnew services may not penetrate the mass market. These consumers do not currentlyhave either the financial education or the financial means to embrace these low cost automated investment propositions.The diagram below identifies the key steps a consumer should go through on the journey towards building a sustainable and successful ‘Financial Life’.]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[15LANDSCAPE OF UK AUTOMATED FINANCIAL SERVICE PROPOSITIONSMy Financial LifeFor consumers, managing their finances can involve making some of the most important and challenging decisions of their lives, yet they frequently do not have the means to understand the information on which such decisions should be based, nor do they have support in making the right choice.Multiple studies identify one of the greatest causes of human stress, ill health and unhappiness is lack of knowledge of how to manage income, expenditure and debt.Our analysis highlights a glaring failure within most of the market is the lack of focus on assisting the consumer in managing these three components, in order to help them prepare for longer term savings.(steps 1-3)F&TRC’s DigitalWealthInsights.com team are actively monitoring over 130 organisations within the UK that are currently in various stages of developing digital financial services propositions for consumers.The graph below illustrates which part of the consumer’s ‘financial life’ these propositions cater for.68% of automated financial service propositions provide an online investment service. Of these propositions 81% do not address the consumer’s income, expenditure and debt at all. If the objective is to provide automated financial advice to the mass market, then is it fair to say that 81% of automated investment propositions in the UK are not optimised to help the mass market?My question then is, how much longevity and customer loyalty will these propositions have when the debt managers and micro savings tools start to gain momentum by actively helping customers improve their financial life?Consumer DebtThe Office for Budget Responsibility identified that credit card debt in May 2016 was £2,397 per household. Based on an average interest rate and minimum payment this would take 25 years and 6 months to repay. It also suggested that consumer borrowing trends will result in most UK households spending more than they earn for the rest of the decade.Micro SavingsThe savings landscape is changing. There is no longer any reason for savings to be regular or centred on a single long-term goal now that there are micro saving tools to encourageconsumers to save little and save often, as and when funds become available.Of all the propositions I analyse on a daily basis there are very few with which I actively engage. Moneybox (www.moneyboxapp.com) is an exception. It is a great example of using micro savings to contribute towards an ISA or Investment account. I was able to save £94in six weeks simply by rounding up my daily spending transactions to the nearest £1.Cleo is another example of a Chatbot (www.meetcleo.com) budgeting tool which I use regularly. Instead of logging into my online banking or trying to make sense of a pie chart, I am able to send a simple text to Cleo to get the information I need instantly.Whilst these two tools don’t have all the optimal functionality, they actively help me save and move towards a better financial life.Our income, expenditure and debt definehow we live our lives today, tomorrow and ultimately into future. Is it not crucial therefore to ensure that every person gets steps 1-3 right before approaching any actual investment, protection or retirement advice?To provide a truly effective automated proposition it is essential that we focus on helping the consumer build their financiallife from the ground up. We would encourage those organisations standing out in the storm to think of the end consumer and the journey they need to take in order to get in a position to actively engage in your proposition.Those organisations waiting out the storm–it’s coming for you!Further access to our analysis can be found at www.digitalwealthinsights.com (currently in beta). We aim to provide our audience with objective comparisons alongside our own informed analysis of automated financial service propositions, market trends and clarity around topics which typically create confusion.]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[16Income Thinking: Structurally Diversifying Sources of RiskJohn Stopford | Head of Multi-Asset Income | Investec Asset ManagementLooking beyond labels to protect the portfolioTraditionally, an investor’s portfolio hasbeen allotted to different asset classes inthe hope of achieving desired returns while diversifying risk. Investec’s Multi-AssetIncome team place greater emphasis on an investment’s relationship with the economic cycle in determining its place in a portfolio than we do on its simple label. An asset’slabel usually provides little insight, or worse still, can be misleading with regards to its risk-reward characteristics. Figure 1 below, shows the percentage return on different asset classes over the recent equity drawdown.As can be seen, securities with very different classifications but comparable characteristics produce similar returns.To achieve true, or structural diversification, we prefer to divide assets into ‘Growth’, ‘Defensive’, and ‘Uncorrelated’ (G/D/U) buckets. Equities or lower grade company debt are highly correlated with the health of the global economy, being reliant on periods of economic expansion for earnings potential. Consequently, we classify both shares and high yield corporate bonds as Growth assets rather than thinking of them as equities and fixed income.By contrast, investments such as high quality bonds typically have inverse relationships with the economic cycle, offering more Defensive properties. These have tended to deliver better returns in more difficult economic conditions.Certain asset classes are little affected by the economic cycle, such as infrastructure investments, the cashflows of which are frequently backed by very long-dated government funding, and therefore behave in an Uncorrelated fashion with Growthand Defensive assets. Crucially, to be used effectively, these classifications requirean understanding beyond historical relationships and an anticipation of future trends. There are important implications for a defensive return strategy. Firstly, a characteristic-focused approach avoids the need for market timing or overtrading when high levels of market stress cause asset class correlations in parts of the portfolioto rise. This allows investors to consistently collect the coupon or dividend payments0 -2 -4 -6 -8 -10 -12 -14 -16 -18 -20-18.6% MSCI World ($)-10.8%BOFA ML GLB Original High Yield ($)-11.3%BOFA ML Global 300 Convertible-14.1%FTSE EPRA/Nariet Developed ($)Figure 1:Percentage return over equity drawdown across different labels (with similar characteristics)Source: Morningstar, Bloomberg, BofA Merrill Lynch, Investec Asset Management. Drawdown from May 2015to equity low of February 2016. Global Equity: MSCI World; High Yield Bonds: BofAML Original High Yield; Source: Morningstar, Bloomberg, BofA Merrill LyCnoncvhe,rtInibvlees:sBtoefcAAMsesreriltl LMynacnhaGgloebmale3n0t0.CDornavwertdibolew; LnistferdomProMperaty: 2FT0S1E5ERtPoA/eNqAuRiEtIyT ldoewvelopfed. February 2016. Global Equity: MSCI World; High Yield Bonds: BofAML Original High Yield; Convertibles: BofA Merrill Lynch Global300 Convertible; Listed Property: FTSE ERPA/NAREIT developed.Percentage (%)]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[17Figure 2: Composition of the Investec Diversified Income Fund’s yield9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0DM Gov't BondsGrowthIG Corporate BondsEquitiesInfrastructureCurrent portfolio yieldHY Corporate BondsPropertyEM Sovereign DebtPortfolioDefensive UncorrelatedSource: Investec Asset Management as at 30.06.16.By considering how asset classes behave, ratherthan their labels, we group them together into three baskets: Growth Defensive an Uncorrelated. We believe a blend of these characteristics results in superior diversification, and therefore more consistent outcomes.The Investec Diversified income Fund aims to fill the role that income can no longer fill.A defensive multi-asset fund, it seeks to provide attractive income with long-term growth.• Attractive income - aims to provide 4-6% p.a.•• Sustainable income - global multi-asset portfolio seeking to grow capital• Lower volatility - historic volatility less than 50% of UK equities• Taxefficiency-classifiedasan‘interest-paying’fund• Activity managed - by co-Head of Multi-Asset Income John Stopford and team. *Gross of fees, over a 3-year rolling period. This is an aim and not guaranteed.from their positions. Secondly, it focuses attention on position conviction - investors have a broad opportunity set and should avoid inadvertently duplicating risks. In the Investec Diversified Income Fund we only hold developed market duration in areas in which we have high conviction, currently this includes the Antipodean and Canadian bond markets, which we believe to be attractively valued with positive domestic drivers.Diversifying sources of incomeAnother aspect of risk for a defensive strategy to consider is how concentrated its sources of income are and whether they are unintentionally exposed to similar sourcesof risk. A consequence of the hunt for yield, instigated by post-crisis monetary stimulus, has seen increasingly concentrated sources of yield and a shift towards higher-risk origins. To ensure a smoother and more sustainable flow of income, the Multi-Asset Income team look to diversify risk from a yield perspective also.In a number of asset classes, yields are very concentrated in a small numbers of sectors or issuers.Clearly investors are highly beholden to certain concentrated sectoral and regional factors for yield. Figure 2 shows the composition of the Investec Diversified Income Fund’s yield as shown in the righthand bar. This ensures yield diversification across both Growth/ Defensive/ Uncorrelated assets and by sources of risk within these. The result is a less concentrated income stream.For further information please visit www.investecassetmanagement.com/DIFTHIS COMMUNICATION IS DIRECTED ONLY AT PROFESSIONAL FINANCIAL ADVISORS. IT SHOULD NOT BE DISTRIBUTED TO, OR RELIED ON BY PRIVATE CUSTOMERS. Past performance shouldnot be taken as a guide to future returns. The value of investments can go down as well as up and your clients could end up with less than they invested. Your clients’ capital is at risk. Please note that equities rank in the lowest tier on the capital structure so, in the case of a company bankruptcy, bond holders would get paid before equity owners. Fund ratings may be provided by independentrating agencies based on a range of investment criteria and do not constitute investment advice by Investec Asset Management. English language copies of the Funds’ prospectuses, Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) and report and accounts are available from Investec Asset Management. The Fund may invest more than 35% of their assets in securities issued or guaranteed by an EEA state. The Funds are domiciled in the UK. The Fund Prospectus and Key Investor Information Documents (KIIDs) may be obtained from www. investecassetmanagement.com.Percentage (%)]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[18Politics, policy and perceptionsSusanne Grabinger | Investment Specialist | M&G Multi Asset TeamUsual uncertaintyThe old proverb, “May you live in interesting times,” might not sound the most worrisome of curses, but when 2016 kicked-off in what was frequently asserted to be a period of ‘unusual uncertainty’, it would have strucka chord with many investors. Amid what turned out to be another year of mediocre global economic growth and a persistently low return landscape, perhaps investors will best remember 2016 as a year dominated by divisive politics and pivoting policy.In the view of the M&G Multi Asset team, there is no such thing as ‘unusual’ uncertainty – every year is eventful. What matters is how events are interpreted by the market in the context of fundamental conditions. So when we look ahead to next year and beyond,it is not about predicting what events will dominate headlines, but about being ready to respond to the changing mood of the market. Most importantly, successfully analysing investor sentiment and market volatility means first establishing a sense of the broader, longer-term economic backdrop, and not being distracted by short-term ‘noise’.PoliticsThe two topics we were asked to comment on most frequently during 2016 were ‘Brexit’ and the US election. What made these events so important to investors was the apparent rise of populism – what people really wanted to know was whether the developed world was facing significant regime change of the type that dictates asset returns materially for long periods.Politics should matter to investors because equity returns are determined by the share of economic growth that goes to companies as profits. However, the types of changesin political and social structure which drive that take place over many years and in ways that are not obvious. They cannot easily be traced in financial ratios or even necessarily looking at the policies of governments. So instead, commentators generally focused on short-term forecasts, and specifically, that politics matters to investors because you get ‘increased uncertainty’ around elections and referendums.It is true that in running our portfolios,for the most part, we look for political worries to create opportunities – volatility is often in excess of the genuine impact on fundamentals. What is important, however,is the broader political regime: Pro-trade or protectionist? Where does the pendulum sit between capital and labour and what is the direction of travel? These are vital for the key variables in valuation: inflation and profitability. The reality is, in the immediate wake of a political event, most of this is not yet clear.In the run-up to the US election, the language of both candidates touched on the above, but history has shown us that political rhetoric is often not matched in reality. Only time will tell. In any case, President Obama’s tenure has shown that the ability of the US president to enact radical change is very limited.Similarly, six months on from the UK’s referendum on EU membership, the final shape Brexit will take is unknown, by anyone. The focus so far has largely been on sterling and the pass-through to inflation. It is difficult to discern how much of the sterling move in recent months is of a sustainable nature and how much is short-term or even speculative.In the case of any major political event, we are careful not to persuade ourselves we can know much about the long-term impact, but in the short-term, large price moves could mean opportunities.]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[19In the view of the M&G Multi Asset team, there isno such thing as ‘unusual’ uncertainty – every year is eventful. What matters is how events are interpreted by the market in the context of fundamental conditions.PolicySince 2008, investors have become obsessed with the words and actions of policymakers. 2016 has been no different, in fact, focuson policy seemed to intensify. We believe policymakers have reached a crossroads and there seems to be a shift under way in the global policy-making mindset away from monetary stimulus and towards fiscal support.Amid a general acknowledgement that the world’s major central banks are approaching the limit of accommodative measures such as quantitative easing and lower – even negative – interest rates, there is a growing recognition that these policies, once relevant, may now be counterproductive. To some extent, ultra-loose monetary policy has been successful in averting the worst possible outcomes from the financial crisis, but today, there are two important questions to ask: Are low rates actually causing households to save more? And do these policies pose a threat to financial sector profitability and stability?There is evidence that central banks have begun responding to demand for more innovative approaches, specifically in taking steps to make sure their actions directly influence the real economy. Measures such as TLTRO (targeted long-term refinancingoperations) in Europe, the Term Funding Scheme in the UK and tiered reserves in Japan show a concerted effort to increase inflation and challenge the rule of thumb of recent years that any weak growth will be greeted with lower rates and bond buying.We think the shift in the global policy stance could be very meaningful because of the potential impact this might have on the pricing of mainstream government bonds. Meanwhile, less consensus and coordination between global policymakers could prompt greater volatility in currency markets than we have been used to for much of the past 20 years.PerceptionsAs I have mentioned, what matters to usin finding investment opportunities and mitigating risks is analysing how investors perceive all this. Turbulent geopolitics combined with questions over the willingness and ability of policymakers to innovate beyond their traditional tools, has donelittle to calm the broad sense of ‘heightened uncertainty’ that has persisted since 2008.Market commentary and pricing still suggest deep-seated pessimism about global growth and a high level of volatility aversion. This could present compelling opportunitiesfor those with the stomach for short-term volatility in pursuit of attractive longer-term rewards.For financial advisers only. Not for onward distribution. No other persons should rely on any information contained within. This Financial Promotion is issued by M&G Securities Limited which is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority in the UK and provides investment products. The company’s registered office is Laurence Pountney Hill, London EC4R 0HH. Registered in England No. 90776.Less consensus and coordination between global policymakers could prompt greater volatility in currency markets than we have been used to for much of the past 20 years.]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[20The four pillars: The benefits of SimplicityJustin Onuekwusi CFA | Fund Manager | Legal & General Investment ManagementThis article discusses the benefits of ‘simplicity’ when it comes to the Multi-Index funds. In particular, it explains the advantages of using transparent index funds as the building blocks for our Multi- Index portfolios.ONGOING SUITABILITY• Actively targets risk profile• Long-term suitability, within the risk mandateACTIVE ASSET ALLOCATION• Flexibility to respond to market events• Seeks strong returns within the risk mandate of each portfolio• Takes a medium-term viewCOST EFFECTIVENESS SIMPLICITY• Low OCF from 0.31%• Mainly uses low-cost in-house index funds• Helping you to close the advice gap by serving clients at lower price points• Predominantly uses straightforward, in-house index funds• Avoids using complicated derivative strategiesSimplicity Is KeyWith so much jargon being used and such a variety of complex products on offer, it is no wonder that clients can feel bewildered by the options available to them when it comes to selecting the core, long-term components of their portfolios.The Legal & General Multi-Index Funds try to keep things simple. We do this by building our funds predominantly using underlying index funds that are straightforward,transparent and easy to understand. This can be beneficial for you and your clients.Index Funds Offer TransparencyOne of the key advantages of index funds is that they are transparent, which means investors can see what underlying stocks or bonds the funds own. This ‘look-through’ is important because it allows our portfolio managers to fully understand the risks and exposures that exist within the Multi-Index Funds at any given time. This, in turn,gives the team a better understanding of how unfolding market events may affect the portfolios and allows them to make adjustments accordingly.With some active funds investors do not get this level of transparency because they only publish their holdings on a monthly basis, making it more difficult for clients to understand how they are positioned and where their portfolios may be vulnerable.]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[21Whilst we make considerable use of straightforward index funds, we are not passive for the sake of it.We don’t take positions using complex derivativesWhile lots of funds execute their strategies using complex derivatives – investment products which derive their value from that of an underlying asset at a forward-looking time – we take a more straightforward approach so that there are no nasty surprises.We minimise the use of derivatives, predominantly using index funds to access market risk. Derivatives can often involve additional layers of risk which are not evident at first, such as counterparty risk, whereone of the parties defaults on the derivative contract, and liquidity risk, where the cost of closing a position can be prohibitively high if lots of investors want to sell their investment at the same time.In the Multi-Index Funds, we make very limited use of derivatives and only use them in order to manage the portfolios more efficiently, such as managing short-term risk or cashflows. Avoiding significant exposure to these additional risks and complexities makes the funds more appropriate as core long-term holdings for your clients’ portfolios.Whilst we make considerable use of straightforward index funds, we are not passive for the sake of it. Alongside ourindex holdings, we also hold some actively managed funds in areas where we feel these exposures can be managed more effectively, such as global corporate bonds, global high yield bonds and direct property investments.An added benefit is that the lower costs associated with the underlying index funds also make the Multi-Index Funds more cost- effective, helping you to close the advice gap by serving clients at a lower price point.With so much jargon being used and such a variety of complex products on offer, it is no wonder that clients can feel bewildered by the options available to them.Leveraging Legal & General Investment Management’s (LGIM’s) Index Scale And ExpertiseThe Multi-Index Funds make full use of LGIM’s wider capabilities in index investment, predominantly utilising internal funds.With over £300bn in index assets, as at30 June 2016, LGIM is the largest managerof index funds in the UK, and this comes with considerable advantages. LGIM usesits scale to make index fund management more efficient, reducing tracking error and transaction costs.Important NoticeThis is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons.The views expressed within this document are those of Legal & General Investment Management, who may or may not have acted upon them. Legal & General Investment Management is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.Issued by Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. This document should not be taken as an invitation to deal in Legal & General investments or any of the stated investments. Remember, the value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise and investors may get back less than they invest. Multi-Index Funds are sensitive to interest rate changes. An increase in medium to long-term interest rates is likely to reduce the value of an investment in these funds. Details of the specific and general risks associated with the funds mentioned are contained within the Key Investor Information document for each fund. *Call charges will vary.Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Q0054952. 10/16. H0160433.Contact detailsContact us for more information T: 0345 070 8684*E: fundsales@lgim.com W: lgim.com]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[22Why that fund for that client?Davinia Rogers | Head of Sales and Marketing | Verbatim Asset ManagementIt is surprising how often you meet fundamentalists in financial services when discussing portfolio construction. For every apostle of funds there is a pilgrim for model portfolios, a disciple of DFMs or a sect for advisers’ own fund selection.Yet surely none of these broad churches is inherently right or wrong? There are some key questions that the fundamentalists who focus on just one primary solution should always ask:1. How does this solution match the journey of risk I have agreed with my client?It is quite clear that ongoing suitability of investment selection is one of their main areas of focus for the regulator. However, aside from compliance there are real commercial and client benefits to a robust risk profiling process. Quantifying and qualifying riskwith a client not only allows you to set their expectations of how much they could gain but also how much they could lose, framing future conversations around performance, regardless of market gains or losses. If you cannot clearly communicate to your client why and how the funds or portfolio you have selected will deliver within the parameters of their expected risk journey, you should not be using that solution. The same holds true for overall asset allocation.2. What’s your documented approach to investment solution research?Can you articulate how and why you arrived at using that particular fund or portfolio, rather than a host of other similar funds that could have done the same? Do you knowall the moving parts of that fund? Can the manager buy what he or she likes within the fund or are they constrained by a mandate, and indeed do they stick to that mandate? The question really should be not why you chose that fund, but why didn’t you choose all the others that are similar.Furthermore, a quick read of TR16/01 will prompt you to question whether your client is front and centre in your research and due diligence process. Can you articulate what the benefits are for your client as opposed to a benefit for the advisory business of using a particular solution?3. How will you cost-effectively administer the portfolio?This might be done on a platform, a stand- alone tax wrapper or even directly with the fund manager, but certain key tasks need to be undertaken. Rebalancing in line with the risk journey is one thing, but how will you do what used to be called 'switching' butis now really just advice – every time you recommend a switch you recommend a client sells an asset, turns it into cash and buys another and this needs full disclosure and client agreement.TR15/12 highlighted the gap betweenthe regulator’s expectations of portfolio suitability and the reality of many discretionary and advisory portfolios.The challenge is to ensure that portfolio drift does not impact upon suitability, whilst portfolio drag (the cost of delaying implementation of investment decisions) does not hinder advisor implemented portfolios compared to the more agile fund of funds or discretionary model portfolio.]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[23The successful advisory firm now has a supply chain of solutions they can use which will meet their clients’ expectations and allow the adviser to focus on delivering financial plans that meet their clients’ goals.4. Who provides governance and review?Who is in charge of documenting your process, reviewing its suitability and ensuring that your firm sticks to this process? Sole practitioners may need outside assistance with this, whereas multi RI firms will need consistency across advisers. Furthermore,do you have the time and expertise to really scrutinise the inner workings of a fund or portfolio to ensure you fully understand all of the potential options open to that manager and their performance against mandate?What good looks likeIf you start with the whole of the relevant market, use enhanced suitability questions to filter out unsuitable solutions, quantify risk and assess capacity for loss and then have a clear and documented investment philosophy that states why you use the solutions you currently use, then youwill have a clear and credible process to share with clients, staff and the regulator. What’s more, you will be able to answer comprehensively why that client holds that fund, regardless of which broad church of solutions you have put your faith in.However, you have to have your team of suppliers lined up to provide solutions for you. That doesn’t mean picking up on best ideas from around the industry. It means knowing what your service and process is and then pro-actively seeking manufacturers who can deliver within your requirements.The successful advisory firm now has a supply chain of solutions they can use which will meet their clients’ expectationsand allow the adviser to focus on delivering financial plans that meet their clients’ goals.At Verbatim we believe our job is to provide solutions that do exactly what they say on the tin for advisers and their clients. That’s why we provide:• FP Verbatim Portfolio Funds – multi- asset, risk managed, active funds with over 6 years’ strong track record of delivering performance.• Total Clarity Funds – multi-asset, risk managed funds using passive instruments.• Verbatim Discretionary Service – putting you in control of your own risk managed discretionary service, with 5 leading portfolio managers working for you within your advice process.• Verbatim Model Portfolio Service – risk managed model portfolios, implemented for you on leading retail platforms.• IndependentInvestmentCommittee– a team of industry experts overseeing the funds and portfolios, making sure the investment managers are delivering to the set mandate.One of the best ways to assess whether a solution should make it into your supply chain is to look at what the fund or portfolio promised to deliver for clients and how well it delivered against that mandate. Here you can see the performance of the FP Verbatim 3 fund charted against the worst, best and average expected return of the risk profile the fund is aligned to (dynamic planner risk profile 3). If an adviser had set their client’s expectations by pointing out that in this risk profile their money could be expected to rise or fall between these boundaries, then this fund delivered as expected. And it is on that basis of setting and meeting expectations against a set of clear, quantifiable intended outcomes that advisers should pull solutions into their supply chain.]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[24Brainless Portfolio:The natural benchmark for multi-asset fundsAbraham Okusanya | Principal | FinalytiQThe overwhelming conclusion of The Great Guide to Risk-Rated Multi-Asset Funds is that most multi-asset managers have no asset allocation, manager selection or risk management expertise worth paying for. Judged against simple low-cost equity-bond portfolios constructed by a novice investor (dubbed ‘Brainless Portfolios’), most multi-asset funds systematically damaged returns on a risk-adjusted basis and reduce the chances of an investor meeting their return objectives.For our analysis, we created 5 ‘Brainless Benchmark Portfolios’ made up of percentage allocation to two asset classes – global equities and global bonds – as shown in the chart below;The Brainless Portfolios have an annual fee of 0.50% p.a. and are rebalanced once a year on the 1st of January. The Brainless Portfoliois a passive portfolio in its purest form that allocates to market cap-weighted global equities and bonds, depending on the degree of risk an investor is prepared to stomach.In other words, they would take whatever return the market gives them, rather than trying to make active predictions about which assets will perform better than others.The ‘Brainless Portfolios’ depict the baseline return investors should expect for investing in a risk-based portfolio because it doesn’t require any asset allocation or manager selection expertise. The only asset allocation decision our ‘Brainless Benchmark Portfolios’ require is what proportion of their portfolio should be invested in global equities and global bonds. They simply rebalance once a year on January 1st.And that’s it.No tactical decisions. No allocation to property, commodities, alternatives or any other fancy stuff.The question we aimed to answer is, how do portfolios constructed by expert fund managers, asset allocators and Masters of the Universe compare with our brainless portfolios?“Brainless” Benchmark Portfolios]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[255 Year Scatter Chart for Risk Rated Multi- Asset FundsVolatility (%)10 Year Scatter Chart for Risk Rated Multi- Asset FundsVolatility (%)Well, here’s how...has been covered extensively in academic and practitioner research, notably by Ronald Doeswijk et al in his paper titled The Global Multi-Asset Market Portfolio, Meb Faber in his posts and book titled Global Asset Allocation and by Cullen Roche who noted in recent article that;“The global multi-asset market portfolio contains important information for strategic asset-allocation purposes. First, it shows the relative value of all asset classes according to the global financial investment community, which one could interpret as a natural benchmark for financial investors. Second, this portfolio may also serve as the starting point for investors who use a framework in the spirit of Black and Litterman (1992), or for investors who follow adaptive asset-allocation policies as advocated by Sharpe (2010).”— Ronald Doeswijk et al, The Global Multi- Asset Market Portfolio“If there was such a thing as an indexing purist that person would simply buy all of the outstanding available financial assets in the world and call it quits. In other words, they would take what the market gives them rather than trying to make active predictions about which parts of the financial asset world will perform better than other parts.”— Cullen Roche, Is the Global Financial Asset Portfolio the Perfect Indexing Strategy?The Brainless Portfolio is neutral; it’s how a novice investor should approach investing. Without any asset allocation expertise, a starting point should be to allocate their capital based on aggregate global market, and so it’s a perfect benchmark for multi- asset funds.The Curse of Home BiasThis brings me to the next point. A few people criticise the Brainless Portfolio because ‘most multi-asset funds would have more allocation to UK equities.’This misses the point. Deviating from the cap- weighted global equity allocation presumes that you know better than the aggregateof investors across the world. UK multi-asset fund managers exhibit home bias by allocating more to UK equities, presumably because they have carried out thorough analysis about how best to allocate investors’ capital. And they know better than the markets. They can choose any asset class they want – commercial property, commodities, whatever. This is where their expertise lies; since the proof of the pudding is in the eating, this should result in higher risk- adjusted returns. Except it doesn’t.To Hedge or Not to Hedge a Global PortfolioAnother criticism of the Brainless Portfolio is that it hedges currency back to Sterling. The rationale is that, as a UK investor, you presumably earn and spend in Sterling. And so, while you are keen to benefit from the returns and opportunities offered by the aggregate publicly traded financial assets across the world, you are not prepared as a novice investor to take currency risks.So it makes perfect sense to me that a novice investor, using the Brainless Portfolio, would take currency risk off the table by hedging back to their local currency. If not entirely, some of it. This is why many global bond funds offer a GBP hedged share class.UK multi-asset managers are ‘experts’ and they make an informed decision to take currency risk. This adds another tool to their armoury, and since the additional currency risk should be rewarded, this is yet another reason why multi-asset funds should outperform the Brainless Portfolios. Except that, they don’t.In summary, given we are all living longer, we are having to save for retirement and most face prospects of having to spend less in retirement, the least asset manager can do is to earn their crust!These scatter charts plot the cumulative return against the risk (volatility) of multi- asset funds. Each dot on the chart represents a fund. A polynomial trendline shows the risk-return relationship between all the funds in the same fund range. Each trendline on the graph represents an entire fund range, which consists of all the individual funds that make up the range. We refer to this trendline as the ‘Efficient Frontier’ for each fund range.Fund ranges that lie below the ‘Brainless Benchmark Portfolio’ trendlines are sub- optimal because they do not adequately compensate clients for the level of risk associated with the fund. Portfoliosthat cluster to the right of the ‘Brainless Benchmark Portfolio’ trendline are also sub-optimal, because they take higher levels of risk for the level of return they deliver i.e. clients are taking more risks to get less return.The Empirical Foundation for Brainless PortfoliosThe Brainless Portfolio is based on the concept of The Global Multi-Asset Portfolio (GMAP or Global Financial Asset Portfolio) which represents how the markets across the world allocate capital across publicly traded financial assets. The concept of GMAPCommulative Return (%) Commulative Return (%)]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[26A steady outlook but watch out for the banana skinsAlex Scott | Deputy Chief Investment Officer | Seven Investment ManagementInvestors’ attention has been dominated by political risk recently. This is no surprise given the slew of headlines from the 8 November US Election. The results may still be dominating newspaper inches even as you read this, especially since it was not a binary choice akin to Brexit. Americans voted in the 45th US President, but also chose 435 candidates to sit in the House of Representatives (a.k.a. Congress) and selected 34 Senators. The possible permutations of Democratic or Republican President, Congress and Senate all have different implications for capital markets.Closer to home, European political risk is a little lower down the agenda, but the Italian constitutional referendum in December may present a banana skin. Then add in elections in France, Germany and the Netherlandsin 2017 against a climate of populism, anti-immigration and anti-globalisation rhetoric, all of which are starting to weigh on investors’ minds.Of course, huge uncertainty still hangsover the outlook for the UK and its future relationship with Europe: an inflexible stance by the UK government on controlling European Union (EU) migration is colliding head-on with an uncompromising position by the EU on its four basic freedoms. These tie membership of the single market to thefreedom of movement of goods, capital, services and people. Unless either party can give ground, and it is hard to see politically how they can, this suggests that a favourable trade deal for the UK will be hard to negotiate. It’s dawned on markets that Brexit probably means a hard Brexit, with negative implications for trade, investment and productivity for the UK economy, and with the Pound as the key battleground.We shouldn’t expect hard economic data to show much impact yet, but we’ll start to see more effects in the months to come – not only through imported inflation, where high profile stories are already grabbing attention, but also in cancelled or deferred capital investment decisions. This may not cometo a single dramatic defining moment, but suggests a drip-feed of disappointment, where economists are gradually reducing their long term expected growth trajectory for the UK, and where the government has to respond to a lower expected tax base as a result.It’s dawned on markets that Brexit probably means a hard Brexit, with negative implications for trade, investment and productivity for the UK economy, and with the Pound as the key battleground.]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[27We should indeed expect reasonable earnings growth for 2017, as headwinds from the energy sector’s pain fade away.Elsewhere, we see little to challenge our expectations of a subdued but steadygrowth outlook. European economic datahas surprised a little to the upside recently, offsetting slightly underwhelming US data, but the broad pattern holds good: labour markets in the US and Europe are strong enough to support the consumer, the key driver of these economies. And China’s policy interventions have again stabilised growth drivers there enough to prevent a hard landing. However animal spirits are not strong enough to fuel a significant acceleration in growth, corporates are generally still very cautious about investment plans and, while governments have generally pulled backfrom recent austerity drives, few have either the will or the fiscal wriggle-room for major stimulus. While infrastructure spending plans may bear fruit in the long run, time takento plan new projects and overcome local objections suggests we shouldn’t hope for much real world impact in the near term.While there may seem to be a narrower range of likely outcomes for the global economy – fading a bit, brightening a little, but neither racing to escape velocity nor falling off a cliff – the range of possible actions by policymakers seems wider and has profound implications for markets. Markets seem, for now, to be taking in their stride the possibility of another rate hike by the US Federal Reserve in December, assuming there is no meaningful weakeningof the economic data before then. Indeed, there are some who would strongly welcome it, both as a signal that the US economy is a step further on the road back to normality, and as a move to rebuild policy flexibilityfor the next downturn, hiking rates now so that they can be cut later. But perceptions can change, and it would not take much for a hike to be perceived as a policy misstep, tightening policy for an economy that needs ongoing support.The policy debate in Europe and Japan is a little different. With interest rates below zero and asset purchases – Quantitative Easing (QE) – continuing to expand central bank balance sheets, the tone has shifted. Is QE now the problem, with low bond yields crushing banks’ profitability, undermining corporate pension schemes and forcing households to save ever more to meet their long term goals? Or is it the solution, on a still grander scale, covering more assets and culminating in the central bank cancelling government debt? Is it even necessary, in Europe at least, given that GDP growth of the 1.5-2% we are now seeing is probably as good as it gets for a demographically- challenged continent? And, if it’s notthe solution, what is? Central bankers’ statements and investors’ interpretations of those statements look likely to be a bigger factor than economic surprises in driving markets. Yet, despite elevated political risksand uncertainty around monetary policy, stockmarkets have traded up to their highs for this cycle, with valuations looking increasingly demanding. Not high enough to preclude further progress – momentum and sentiment can be powerful forces – but high enough to already factor in the fairly decent earnings growth. We should indeed expect reasonable earnings growth for 2017, as headwindsfrom the energy sector’s pain fade away. But it’s hard to see where substantial positive surprises can come from. This pushes our focus more towards riskier corporate debt – pricing is still reasonable and the economic outlook is resilient enough to suggest that corporate defaults should be lower than priced in by current credit spreads. And, if we are wrong, debt should significantly outperform equity in a downside scenario.Seven Investment Management LLP is authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. Member of the London Stock Exchange. Registered office: 55 Bishopsgate, London EC2N 3AS. Registered in England and Wales No. OC378740.Contact detailsFor further information about Seven Investment ManagementT: 020 7760 8777 W: www.7im.co.uk]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[28Currency risk – a real and present danger to advisers & clientsBen Raven | Director | Tavistock WealthThe impact of currency risk on client portfolios could become the next big scandal in UK financial services.The past twenty years have seen a fundamental shift from financial advisers recommending UK-centric portfolios toa globally diversified approach, both in terms of asset classes and markets. This has arisen because of the desire for well diversified investment solutions, together with the introduction of a vast array of global investment options, particularly in the passive space.Whilst broadly desirable, the global diversification trend has also resulted in a significantly increased exposure to currency risk. Unfortunately, this exposure is often missed or misunderstood by financial advisers.Too many people seem to mistakenly believe that if you invest in a foreign index via a sterling (GBP) share class, you are somehow protected from any currency exposure. This is simply not the case. If you invest in GBP, but hold an investment that is denominated in USD or JPY such as an S&P or Nikkei tracker, you are not only exposed to the equity market, but also to the GBP/ USD or GBP/JPY currency pair.Various articles have been written recently on the impact of currency markets oninvestment portfolios. These articles stimulate debate over the most efficient way to run an investment mandate, but there tends to be little, if any, consideration of the impact on an IFA, their clients and therefore their business.have been derived from currency moves, rather than from the asset allocations and investment strategy that IFAs discuss with their clients. This significant contribution has come during a period of sustained GBP weakness against a number of currencies, particularly the USD.In this scenario, a client’s overseas exposure has been increasing in value whilst theGBP has fallen. They have therefore seen their portfolios perform well, with that performance ‘boosted’ by currency market gains; so far so good.However, currency markets like any other markets, move in both directions. This is where the serious risk lies for advisers and clients.Consider a straightforward illustration where a client is advised to invest £100,000 in an S&P 500 ETF today. The advice is based on the historical volatility of the index being consistent with the client’s agreed risk appetite. In a year’s time, the underlying S&P 500 index has risen by 5%. However, the GBP has appreciated 10% against the USD (returning to the level last seen just before the Brexit referendum).Currency markets like any other markets, move in both directions. This is where the serious risk lies for advisers and clients.How are advisers fulfilling their responsibility to ensure that clients are fully aware of the additional currency risk they are exposed to? Do they understand what proportion of their clients’ returns has resulted from currency market moves over the past 10 years?Our analysis indicates that up to half of portfolio returns over the last decade]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[29The past twenty years have seen a fundamental shift from financial advisers recommending UK-centric portfolios to a globally diversified approach.This means that despite the underlying S&P index having returned +5%, the appreciation of GBP has resulted in the client’s investment (which is denominated in GBP) being worth a little over £95,400.Where does the liability lie in this scenario? The ETF has performed exactly as it should – reflecting the returns of the index coupled with any movements in the currency pair. The adviser however, recommended an investment positioned as providing the client with the returns of the S&P 500 whilst exposing them to a level of volatility (risk) supposedly equal to that exhibitedby the S&P 500. In fact, the client received neither, and the responsibility lies firmly at the door of the adviser.In this example, the client would see the underlying equity investment make a gain, yet they would lose money because of the currency market they were exposed to. The fact that the client invests in GBP, but holds an investment that is denominated in USD, shows that they are not being exposed to the US equity market alone, but also to the GBP/USD currency pair.More concerning is if the client was told they were taking a level of risk equal to the S&P 500, but were actually being exposed to the volatility of both the S&P 500 and the GBP/USD currency pair. It isthe adviser’s responsibility to understand and sufficiently explain all types of riskto a client prior to recommending an investment. In this instance, a client would have legitimate cause for complaint and compensation, and the adviser might face regulatory sanction.Over the last decade, UK clients have generally benefitted from the GBP falling, but even they could complain (were they so minded) about exposure to a type and level of risk they were unaware of. Whilst the average retail client will not have a 100% currency exposure as per our illustration, they will probably have a significant proportion of their portfolio invested in countries and markets outside the UK. They may also be subjected to more volatile currency pairs than the GBP/USD.The FCA is demanding that portfolios“truly reflect the investment need and risk appetite of customers”. Having evolved into the era of global diversification however, we are seeing portfolios enormously impacted by a high risk asset class that the average retail client is unaware of. Clients may be exposed to a type and level of risk that is not sufficiently discussed, that they didnot sign up for and which is highly likely to result in a level of portfolio volatility that is misaligned with their agreed risk profile.The question for advisers therefore is not whether “to hedge or not to hedge” asthis relates to a fund manager’s approachto managing money. The question forthe IFA community is “how can I ensurethe portfolios I recommend to my clients accurately reflect their investment need and risk appetite at all times?” In answering this question, the hedging of overseas currency exposure is an important consideration.Some fund managers may argue that currency fluctuations even themselves out over time. This however, is no consolation for a retail investor who has been exposed to a risk they were unaware of, nor is it any form of defence for an IFA whose role isto identify suitable investment solutions for their clients. A suitable investment solution is one that performs in line with expectations. It subjects clients to the level of risk that they have agreed to take and does so in their best interests on an on- going basis.Most advisers would readily agree that direct investment in a currency fund would be inappropriate for the vast majority of retail clients. However, recommending globally diversified portfolios with a significant amount of overseas, unhedged currency exposure appears to be a regular occurrence.]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[After 21 years we still hold the key to complianceSYNAPTIC PRODUCT & FUND SOFTWARE• Providing independent and objective whole of market research. • Helping advisers navigate the challenges of compliance.• The cornerstone of compliance advice in the UK.• Integrates fully with the entire Synaptic Research Suite.For more information call us on 0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.uk]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[31‘Feeling the Squeeze’, Royal London asks advisers their viewsFiona Tait | Pension Specialist | Royal LondonSavings Moments of TruthRoyal London carried out aUK wide survey with 2,500 consumers age 35-44 over the summer.The survey found that over a third, 34% said their finances felt Squeezed and so were struggling to meet day to day expenses, despite 87% being aware that they need to save more.However, the survey did also identify positive Savings Moments of Truth (MOTs) when some financial commitments such as car finance or nursery costs come to an end which could free up money to save for retirement.To support the research with consumers we also wanted to find out what our advisers thought. Nearly half of the advisers surveyed said clients who class themselves as Squeezed (that is where keeping up with bills and repayments is a constant struggle) are engaging with their retirement savings but are struggling to save more. 150 advisers responded to our poll which concluded:• 75% of advisers with clients age 35-44 said they were slightly engaged with saving for retirement.• 57% said that any extra money available to clients would be used to reduce debt or ease financial pressure rather than save into a pension.• Only 17% believed that those who felt Squeezed would use extra cash to boost pension savings.Commenting, Fiona Tait, Pensions Specialist at Royal London, said:“While our findings show that many peopleare ‘Feeling the Squeeze’, it is good news that advisers think their clients are engaged with saving for retirement. Even if people can’t afford to save more now, it is possible to create a definite plan of action to save more in the future when their income increases or outgoings are reduced.”Encouragingly, the wider research showed that those who had spoken to an adviser valued their advice, with 87% of 35-44 year olds sayingthat they would be likely to do so again in the future. Of those who had used an adviser, 45% reviewed their finances with an adviser at least once a year.Identifying your client’s Savings MOTs could help encourage them to redirect freed up finances into their retirement savings.For example, those with a mortgage to be paid off within the next 15-20 years could contribute 5 years of payments which on average are £500-£599 per month into their pension, securing a potential boost to their pension pot of over £20,000.*Fiona Tait continued: “Nearly half, (45%)of 35-44 year olds surveyed, said that afterfirst speaking to an adviser about their pension options they are now reviewing their finances with an adviser at least once a year. These reviews are a great opportunity to reassess a client’s current pension savings and set in place those Savings MOTs to potentially boost their future income in retirement over the long term.”Read more detail on the Royal London’s Feeling the Squeeze research and the Savings MOTs or speak to your usual Royal London contact.Notes:The findings of Pensions Through the Ages: Feeling the Squeeze, are based on in-depth quantitative analysis of 2,418 people aged 35 to 44 across the UK using a bespoke survey panel conducted by HarrisInteractive UK from May 26th – June 9th 2016. The statistics for this release is based on 203 individuals who said that they had spoken to an adviser at least once when reviewing or taking out pension products.The adviser online poll was conducted by Royal London Intermediary marketing team from Thursday 16 June to Monday 20 June 2016 and is based on responses from 155 advisers.*Saving £250 into a pension once mortgage payments are finished, until a retirement age of 65, could deliver £21,200 of pension savings.This is a Royal London promotion.]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[32SYNAPTICNo longer is retirementthe finishing line...Pete Bayliss | Product Director | Synaptic Software LimitedIt is now another exciting chapter in life!We are living longer, our children will leave home (at some stage allegedly!) and our parents just never age – and here we are in the middle!!The government are planning to launch a pilot pension dashboard service next spring, which will give us all an insight into the pension schemes and plans that we have accumulated during our careers. I have no doubt this willbe a really popular and useful service, but at Synaptic we have been looking at ways to supplement and improve the service for your customers.Since the chancellor announced the changes to pensions freedom nearly two years ago, we have seen:• Anincreaseindrawdownbusiness• Areductioninannuitybusiness• AsubstantialincreaseintakingcashIn terms of customer behaviour however we have seen:• Consumersstartingtobecomemore engaged in their retirement income decisions at a much earlier age• Consumerswantinginformationtomake informed decisions• Consumersplanningaheadandwanting to model their income requirements and investment portfolios• Consumersneedinghelp/adviceand guidanceAnd what has the ‘market’ done?:• Defined benefit schemes offering what appears to be generous CETVs• Providers reducing their drawdown minimum investment amount• Government building the pension dashboard service• Treasury launched the Treasury Pension Dashboard (Finder) Project• The Pension Advisory Service has been increased in size to handle consumer callsAnd in the real world, what are 50 ‘somethings’ asking?• What pensions have I got?• What is the value? Income and transfer?• What options have I got?• When can I do it?• How much income do I need in retirementor phased retirement?• Whatarethechancesoftherebeingenoughmoney left?• Whataretherisksoftransferring?• WhataretherisksofstayingwhereIam?• Whatisinflationgoingtodo?• Whatismyattitudetorisk?• WhatvehiclescouldIinvestin?• WhatformatcouldItakemymoneyoutin?At Synaptic we are keen to work with our customers, trade bodies and the Treasury in building B2C solutions to:• White label and identify the existing pension data of the client• Help the client to identify their capital and income aims and requirements• Understand their risk profile • Compare potential products • Model their portfolioWe have built a prototype that we would love to demonstrate, please contact Sales on 0800 783 4477 or email sales@synaptic.co.ukThe government is planning to launch a pilot pension dashboard service next spring, which will give us all an insight into the pension schemes and plans that we have accumulated during our careers.]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[d/work -time234£2.9bn has been paid out as incomeThe average pot being used to> 80% of all newCASH WITHDRAWALSSource: Towers Watson Q2 2016CASH WITHDRAWALSGUARNANTUEIETDIEDSRAWQD3 O20W15Ns(aGwDt)he first ANNUITIES Q3 2015 saw the firstIn the first full year of pension freedoms:RETIREMENT SET INCOME FOR BASIC NEEDSRetire Late2012 to SION (E.G. but volumes droppedwas paidThe averagewas paid The average REGULAR INCOMEincrease in annuityout in cashpayment was80% drop inPensinicorneawserainppanenrusityRETIREMENT out in cash payment was80% drop insales since Q3 2013,£2.9bn has been paid out as incomevolumes from Q3 sales since Q3 2013, DISCRETIONARY NON-PnEoN-w account forlump sumsvolumes from Q3lump sumsbut volumes droppedatTNhReDaveragreetirpeomtenbteing used to2012 to > 80% of all newaccess regular income is £60,000ISA) again in Q4 2015 and LUXURIES Q3 2015. again in Q4 2015 andSource: ABIdecreased from £1.4bn inQ1 2016123now account forThe average pot being used to access regular income is £60,000>SOM8E0% of all newPASSIVESource: ABI DRAGWDOWsNales in the UK WARMING UP: SOME KEY STATS ON WHUAKTp’rSovGidOerIsNG DOWNaccess regular income is £60,000DEFINED STATEGD sales in the UKSource: ABI BENEFITWORK AND SAVE UK proPvEidNeSIrOsNSource: Towers Watson Q2 2016Lump sum withdrawals have Q3 2015. . Lump sum withdrawals have UK providers Q1 2016decreased from £1.4bn in Source: Towers Watson Q2 2016Q2 2015 to £750m in Q1 2016Source: ABICASH WITHDRAWALSSTATEQ2 2015 to £750m in Q1 2016PENSIONIN THE FIRST TWNAEKLEVDE- MONTHS OF PENSION IN THE FIRST TWELVE MONTHS OF PENSIONANNUITY DEFINEDCash lump sums remain populaIrNCwOMitEh the ANNUITIES Q3 2015 saw the firstCash lump sums remain popular with the FREEDOMS, FLEXIBLE PAYMENTS FROMwas paid The avGUeArRaANgTeEE under 60s, accounting for half theFREBEDNEOFMITS, FLEXIBLE PAYMENTS FROM PENSIONS TOTALinLEcDrease in annuityunder 60s, accounting for half the80%PdErNoSpIOiNnS TOTALLEDESSENTIALS sales since Q3 2013,out in cash payment was value of cash taken in Q1 2016£4.35bnvalue of cash taken in Q1 2016volumes from Q3Source: ABI£4.35bnGD sales in the UKDRAWDOWNQ2 2015Q2 2015Q4 2015Q44 22001155Q3 2015QQ22 22001166Q3 2015Q2 2016QQ11 22001166Q1 2016e asPENSIONS HADve in 16eQ3 2015.Q1 2016ADVICE lump sums A RANGE OF INCOME SOURCE FOR VARIOUS AND CHANGING NEEDSGuidance Source: ABISource: ABI but volumes dropped/Pension Wise DIY2 Cash lunder 60s, accounting for half thevalue of cash taken in Q1 2016Source: ABIGUARANTEED DRAWDOWN (GD)Q3 2015.Source: ABIIN THE FIRST TWELVE MONTHS OF PENSIONUK providersSource: HMRCSource: Towers Watson Q2 2016FLEXIBLELump sum withdrawals have decreased from £1.4bn inQ1 2016Q2 2015 to £750m in Q1 2016IN 516,0003ump sums remain popular with theIN 516,000ACTIVEASSISTEDPension wrappersnow account for> 80% of all newGD sales in the UKPENSIONSANNUITIES Q3 2015 saw the firstRECENT WHITE PAPER: DOWNLOAD FOR FREE AT:80% drop in increase in annuity SLOWED BUTHOW TO GET YOURSource: HMRCMONEY BACKSource: ABIsales since Q3 2013,www.langcatfinancial.co.ukvolumes from Q3 but volumes dropped 2012 to again in Q4 2015 andINCREASED£12.9k £9.0k £6.5k £5.8k £6.9kIN THE FIRST TWELVE MONTHS OF PENSION FREEDOMS, FLEXIBLE PAYMENTS FROMTHE UK WITHDRAWALPRODUCT LANDSCAPEPENSIONS TOTALLED£4.35bnA MARKET ANALYSIS REPORT FROMTO 232,000 INDIVIDUALSIN 516,0002012 toTHREE STAGES OF RETIREMENTaTgOai2n3i2n,0Q0402IN0D15IVaIDnUdALS TO 232,000 INDIVIDUALSPAYMENTS FREESDouOrcMe:SH,MFRLCEXIBLE PAYMENTS FROMPASSIVE Source: HMRC PENSIONS TOTALLED516,000TO 232,000 INDIVIDUALSIN 516,000KEYSTATS PROVIDED BY THE LANG CAT AS PART OF THEIR EXCELLENTAVERAGE £4.35bn FLEXIBLEPAYMENTSFROMHADSLOWEDBUTPAYMENTSINCREASED Source: HMRC£1521..96k,00££099.0.0kk ££66.5.5kk ££55.8.8kk £6.9k £6.9kIN Q2 2016 Source: HMRCAVERAGEPAYMENTSFROMIN Q2 2016516,000]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[34SYNAPTICPlatform centricEllen Ashcroft ACII | Head of Research | Synaptic Software LimitedAllegiance to a platform can come at the cost of the client, because ‘in some cases, firms no longer adequately review the options available to the client because the firm was happy with the service from the providers they were using.’ (FCA TR16/1)In some ways, the main narrative for our industry has tried to get away from a discussion about platforms, the dominant theme for several years. Except, the core principal of Treating Customers Fairly has re- emerged in the recent thematic review paper TR16/1, which highlights a specific concern relating to platform due diligence. ‘You must consider the suitability of the platform service itself’ says the paper, because platform choice can be frequently made, in the opinion of the FCA, for the benefit of the adviser at the cost of the client.Rory Percival, the closest thing to a regulatory rock star, and who has helped countless organisations achieve a constructive perspective on their due diligence, recently left the FCA and mused on the attitude of many practice managers towards platforms: “I was heavily involved in platforms from the start.Platform due diligence is a good demonstration of the ethics bit not working’’.Our experience as a provider of due diligence tools bears this out. We know that some firms do not wish to examine their preferred platforms in detail, particularly from a cost point of view, as they are more than happy. The real hazard exists in that they are over reliant on their platform’s tools, investment risk management and reporting and have ceased to make any meaningful external comparisons.The issue under discussion today is the broader role of platforms and how the landscape is changing. AUM held on the main platforms has exploded over recent years representing 35% of £1.1 trillion of retail investment (2015 IA figures). Platforms are indispensable to advisers at the current time, providing effective custody and management of clients investments. Platforms facilitate adviser charging.We should though, be cognisant of change and its implications. Some relevant insight has been provided by a couple of the industry’s respected commentators:The Lang Cat, led by Mark Polson, have provided some interesting analysis indicating that ‘over half’ of platform assets are ‘under transition’, due to mergers, sales and technological re- platforming. That’s £207 billion out of £386 billion. That is too significant not to have an impact, though that is not to say that we will return to the old days of dire interruption of service. It is the scale of change that poses a risk;Consultancy FinalytiQ have done some interesting number crunching around profitability. This aims to quantify the seemingly eye-watering investment that has gone into the insurers’ platforms. Standard Life, Axa Wealth Elevateand Zurich reported £50m in pre-tax losses – accumulating nearly £500m in losses since inception (2014 figures). This proves, if nothing else that there is more to platforms than meets the eye! Profitability, argues FinalytiQ,is important if growth, service and technological development are to be sustainable.Many research reports that are circulating are indicating that all customer groups will continue to value advice, including for example millennials (and their love of self service and technology).]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC35A typical client may be looking at an investment horizon of decades, including over 30 years of retirement in the post pension freedom world. Disruption, if not correctly anticipated and managed, could be devastating to a firm that are overly reliant on a single platform and a ‘homogenous’ client base.Good news is reflected in the many research reports that are circulating, indicating that all customer groups will continue to value advice, including for example millennials (and their love of self service and technology). What is not so clear is how platforms will evolve to maintain their role as custodians. Either way, it is worth improving platform due diligence to keep abreast of things, and your options open.Should advisers consider case by case cost due diligence?Synaptic launched the Comparator tool several years ago to help advisers and the industry in general understand platforms, and specifically pricing on platforms. It was developed in conjunction with Platforum, who became for a while the touch point for discussion and change of ideas in this important field. Comparator continues to be the industry standard. Whereas there are a couple of imitators out there, comparisons prove time and again that it is the Synaptic data and methodology that is consistently matching the Providers’ own calculations (the others do not). Comparator analyses Platforms, but includes off platform products too.Thesoftwareallows‘generic’chargingtobeinputwhererequired,toallow ranking alongside the more widely available investment options.Such is the ease-of-use of the tool, that we feel that there is a case for a Comparator report to accompany each recommendation. The FCA is making proof of Suitability the key requirement of advice, and has reiterated the need to achieve this at a client level. In the recent thematic review paper, 'Assessing suitability: research and due diligence', the emphasis was on creating a ‘culture of challenge’ where research was used to ensure price was always examined to guarantee value for money for clients.Even where a single platform is used in a practice, and a Central Investment Proposition accessed in most cases, Comparator can be used to establish value for money. If you don’t look, you can’t form a view. If you haven’t got a view, you can’t be sure that you are working to your clients’ best interests, or therefore confident in your compliance.Screenshot of Comparator research provides an illustration for a £150k pension over a 20 year term. Full adviser charging analysis is available, as is off platform options. Pricing is accurateat platform, product and share class level. The reduction in yield figures that are produced offer the ‘single solutions cost’, like for like comparison required by the FCA.For more information about Synaptic Comparator, please visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 4477 to arrange a short demo.Article is adapted from Financial Planner Magazine publication.]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[36SYNAPTICManaging Risk:A clear winner is emerging for advisersEric Armstrong | Product Marketing | Synaptic Software LimitedIt can be unnerving to read that investors like Odey are positioned for a slump ‘of up to 80%’ in UK equities, or that sovereign bonds have absolutely arrived at the bottom of their 35 year trajectory (except they haven’t?). When we consider macro themes of energy, trade, technology, health, retail, anti-globalilsation, European disintegration, American protectionism, Chinese expansionism, Russian aggression, corporate bond liquidity, duration risk ... plotting a sensible investment path for your clients is anything but simple.This is one area where your firm cannot afford to settle for second best. Which is why Synaptic have built a risk management solution for advisers around the Moody’s Analytics, industry - leading risk framework.Creating an investment strategyYou have to have a system for evaluating risk. The recent Thematic Review Paper identified poor Risk profiling as one of the causes of ‘poor outcomes’ for customers. The ‘Finalised guidance’ blockbuster from 2011 titled ‘Assessing suitability’ stated that you must be able to ‘establish the risk a customer is willing to take’. The paper warns you in no uncertain terms that you must have tools that you understand and can operate effectively, and an approach that can explain the dynamics of risk and investment to a client –but the paper won’t tell you how to do it. A major part of the challenge is to ensure that ‘investment selection is consistent with the customer’s risk category description’.You will always hear people in our industry discuss risk as a ‘conversation’. This is because there are no absolute truths, thereis only a framework to work from, and the acknowledgement that clients need to understand how risk can work in their favour. It boils down to whether you as an adviser can prove ‘Suitability’, and irrespective of how the investment pans out, whether the risks were correctly assessed and explained to the client at the outset.The Synaptic Risk proposition aims to solve a couple of the thorny problems associated with creating a consistent investment strategy. One is ensuring that the elements relate correctly to each other:- The Attitude to Risk Questionnaire. This must be predicated on research of statistical significance to anchor your client in a recognisable comparative framework;- Risk Categories. In our case 5 categories Cautious through Adventurous. In fact, the Synaptic system offers a 50 category risk proposition (if you take into account the decimalisation. e.g. 2.2 and 2.3 exist);- Strategic Asset Allocations. These define portfolio construction and define risk levels;- Suitable investments. Easily assessed in terms of their risk suitability.The Synaptic Risk proposition brings Moody’s Analytics to the adviser’s desktop, offering the most effective system available. There are many reasons why Moody’s lead this field, but let me throw a couple at you:- The system offers a consistent measure for downside (drawdown) risk in the form of a single figure. You can then say to your client, that ‘in a bad year’, say 1 in 20, you could lose 5.5% or more of your portfolio. This approach is consistent with the FCA’s doctrine of ‘Capacity for Loss’;- All the metrics from this system come from analysis of asset allocations. Possible growth trajectories are mapped according to probability, so that they can be discussed sensibly with clients;- Moody’s not only have the most credible assumptions and expert input into the model (again proven empirically over the years), but the most sophisticated modelling. The Moody’s approach is different to others]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTICas it employs mathematical rules that ensure that economic risk factors such as interest rates and asset prices cannot diverge over the long term in a way which would not be economically plausible. Moody’s model the irregular returns of asset prices using atechnique called ‘Stochastic Volatility Jump Diffusion’ to represent equity market ‘fat tails’ (sequence of return risk);- Other propositions tend to try to paper over the cracks with ‘bolt-ons’ and furtherqualification to their ‘qualitative overlays’. The latter provides one essential dimension to the risk assessment, but the quantitative dimension offered by the Monte Carlo based projections of the Moody’s stochastic model offers its truest foundation.The table shows the Synaptic Investment Strategy. Min, ave and max gains indicate the extent of the loss in any 1 year period. As the reading from the model’s 95th percentile, this can be read as the ‘worst loss’ to be sustained in 20 years (5%), thus quantifying risk in a comparable measure. The model is reviewed quarterly. gSynaptic Investment strategy (Moody’s Analytics)Strategic Asset AllocationClassesMin GainAverage GainMax GainCautiousCash 50.00%UK Corporate Bonds 29.00% UK Equities 8.00%Global Equities (ex UK) 7.00% Global Property 6.00%-5.58%4.88%15.27%Moderately CautiousUK Corporate Bonds 55.00% UK Equities 15.00%Global Equities (ex UK) 14.00% Global Property 12.00%Cash 4.00%-10.97%6.01%22.77%BalancedUK Corporate Bonds 36.00% Global Equities (ex UK) 30.00% UK Equities 20.00%Global Property 9.00%Emerging Markets Equities 5.00%-15.54%6.99%28.14%Moderately AdventurousGlobal Equities (ex UK) 43.00% UK Equities 24.00%UK Corporate Bonds 20.00% Emerging Markets Equities 7.00% Global Property 6.00%-18.63%7.65%33.00%AdventurousGlobal Equities (ex UK) 61.00% UK Equities 29.00%Emerging Markets Equities 10.00%-24.18%8.53%40.71%This table shows how popular multi- asset investments appearin some of our customers’fund assessments. tMin gainAve gainMax gainHenderson MM Absolute Return-8.493.4815.32Moderately Cautious2.5Vanguard Life Strategy 20%-9.773.4618.87Moderately Cautious2.7Jupiter Merlin Conservative-10.93.7920.14Moderately Cautious2.9Architas MA Active Intermediate Inc-11.944.3921.3Balanced3.2L&G Multi Index 5-13.234.8723.18Balanced3.4Standard Life Myfolio Managed 3-13.244.6922.62Balanced3.4Old Mutual Spectrum 6-17.026.0630.68Moderately Adventurous4.4Register to the Synaptic Risk service today, including access to the Attitude to Risk Questionnaire for FREE. Visit www.synaptic.co.uk or call 0800 783 447737]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[F&C MM Lifestyle Foundation 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Defensive Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Cautious Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Balanced Fund 1 F&C MM Lifestyle Growth Fund 1 Pyrford Global Total Return (Sterling) 1 F&C MM Navigator Distribution 1 F&C MM Navigator Moderate 1 F&C MM Navigator Progressive 1 F&C MM Navigator Select 1 F&C MM Navigator Boutiques 1CF Canlife Portfolio III 1 CF Canlife Portfolio IV 1 CF Canlife Portfolio V 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VI 1 CF Canlife Portfolio VII 1 Canlife Portfolio 3 1 Canlife Portfolio 4 1 Canlife Portfolio 5 1 Canlife Portfolio 6 1 Canlife Portfolio 7 12 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 32 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Cautious MPS 1 Income MPS 1 Balanced MPS 1 Growth MPS 1 Global Equity MPS 1Close Bond Income Portfolio Fund 1 Close Diversified Income Portfolio Fund 1 Close Conservative Portfolio Fund 1 Close Balanced Portfolio Fund 1 Close Growth Portfolio Fund 1 Close Managed Income Fund 1 Close Managed Conservative Fund 1 Close Managed Balanced Fund 1 Close Managed Growth Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Conservative Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Balanced Fund 1 Close Tactical Select Passive Growth Fund 1 Close DMS Income Plus 1 Close DMS Conservative 1 Close DMS Balanced 1 Close DMS Growth 12 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 52 3 4 5CautiousModerately CautiousBalanced Moderately AdventurousAdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis:Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Multi-Index 3 Multi-Index 4 Multi-Index 5 Multi-Index 6 Multi-Index 7 Multi-Index Income 4 Multi-Index Income 5 Mulit-index Income 61 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 5Diversified Income FundDiversified Growth Fund 1 2 3 4 5 MAP 12345 Managed Growth Fund 1 2 3 4 5 Investec Cautious Managed Fund 1 2 3 4 512345M&G Episode Allocation Fund M&G Episode Income Fund M&G Episode Growth Fund M&G Global Dividend Fund M&G Property Portfolio1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 5MP3 12345 MP50 12345 MP4 12345 MP5 12345 MP6 12345 MP7 12345Adventurous Portfolio Income Seeker Portfolio Growth Seeker Portfolio Income Focus Portfolio Temperate Portfolio Growth Focus Portfolio Lower Risk Income Portfolio Lower Risk Growth Portfolio Protective Portfolio1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[PortfoliosPremier Capital Builder Portfolio Premier Capital Builder Plus Portfolio Premier Income and Growth Portfolio Premier Income PortfolioPremier Conservative Portfolio Premier High Income Portfolio Premier Balanced PortfolioPremier Balanced Plus Portfolio Premier Growth PortfolioPremier Growth Plus Portfolio Premier Dynamic Growth Portfolio1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5PruFund CautiousPruFund Protected Cautious PruFund GrowthPruFund Protected Growth PruFund 0-30PruFund 10-40PruFund 20-55PruFund 40-80Dynamic 0-30Dynamic 10-40Dynamic 20-55Dynamic 40-80Dynamic 60-100WP Optimum Return Focused 0-30Focused 10-40Focused 20-55Focused 40-80Focused 60-1001 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5FundsPremier Liberation IV FundPremier Liberation V FundPremier Liberation VI FundPremier Liberation VII FundPremier Multi-Asset Conservative Growth Premier Multi-Asset Absolute Return Fund Premier Multi-Asset Distribution Fund Premier Multi-Asset Monthly Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Growth & Income Fund Premier Multi-Asset Global Growth Fund Premier UK Money Market FundPremier Defensive Growth FundPremier Corporate Bond Monthly Income Fund Premier Diversified Fund1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 512345Cautious Moderately Cautious Balanced Moderately Adventurous AdventurousSynaptic Risk Rating based on following analysis: Strategic Asset Allocation Tactical Asset Allocation]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[RMAP Total Return RMAP Strategic Growth RMAP Enhanced Growth RMAP Strategic Income Strategy 1Strategy 2Strategy 3Strategy 4Strategy 5Strategy 61 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5MPS Global Growth MPS GrowthMPS BalancedMPS Global Income MPS IncomeMPS ConservativeMPS CautiousMPS Global Growth (Platform) MPS Growth (Platform)MPS Balanced (Platform)MPS Global Income (Platform) MPS Income (Platform)MPS Conservative (Platform) IDX Growth (Platform)IDX Balanced (Platform)IDX Income (Platform)IDX Conservative (Platform)1 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 512345RL Governed Portfolio 1 RL Governed Portfolio 2 RL Governed Portfolio 3 RL Governed Portfolio 4 RL Governed Portfolio 5 RL Governed Portfolio 6 RL Governed Portfolio 7 RL Governed Portfolio 8 RL Governed Portfolio 9 RLGRIP1RLGRIP2 RLGRIP3 RLGRIP4 RLGRIP5(l)(s) (l)(s) (l)(s)1 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51 2 3 4 51234512345123451234512345Conservative Portfolio Defensive Portfolio Moderate Portfolio Progressive Portfolio Positive PortfolioPositive Plus Portfolio Adventurous Portfolio Adventurous Plus Portfolio1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Access the Synaptic Risk Fact Sheets and the Synaptic Attitude to Risk Questionnaire by visiting www.synaptic.co.uk/research-tools/synaptic-risk]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Schroder MM DiversitySchroder MM Diversity Balanced Schroder MM Diversity Income Schroder MM Diversity Tactical Schroder MM International Schroder MM UK GrowthSchroder Mixed Distribution Fund Schroder Global Multi Asset Income Schroder Dynamic Multi Asset Schroder Managed BalancedVanguard LifeStrategy 20% Vanguard LifeStrategy 40% Vanguard LifeStrategy 60% Vanguard LifeStrategy 80% Vanguard LifeStrategy 100%1 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Cautious / Personal Injury Moderately Cautious IncomeBalancedModerately Adventurous AdventurousACUMEN Conservative Portfolio ACUMEN Income Portfolio ACUMEN Progressive Portfolio ACUMEN Adventerous Portfolio ACUMEN PROFILE 3ACUMEN PROFILE 4 ACUMEN PROFILE 5 ACUMEN PROFILE 6 ACUMEN PROFILE 7 ACUMEN PROFILE 8 TW PROFILE 3TW PROFILE 4TW PROFILE 5TW PROFILE 6TW PROFILE 7TW PROFILE 8 Tavistock PROFILE 3 Tavistock PROFILE 4 Tavistock PROFILE 5 Tavistock PROFILE 6 Tavistock PROFILE 7 Tavistock PROFILE 81 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5]]></page><page Index="43" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Verbatim PortfoliosFP Verbatim Portfolio 3FP Verbatim Portfolio 4FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Growth FP Verbatim Portfolio 5 Income FP Verbatim Portfolio 6FP Verbatim Portfolio 71 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 5Verbatim VDSVDSJH3 12345 VDSJH4 12345 VDSJH5 12345 VDSJH6 12345 VDSJH7 12345 VDSJH8 12345 VDSRSM2 12345 VDSRSM3 12345 VDSRSM4 12345 VDSRSM5 12345 VDSRSM6 12345 VDSRSM7 12345 VDSRSM8 12345 VDSRSM9 12345 VDSRSM10 12345 VDSTCF3 12345 VDSTCF4 12345 VDSTCF5 12345 VDSTCF6 12345 VDSTCF7 12345 VDSTCF8 12345 VDSS&W3 12345 VDSS&W4 12345 VDSS&W5 12345 VDSS&W6 12345 VDSS&W7 12345 VDSS&W8 12345 VSDHR3 12345 VSDHR4 12345 VSDHR5 12345 VSDHR6 12345 VSDHR7 12345 VSDHR8 12345Verbatim RSMRRSM Model Portfolio 2 RSM Model Portfolio 3 RSM Model Portfolio 4 RSM Model Portfolio 5 RSM Model Portfolio 6 RSM Model Portfolio 7 RSM Model Portfolio 8 RSM Model Portfolio 9 RSM Model Portfolio 101 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 54 5Total Clarity Portfolio 3 Total Clarity Portfolio 4 Total Clarity Portfolio 5 Total Clarity Portfolio 61 2 31 2 31 2 34 54 54 5Verbatim Total Clarity12345(s) These portfolios were constructed with short investment timelines (5 year) in mind.(l) These portfolios were constructed with longer investment timelines (15 year) in mind. Otherwise Synaptic Risk Ratings assume a 10 year investment horizon. You should consult Royal London directly for further informationbefore recommending.About the service: Synaptic Risk Ratings are worked out by analysing the underlying asset classes within the fund or portfolio. Synaptic Software have requested asset allocation information from participating providers in a specific format aligned to the risk framework of the system. These asset classes are used by the model to determine the risk rating, a process that may result in a level of approximation though in most cases this will be insignificant. It is also possible that certain asset classes may not be represented exactly in the manner that providers would prefer.Reasonable endeavours are made to provide accuracy and consistency, however neither participating providers nor Synaptic Software can be held responsible for any errors or omissions. No recommendation should be made solely on the basis of the Synaptic Risk Ratings, and additional research should be undertaken for any case. This service is intended for use by investment professionals only.]]></page><page Index="44" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[44SYNAPTICSynaptic –Customer Experience Health CheckTiina Stephens | Operations Manager | Synaptic Software LimitedIn the last edition of Connection, we announced our plans to work with an independent Customer Experience consultancy Investor in Customers to assess our product and service offering. We have now completed the assessment phase and you have spoken.Weareextremelypleasedtoannouncethat your feedback has improved substantially year on year and this year has seen our best ever score from our customers – you.What next?We pledge to analyse the feedback you have given us, contact a few of you to clarify comments, and build the feedback into our 2017 product and service strategy. We strive to continuously improve our product and service offerings to provide you with the best possible customer experience.TheInvestorinCustomersannualassessment is based on feedback from clients and staff. The four assessment areas;• understanding customer needs,• delivering products and services which meetthose needs,• delivering first class service • engendering loyaltyHow do we support our customers?Our customer feedback programme is not only an annual survey, but an ongoing conversation.OurCustomerService teamwillcontactyou from time to time, to make sure you are happy with your purchase and to ask for any feedback you may have. Nowhere is this more important than in the constantly evolving arena of financial services. It is our business and our desire to know how the software we provide fits in with your business model, or more importantly, where it falls short.Our Relationship team spend many hours on the road visiting your offices in orderto understand your needs as a customer and ensure you get the best out of the software packages. Here at Synaptic we pride ourselves on working closely with you as a key business partner ensuring your compliance and service requirements are met using the Synaptic Suite.Our products are intuitive, allowing users to easily get to grips and become effective members of your team quickly. The user experience is enhanced by our training proposition, which is best placed to offer“We were amazed by the Synaptic trainer’s knowledge of the product and the ability to help us to improve our processes. The training day was great for all the participants!”]]></page><page Index="45" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC45We are extremely pleased to announce your feedback has improved substantially year on year and this year has seen our best ever score from our customers – thank you.you and your staff the most convenientand relevant training package and method should you need it. We offer all new users complimentary virtual training as we want to ensure that all users get the most out of our software. Our Application Support Technicians are on hand to answer any queries you might have about our software, and our Research Specialists ensure the content of the solution you use is continuously up to date.Our product and service offering places the customer at the centre of our strategy. We are continuously striving to offer the best value proposition to match the specific needs of today’s changing landscape. Althoughwe think our software and source code are pretty valuable to us, our biggest asset by any measure is our people who make all of this happen. All of us at Synaptic strive to push the boundaries every day to provide you with a first class service. Our vision for our service strategy is to be the best.How are we planning to change?Change is inevitable, we like to think that where we do not wait around to be changed, but proactively change things to foster innovation and problem solving. We strive to find areas where we can add further value for our customers, helping you to be the most efficient you can be and provide great outcomes for all. Our most enthusiastic problem solvers can be found behind thedriving seat of our product strategy; these people have the right industry experience, so they know the pain points and have plenty of fantastic ideas on how to make our customers’ lives that much easier.This said, we do not know everything and that is why we continuously engage with our customers in order to keep our finger on the pulse.A snapshot of the current thoughts across our customer base provides us with great insight on how we can improve the value and the outcomes for our customers. The Investorin Customers assessment is our annual medical health check to assess the impactof the continuous improvement activity and development of our value proposition. Once more thank you for your invaluable feedback; it will enable us to become fitter and better placed to continue to improve your customer experience.Thank you to everyone who gave us someof their valuable time to provide feedback, a magnum of champagne is on its way to one lucky respondent.“I met with our Synaptic Relationship Manager yesterdayfor our usual quarterly update meeting. I was singing Synaptic praises in how reliable their system has been for the last 12 months. We’ve worked with Synaptic now for over 2 years and I could not recommendthem enough.”]]></page><page Index="46" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Enjoy an easy life with WeblineBuying financial products online has never been easier with the help of the Synaptic Webline portal, which can be accessed forNot only can you compare hundreds of online products against each other, you can also apply online directly into the chosen providers extranet, reducing time and effort usually spent re-keying data.By applying directly from Synaptic Webline firms may be entitled to an extra 10% of additional commission –For more information call us on0800 783 4477 or visit us at www.synaptic.co.ukApplying Online - The Myths and Facts• The cost for applying via Webline is exactly the same astrading with the Provider on their site.• Webline portal will take a cut of the plan commission due to the adviser.• Applying via Webline means the data from the quote is populated, avoiding double data entry.• Application process cannot be re-started from within Webline service.• The Providers treat the application in exactly the same way as an application coming in via their extranet.• Advisers are often entitled up to an additional 10%commission when applying from Webline into provider extranet.• The client data is not kept by Webline, the application is input directly onto the provider’s system.• There is no cost to you or the client for sending the application in via Webline.Free to existing customersthis could result in huge gainsyou could even earn more commissionFact MythFactFact MythFact FactFact]]></page><page Index="47" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[47Time to look beyond priceFiona Holmes | Proposition Communications Manager | Royal LondonIn the past the protection insurance sector wasn’t known for innovation, embracing technology or making the most of digital capabilities. But we’re gradually seeing this changing in the form of some game- changing FinTech companies, such as the re-insurer backed start-up UnderwriteMe.Royal London was one of the first providersin the UK to start using this platform, which lets insurers retain their underwriting rules and products whilst letting advisers and customers compare costs from a range of insurers. This enables them to get quotes and select the product they want to buy in a simple end-to- end process. By setting realistic expectations of premiums and giving them underwriting decisions up-front, systems like UnderwriteMe are set to significantly improve the customer journey – for both advisers and their clients.A major aspect of this new way of underwriting that’s very close to my heart is that customers can see the value and benefits that sit behind each proposition. So rather than choosingon price alone, customers can compare products based on added value benefits. We’ve been operating in a market that’s been predominately price driven for years so it’s great news to see this kind of progress.Focusing on client needsOf course affordability will always be important. But shouldn’t the initial focus be on what clients can’t afford to be without when it comes to making a claim, rather than what they can afford now? With continued pressure on the financial services industry toensure quality of advice, products that come with additional added value benefits shouldn’t be ignored.Currently, added value services are often seen as an afterthought with the main message still being very much about the financial benefit. But someone coming to terms with a cancer diagnosis will be feeling numb, speechless and in desperate need of some emotional support. Money, although a crucial consideration going forward, is one of the last things likely to spring to mind when digesting the idea that they could actually be paying the ultimate price. Indeed, in our experience it’s not uncommon for plan holders to take a few weeks to come to terms with their situation before they even get around to contacting us to make a claim.With changes in NHS legislation and budget cuts being felt in primary care trusts, more and more people are being forced to waitor look for help elsewhere. If a protection product additional benefit is available that automatically offers impartial support and advice that addresses these needs as part of the plan, then why not embrace it?Support you can’t put a price onOur Helping Hand service provides access to a personal nurse adviser, a second medical opinion, complementary therapies to assist recovery and access to personal, legal and medical helplines as well as bereavement counselling. The depth of services available provides access to all the counselling and helpline services you’d expect but, more importantly, it’s designed to help peoplerecover. It’s available as soon as someone takes out a plan and they don’t need to claim to use the service.Interestingly, some claimants have said they value their nurse advisers primarily just as someone to talk to at a difficult time. But, regardless of the way in which they feel they have most benefited, one comment Helping Hand users consistently volunteer is that they ‘simply cannot put a price’ on the support they received. Indeed, many of our claimants that have used the service told us that they value this more than the pay-out they received. So perhaps it’s time to look beyond the price and give clients cover that counts. And that means not just supporting them financially at their time of need, but emotionally too.Showing the value of your adviceWhen survival rates are constantly improving due to advances in medical science, helping clients on the road to recovery is another way for you to show the value of your service.It also shows you have fully considered your clients’ financial and emotional needs, emphasising the value of buying protection with advice.Many advisers would argue they alreadytake a holistic approach to protection, but given the complexity of products and the frequent changes in definitions, advisers are often forced to return to price as the selection criteria. But I believe innovative technology is set to change that.This is a Royal London promotion.Rather than choosing on price alone, customers can compare products based on added value benefits.]]></page><page Index="48" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[48New occupation trends are emerging, do we have them covered?Nick Jones | Brand and Marketing Manager | The ExeterNick Jones from The Exeter explores how income protection needs to be flexible to the changing needs of a modern workforce.As insurers, it’s too easy to get bogged down by product, product, product. Charts of features, star ratings, ticks and crosses, all comparing the minutiae of our relative propositions.If we’re not careful, we’ll overlook themost important feature of all to our future success – customers. Our customers’ lives are changing all the time, but do we always reflect their changing needs in our thinking and indeed in our propositions? The make- up of the working population in the UK has been a big topic for debate in recent weeks.Self-employed workers on the riseCover Magazine was one of many sources to report that the population of self- employed workers is on the rise, with some worrying statistics showing how they are not prioritising protection insurance for their families:• Two thirds of self-employed workers’ households are reliant on one income• 4.3 million have no protection in place if they were unable to work due to illnessBut, has this changing need been reflected in the protection market? Probably not, but progress is being made.Income protection is typically the most important form of financial protection for self-employed workers, who often have limited or no sick pay arrangements. But this is a group that has been underserved by the market until recent years.Friendly Societies, including The Exeter with our newly enhanced Pure Protection Plus product, have proved that regardless of risk – self-employed workers in manual and physical roles can secure quality protection that works for them. So, what makes our proposition different to that of mainstream insurers?• Waiting periods start from Day 1, so consumers can protect their savings from the very start of their illness or injury• Applicants have options to fix their benefit, which makes claiming easier and is particularly valuable to protect against a fluctuating income• Your clients have a wide range of price points to choose from – from reviewable to guaranteed premiums or short term payment period options, making cover more affordableBut moving away from product features, are we doing enough as providers to engage self- employed clients in protection insurance?Our customers’ lives are changing allthe time, but do we always reflect their changing needs in our thinking and indeed in our propositions?Source: Scottish Widows research]]></page><page Index="49" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[49At The Exeter we also produce real life claims stories about our self-employed customers, helping advisers make a case for IP and opening their clients’ minds to the need for income protection.7 Families was a feel-good initiative that proved how storytelling and the useof video case studies can draw in and engage an audience. At The Exeter we also produce real life claims stories about our self-employed customers, helping advisers make a case for IP and opening their clients’ minds to the need for income protection.Interactive tools also help. The Exeter’s Financial Forecast Calculator highlights the potential shortfall self-employed workers would face if they had to rely on sick pay from the Government alone. Offering something visual often works better than words alone – encouraging participation and ‘buy in’ from the client.One area I think as insurers we can improve on is engaging clients who have already bought protection. The use of annual statements to remind them of the value of their policies has long been discussed, but without the role of an adviser – are clients likely to review their cover every year? This is particularly important for self-employed clients with a changeable income and is probably an area we still need to be better at as an industry.The ‘independent workforce’ – a cause for concern?Another emerging occupation trend is the rise of the ‘independent workforce’,individuals who earn their income outside of traditional employee roles.Reported on the BBC following research from global consultants McKinsey, it is estimated that almost five million people in the UK are employed in this way.Perhaps the best current example is Deliveroo – the on-demand restaurant delivery service that employs a self-employed army to deliver food by cycle or scooter.On the plus side, this is a flexible, casual way for many workers to supplement their income, or even derive a primary incomefrom if the hours are there to support it. On the down side, this is a job that’s high in risk but low in employee security. With no sick pay to fall back on if illness or injury strikes, it would leave many in a very difficult position if they were unable to work.Income protection and the modern workforceIncome protection could prove invaluable for independent workers like Deliveroo couriers, just as it can for the millions of self-employed workers in the UK.The challenge for insurers is to make income protection a product that is relevant and engaging for a workforce that is changing all the time, has very different needs to those of yesterday and is looking for a policy that suits them as an individual and grows and adapts as their working life changes.Many of the fundamentals are in place – we just need to keep striving for simplicity, clarity and better ways to engage a wider audience in the importance of this valuable form of cover. As is often the case, there are some insurers set up better to achieve this than others, at The Exeter we like to think we’re one.Discover The Exeter’s new range of income protection products.Watch the launch video now at www.the-exeter.com/plus-productsThe challenge for insurers is to make income protection a product thatis relevant and engaging for a workforce that is changing all the time.]]></page><page Index="50" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[50Page needs logo and brand colThe truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truthAndrew Wibberley | Director | Alea RiskFraud. Misrepresentation. Non-disclosure. An innocent mistake.Whatever the headline, insurance policiesthat don’t pay are bad news for everyone. The individual who doesn’t have the help they need when they need it suffers the most. But the insurers disappointing customers and facing appeals, costs and media questions also get profoundly damaged by every unpaid claim.Beneath the claims payout statistics are many confused and disappointed people. Some have photogenic families and media connections, others may suffer in silence, but all have lessons we need to learn from.We pay 100% of valid claimsThe fiercely held view of many experienced insurance professionals is that black is black, white is white and once you’ve worked out which side of the line the claim fits, your job is done. Insurers aren’t charities. The claims process is as simple as looking at the claimant’s policy conditions, the questions they answered and the reason for the claim they are now making.There’s an attractiveness to the belligerent certainty of people who take this line - but I’m not convinced. I have seen too many poorly worded condition definitions, too manyunclear application questions, and too many questionable sales processes to truly believe in it.Ultimately I don’t think it matters how many valid claims we pay. The true measure has to be how many genuinely disappointed families there are, and how many people aren’t getting the protection they need because of our reputation.Questions on questionsImproving the questions and processes of any application is key to handing over fewer problems to claimants and claims assesssors in the next generation. These are some ideas for achieving this:Questions – Whose job is it anyway?It is the insurers job to ask the questions, the advisers / sales persons job to ask them and the applicants job to answer them?Let underwriters underwrite, advisers advise (or sales people sell) and customers buy. If the underwriters asked about something, tell them about it. Bore them silly – but don’t make the decision that “it was all OK” for them.The headache that the adviser says “not to worry about”, and the tingling the customer doesn’t want to waste people's time talking about are things that the underwriter needs to know about – if only to discount.Equally, don’t tell the underwriter things they haven’t asked about. It will only confuse them, and slow down the process. If they haven’t asked about your hobbies, your family history or your medical history in childhood then you do not need to tell them. The product youare buying is priced on honest answers to the questions that are being asked.Questions – What does good look like?The number of questions in an application process remains the primary focus in insurance office development meetings. This baffles me as when listening to customer calls I hear them ask “How long will this take?” far more often than “How many multi-bulleted questions will I have to answer?” Having the time to complete at the front of mind is likely to lead to shorter, more concise questions that help the customer understand what is being asked.o]]></page><page Index="51" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ours51We have to better demonstrate that we are capable of providing a fair way for people to get the cover they need without fear of it failing them when they need it.There are many short sets of questions that rely on catch-all questions that would take much longer to honestly and fully answer than longer, more defined question sets. The fact that insurers know this, but persist on pursuing this route, suggests they are complicit in creating an environment where misrepresentation occurs.Questions – You’re OK, aren’t you? v Are you OK?There are many ways that we could ask questions more intuitively to the customer. Trying to speak to them as you would in conversation is a start. Most people over 50 are likely to be on some sort of medication – so why not phrase the question in that way:“What medication are you currently taking?” (with an option to say none) rather than the more common: “Do you currently take any medication?” (with a follow up if you say yes).Questions – Where are you?A big change that has taken place over the last generation is the location people are in when completing their insurance application. Being aware that people are no longer sat opposite an IFA is important. How differently should we treat people answering our sacred questions online, or on the phone – or more relevantly in an open plan office, on the train or on the toilet?This is before we consider the context of the protection application in the applicant’s day. Many questions are answered after an hour completing a mortgage – a time when most people would say anything to be let free. Isit fair for us to ignore this context when making a judgment later on the honesty of the customer?Questions – Who are you?It is still considered scarily innovative to ask a 25 year old different questions to those you ask a 70 year old. In the future, questions that flex dependent on what you already know about the customer from a variety of sources willbecome commonplace. This can then be used to further drive down price, to reduce the time spent on the application process or to make the whole process more seamless.The ultimate answer – non- contestability?Many understandably tire of the nuances of the above and revert to the principle that “insurers should pay all claims”. Stop the wriggling and pay everything.I believe that if insurers and distributors do their jobs properly, then the fairest market is one without non-contestability. Non-contestability in its purest form gives no incentive for people to be honest, and therefore means premiums for all increasing disproportionately to the true risk they are facing.Nevertheless the threat of non-contestability should be another shove to everyone interested to further improve questions (and condition wordings and claims processes). We have to better demonstrate that we are capable of providing a fair way for people to get the cover they need, without fear of it failing them when they need it.Improving the questions and processes of any application is key to handing over fewer problems to claimants and claims assesssors in the next generation.]]></page><page Index="52" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[52The rise of more affordable Income ProtectionJustin Harper | Head of Marketing & Industry Relations | LV=According to the latest Swiss Re Term & Health Watch report, protection sales were pretty much flat when comparing 2015 to the previous year. Yet there was a particular bright spot; sales of individual Income Protection (IP) policies rose by over 10%.And when you dig a little deeper behind the 10% growth in IP, there is a real shining star, limited payment term IP, which now accounts for nearly 4 in every 10 IP sales ... with year on year sales rising an impressive 20%+.Why is this type of IP rising in popularity? The answer lies in a combination of factors, but with one we believe offers a clear and tangible difference (to full IP) ... cost.For example, a two-year limited payment term IP with LV= is generally about half the price of full IP.Income Protection is expensive ... or is it?Research indicates that consumers vastly over inflate the perceived cost of insurance. In fact, some people overestimate the cost of basic life assurance by as much as four times. IP does cost more than life or critical illness cover, and the reason is simple ... the risk of falling ill and being off work isfar higher than suffering a serious illness or dying. And the illusion of value is further distorted with IP, because the client isn’t paid a lump sum, but receives the benefit in monthly instalments until their return to work or the policy ends. But IP doesn’t have to be ‘expensive’.Tailor a solution to your clientOur analysis of quotes on portals indicates that many advisers quote for maximum benefits. And that’s a great place to start – but it’s a not a ‘take it or leave it’ offer.Action point! If affordability is an issue, you can choose a number of routes to adjust cover and reduce the cost to a more affordable level for your client.For example:• Choose a longer waiting period; we have a number of options ranging from four weeks to a year• Reduce the cover required; what monthlybenefit amount do they need?• Reduce the plan time length by choosing ashorter term; perhaps they only need cover for a particular time period, such as to coincide with the end of their mortgage.Limited payment term IP - a financial safety net your clients can depend onSometimes referred to as ‘budget IP’, limited payment term IP pays out for a maximum period per claim. The most common period chosen is two years, but there are options available for one, three and five years. And with most plans, your client can still make as many claims as they need to.The guaranteed premium examples opposite give you an indication of howLV= Budget Income Protection could make quality protection much more affordable for your cost conscious clients:]]></page><page Index="53" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[53Limited payment term IP, which now accounts for nearly 4 in every 10 IP sales ... with year on year sales rising an impressive 20%+.Example premiums - as at October 2016LV= Income protectionLV=Budget income protectionAge 35, non-smoker,office administrator, 6 month waiting period, guaranteed rates, £1,000 benefit a month, inflation linked, expiry age 65£22.77 a month£8.41 a monthSaving 63%Age 28, smoker,retail manager, 12 month waiting period, guaranteed rates, £1,000 benefit a month, inflation linked, expiry age 65£34.94 a month£9.88 a monthSaving 71%These quotes are based on our standard rates correct as at 24.10.16 and are subject to change. The actual savings for your client will depend on their individual circumstances.At LV=, we also offer a budget option of Personal Sick Pay – our IP policy designed for those in riskier more expensive to insure occupations, and the self-employed. And with LV= our budget plans offer all the same great features as our full IP - the only difference is the claim period.Action point! Look out for limited payment period IP options on the portals.Reinforcing the value of income ProtectionTo help position the importance of protecting income and bring alive the everyday risks your client may face, you can use the LV= Risk Reality Calculator.It doesn’t talk about products, just ‘risk’ and in a simple, personal and powerful way... simply enter a few client detailsand you can transform your protection conversations and readily position protecting income as the risk people should protect against.Action Point! Talk about protection with every client. Make protection instantly personal, immediate and real ... with the LV= Risk Reality Calculator.Visit www.riskreality.co.uk/gen. And it includes links to the 7Families films.Can your clients really afford not to?One of the most common objections we hear from advisers is that their clients can’t afford to take out income protection, or any protection for that matter, and that this can be a particular issue if clients have recently taken out a new mortgage.But with millions of people spending months or even years off work due to long-term sickness or injury, and the welfare reforms eroding state benefits with some of the biggest cuts for decades, how would your clients cope financially if this happened to them?The affordable answer might just lie in limited payment term Income Protection.Visit LV.com/adviserOne of the most common objections we hear from advisers is that their clients can’t afford to take out income protection, or any protection for that matter.]]></page><page Index="54" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[54SYNAPTIC5 great reasons to use Synaptic WeblineOur Multi-Benefit service creates opportunities for the adviser to display additional value to their clients,earn additional commission from additional cross sales, and reduce the administrative burden from writing multiple policies.Webline has a wide range of functionality to make comparing and applying for products online easy for advisers. Here are a few you may not be familiar with.Multi-BenefitThis powerful functionality will allow advisers to discuss with their customers the benefits of being fully protected, covering all their needs within the one plan, rather than focusing on the minimum life insurance to cover their mortgage.Our Multi-Benefit service creates opportunities for the adviser to display additional value to their clients, earn additional commission from additional cross sales, and reduce the administrative burden from writing multiple policies.The following Multi-Benefit products are available:• Aviva Life Protection Solutions •L&GMultiBenefit• Royal London Personal Menu Plan • VitalityLife MultibenefitAdvisers will be prompted to either produce a comparison for standalone products, or Multi-Benefit products from the outset. When selecting the standalone product comparison journey, Webline will also run a seriesof Multi-Benefit product comparisons allowing advisers to compare standalone products against the Multi-Benefit product offerings.Screenshot showing Multi-Benefit selectionsAnnuity Quick QuoteWith Webline’s market-leading and powerful annuity quoting functionality, you can produce up to 80 quotes in a matter of seconds.Webline’s user-friendly attitude towards web-based quotation and fulfilment services offers a “Quick Quote” function for annuities, which makes this already time-saving solution even faster! However, Webline still offers a detailed (CQRF) Annuity quoting function in addition to this, giving you the best of both worlds.All that is required is for you to fill out some very basic client details, the total fund/amount and, if required, the Escalation Type, Guaranteed Period and Widows Benefit (if quoting for a joint policy).Webline then returns up to 80 quotes to compare all of the different options available that meet your annuity quote criteria. Then simply “click” to turn options on or off, clearly displaying to your client how the various features can affect the value of their likely annuity rate.]]></page><page Index="55" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[SYNAPTIC55Income ProtectionWebline’s comprehensive Income Protection quote tool allows advisers to quote and compare 36 products from a panel of eleven providers.On top of this it provides you with a fully comprehensive matrix of up to 130 quotes, based on a number of flexible deferment period options. By selecting more than one deferment period option on the quote form, each provider will return quotes for the respective deferment periods (as shown below).This allows you to give your client the best deal possible based on their personal circumstances and needs.As with other quote forms on Webline, applying electronically isalso available when using the Income Protection tool. Select the premium from your chosen provider’s quote, and obtain a personalised illustration for your client. You may then apply online (or “retrieve” this quote, and apply later on) – again, using Webline means that muchof the client and product data already entered will be reused in the application itself, making life easier for you!So using Webline means there’s everything you need to provide income protection to your client from your PC or Tablet!Applying onlineBuying financial products online has never been easier with the help of Synaptic Webline.Not only does the Webline portal allow you to compare hundreds of online products against each other, you can also apply online directly on the chosen provider’s extranet, saving time and effort usually spent re-keying data.When using the portal, any client data that is captured in the service will be passed across into the chosen provider’s adviser extranet, pre- populating the application form.This online application functionality is available to every user who has a Webline account, and will be supported by providers that have online new business capability.And another reason... it’s free to existing Synaptic users!!Webline Registration Guide1. Browse to www.synaptic.co.uk2. Select Research tools from the menu at the top3. Select Webline Protection or Webline Annuities4. Select Register now on the chosen product area5. Complete account registration form. Once complete, select theRegister button to receive your online account details.6. Once you have completed your registration, your Synaptic WeblineWelcome Pack will be sent via email – this will include your personal logon details.Webline’s comprehensive Income Protection quote tool allows advisers to quote and compare 36 products from a panel of eleven providers.]]></page><page Index="56" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[Our Multi-Index Funds make it easier for you to get your ducks in a row.Active managementSimplicity Cost-effectiveness Ongoing suitabilityTelephone: 0345 070 8684* • fundsales@lgim.com www.lgim.com/ducksinarow • @LGIM #ducksinarowMulti-Index Fund RangeGiven the volatile undercurrents of today’s market, it’s easy for a static portfolio to drift off course. Our Multi-Index Funds however are risk-targeted and actively managed, ensuring they remain suitable to your clients, even when the market gets choppy. Yet because they’re largely made up of our index funds they remain simple. And, more importantly, cost effective. There are eight risk-targeted funds to choose from, focusing on either income or growth. The range has just celebrated its third anniversary and now has over £1bn under management. Multi-Index Funds.Your client’s portfolio stays serenely on course, because we’re doing the hard paddling beneath the surface.3 year anniversaryThis is not a consumer advertisement. It is intended for professional financial advisers and should not be relied upon by private investors or any other persons. The value of investments and any income from them may fall as well as rise, and investors may get back less than they invest. Exchange rate changes may cause the value of investments and the level of any income to rise and fall. Multi-Index funds are sensitive to interest rate changes. At times, especially over shorter timescales, lower risk rated funds may fall in value by more than higher risk rated funds. Details of the specific and general risks associated with the funds mentioned are contained within the Key Investor Information Documents. *Call charges will vary. Square Mile rating applies to Legal & General Multi-Index Funds only. Legal & General (Unit Trust Managers) Limited. Registered in England and Wales No. 1009418. Registered office: One Coleman Street, London, EC2R 5AA. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.]]></page></pages></Search>